<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;13 GROUPS OF DEITIES on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/13_GROUPS_OF_DEITIES/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;13 GROUPS OF DEITIES on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/13_GROUPS_OF_DEITIES/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 The Dual Deities</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/13_GROUPS_OF_DEITIES/1_The_Dual_Deities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/13_GROUPS_OF_DEITIES/1_The_Dual_Deities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THE type of the dual deities, who form quite a marked feature of the Rigveda in which some sixty hymns are addressed to such gods, is given by the pair Dyāvāpṛthivi, heaven and earth, the primeval parents. The two individual gods are comparatively little mentioned in comparison with the pair: Dyaus has no hymn, Pṛthivi one only, and the pair have six. Other names are Dyāvākṣāmā, Dyāvābhūmi or Rodasi, in which the male character of Dyaus, never perfectly established, has yielded to the prevailing femininity of Pṛthivi. The pair are two fathers, two mothers. They are the makers of all creatures, but also they are made by many individual gods, Indra, Viśvakarman, Tvaṣtṛ, or even produced from the sacrifice of the giant Puruṣa. One is a bull, the other a cow: they are unaging, they grant wealth, and are also wise and promote righteousness. They are also conceived as coming to the sacrifice or taking the sacrifice to the gods, but they are not of much importance in the ritual.1 They have, however, a hymn addressed to them in the Vaiśvadeva Śastra of the Agniṣṭoma, and an offering is made to them by the plougher, with the result that Parjanya sends him rain. The priests liken the two to the oblation holders or the earth to the altar, and the sky to the sacrificial fee.2&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2 Groups of Gods</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/13_GROUPS_OF_DEITIES/2_Groups_of_Gods/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/13_GROUPS_OF_DEITIES/2_Groups_of_Gods/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is a characteristic trait of the Rigveda that some forty hymns are devoted to the group of gods called All-gods, Viśve Devās, and the impression given by the Rigveda is borne out by the ritual in which the All-gods receive frequent attention.2 The fact must be carefully borne in mind in framing any theory as to the feeling of the poets as to the rank of the several gods: they must have known of these joint invocations, in which as many gods as possible are propitiated, and the same tendency to be catholic in the reverence&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
