<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;11 THE MINOR GODS OF NATURE on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/11_THE_MINOR_GODS_OF_NATURE/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;11 THE MINOR GODS OF NATURE on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/11_THE_MINOR_GODS_OF_NATURE/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 The Rbhus and the Ṛtus</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/11_THE_MINOR_GODS_OF_NATURE/01_The_Rbhus_and_the_Rtus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/11_THE_MINOR_GODS_OF_NATURE/01_The_Rbhus_and_the_Rtus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THE minor figures of the Vedic mythology are distinguished as a rule by the obscurity of their outlines: even when they are freely mentioned, as in the case of the Ṛbhus, it is a matter of the utmost difficulty to decide their precise character: it is probable indeed that in many cases the nature of the gods was little better understood by their worshippers than it is by us. Of this there is an excellent example in the Rbhus: they occur in eleven hymns in the Rigveda, being special favourites of the Bharadvāja family, and they are mentioned over a hundred times, but their mythical nature is very doubtful, and the Atharvaveda mentions them but eight times in seven hymns, and adds nothing to their character, indicating that in the popular side of the Vedic religion they had little hold.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>010 Constellations and Time Periods</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/11_THE_MINOR_GODS_OF_NATURE/10_Constellations_and_Time_Periods/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/11_THE_MINOR_GODS_OF_NATURE/10_Constellations_and_Time_Periods/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is a certain curious paucity of evidence of worship of constellations other than the sun and the moon, especially in its connexion with Soma,&amp;quot; and the planets seem to have attracted little notice. Whether we believe or not that they were known to the Vedic Indians, at any rate it is obvious that they received no direct worship in the period of the Rigveda, and it is not until the close of the Vedic ritual that we have enumerations of them such as that of the Baudhāyana Dharma Sūtra,10 which gives in a late passage sun, moon, Añgāraka, Budha, Bṛhaspati, Śukra, Śanaiścara, Rāhu and Ketu. Planetary&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 The Gandharvas and the Apsarases</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/11_THE_MINOR_GODS_OF_NATURE/02_The_Gandharvas_and_the_Apsarases/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/11_THE_MINOR_GODS_OF_NATURE/02_The_Gandharvas_and_the_Apsarases/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the Rigveda the word Gandharva occurs twenty times, but only thrice in the plural, from which it is fair to deduce that the nature of the spirit was originally conceived as one. What is still more important is that it occurs but once in book ii-vii, and is found twice in the eighth book as a being hostile to Indra. The epithet viṭvāvasu, &amp;lsquo;possessing all good things&amp;rsquo;, which accompanies it, appears once in the Rigveda 1 itself, and often later, to denote a definite individual. The Gandharva of that text is a high being of the air of the sky, a measurer of space who stands erect on the vault of heaven. He is brought into relation with the sun, the sun-bird, the sun-steed, and Soma likened to the sun. He is also connected with the rainbow in a late hymn.* He is, however, especially connected with Soma, whose place he guards, standing on the vault of heaven. Kṛśanu, the archer, who shoots at the eagle which steals the Soma, is expressly said in a later text to be a Gandharva. But the Gandharva is also connected with the waters: Soma in the waters is said to be the Gandharva of the waters: the parents of Yama and Yami are the Gandharva and the maiden of the waters: the Gandharva is the lover of the Apsaras. The Gandharva is further found in the marriage ceremony: the bride is claimed by him, and he is in the beginning of the marriage a rival of the husband. Further the Gandharva has a fragrant&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Spirits of the Forest, the Trees, and the Plants</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/11_THE_MINOR_GODS_OF_NATURE/03_Spirits_of_the_Forest_the_Trees_and_the_Plants/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/11_THE_MINOR_GODS_OF_NATURE/03_Spirits_of_the_Forest_the_Trees_and_the_Plants/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;5&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The references to the worship of the tree and the plants are very scanty in the Vedic ritual and mythology alike, but they are quite adequate to show that as among all other peoples these objects were not without their share of reverence. A long hymn in the last book of the Rigveda is devoted to the deification of the plants with special reference to their healing properties, and plants also appear in the Atharvaveda, where they are used in spells for healing, and for driving away demons of all kinds: the plant is even besought to bestow a horse, a sheep, a garment, and the life of the patient, who doubtless was to be the instrument by which the prayer of the medicine man was to be made good if the spell succeeded in attaining its purpose. In the Rigveda 7 Soma is already the king of the plants, and they are called mothers and goddesses: the Atharvaveda poetically describes a plant as a goddess born of the goddess earth. On the other hand plants have power to hinder child-birth, and in that case the offering of an animal victim to them is prescribed by the Taittirīya Samhita in order to procure their favour.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Spirits of Agriculture, Pasture, and the Mountains</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/11_THE_MINOR_GODS_OF_NATURE/04_Spirits_of_Agriculture_Pasture_and_the_Mountains/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/11_THE_MINOR_GODS_OF_NATURE/04_Spirits_of_Agriculture_Pasture_and_the_Mountains/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;9&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The deity of the field as Kṣetrasya Pati, &amp;rsquo; lord of the field&amp;rsquo;, in the Rigveda 1 is invoked to grant cattle and horses, and with sweetness to fill heaven and earth, the plants, and the waters. In another hymn a he is asked, along with Savitṛ, the Dawns, and Parjanya to bestow prosperity, and elsewhere it is said that worshippers are fain to have him as a neighbour. The full nature of the deity is made clear in the Gṛhya ritual,3 which prescribes offerings to him when the field is ploughed, and he is, it is clear, no more than the deity believed to be in the ploughed land. Similarly the Rigveda contains an invocation of Sita, the furrow, to grant rich blessings and crops.&amp;quot; The figure of this goddess naturally has more life in the Sutras, which deal with the operations of agriculture: she appears as the wife of Indra, which may be due to the fact that in the Rigveda&amp;rsquo; the god is once called Urvarapati, lord of the plough field,&amp;rsquo; and her existence is manifested in the four Sondergötter, the deities Sītā, Āśā, Araḍā, and Anaghã, who are to be worshipped at the furrow sacrifice, the threshing-floor sacrifice, the sowing of the crop, and the reaping and the putting the crop into the barn. In another Sūtra&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Deities of the House</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/11_THE_MINOR_GODS_OF_NATURE/05_Deities_of_the_House/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/11_THE_MINOR_GODS_OF_NATURE/05_Deities_of_the_House/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The deity of the house and the home is Vāstospati, ‘lord of the dwelling&amp;rsquo;, who is invoked in one short hymn of the Rigveda to bless man and beast, to remove diseases, to make cattle and horses prosper, to afford protection, and to grant a favourable entry. He is elsewhere described as destroyer of diseases, is identified with Soma, brought into close connexion with Tvaṣṭr as an artificer, or again he is likened to Indra as a cuirass of Soma pressers. In the late tenth book 3 he appears as an observer of ordinances, who was fashioned by the gods along with prayer. His character is made more clear by the fact that the Gṛhya Sūtras prescribe that offerings are to be made to him when a new house is entered. There is no possible ground for supposing that either Pūṣan,&amp;quot; or Rudra, or Agni,” or any other god is designated by the title, though Rudra actually bears the style in one passage. The god is clearly the god of the house, who when a new house is built comes and abides in it. In the Sūtras&amp;rsquo; we hear more generally of deities of the house.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 Divine Implements</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/11_THE_MINOR_GODS_OF_NATURE/06_Divine_Implements/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/11_THE_MINOR_GODS_OF_NATURE/06_Divine_Implements/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is no very essential distinction between the worship of natural objects conceived as living and the worship of objects made by human hands, but it is obvious that the worship of such objects tends to be restricted in effect and importance. This is borne out by the evidence of Vedic religion where such religion is of very minor importance, despite the fact that it receives further attention in the Rigveda than might a priori have been expected. Thus we find there 10 that two implements of the ploughman, Śuna and Sira, which may be the ploughshare and the plough, are invoked, and that in the Śatapatha Brāhmana a cake is assigned to them in the sacrifice. The warrior invokes his arrow as divine,&amp;quot; and begs it to protect him and assail his foes his armour, his bow and quiver, are also celebrated, and the drum is invoked to drive away the demons and the danger: in the Atharvaveda 1a a whole hymn is devoted to its praises. But the priest naturally is more&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 Divine Animals</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/11_THE_MINOR_GODS_OF_NATURE/07_Divine_Animals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/11_THE_MINOR_GODS_OF_NATURE/07_Divine_Animals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The place of animals in the Veda is restricted and of comparatively little importance so far as it concerns direct worship of animals, whether individuals or species, as distinct from the theriomorphism of gods who are not animal gods, and the use of animal fetishes. But the existence of these different ways, in which an animal may seem to be divine, renders it difficult in each case to say whether or not direct worship of animal is to be detected.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 Totemism</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/11_THE_MINOR_GODS_OF_NATURE/08_Totemism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/11_THE_MINOR_GODS_OF_NATURE/08_Totemism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The nature and meaning of totemism are so uncertain and ill defined that it would be necessary to examine the concept in detail, if it were not for the fact that, on any theory of totemism which does not reduce it to the worship of animals, there is no support for the view that that phenomenon is to be found in Vedic religion. The essential feature of a totemist community as conceived by S. Reinach, who is now its most consistent supporter, assumes that the men and women of that community conceive themselves severally to be related to some animal or plant or other thing, and that they normally treat that plant or animal with great care and respect, only on special occasions in the case of an animal or plant destroying it in the course of a formal meal, in which they enter into communion among themselves and with the god, through devouring the representative of the god: the species and not the mere animal being sacred, as soon as one animal is killed, another takes its place. To this conception of totemism the most value is attributed by Reinach because of his view that the domestication of animals and plants came about through this belief, which he traces to a hypertrophy of the same social instinct which allowed of the growth of human society by forbidding killing within the family and the clan. He does not regard it as primitive in totemism that the members of the totem group should regard the totem as an ancestor : this is in his view the sort of wrong explanation which is inevitably given by savages when asked to explain uses of which they do not know the real origin.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 The Lesser Nature Goddesses</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/11_THE_MINOR_GODS_OF_NATURE/09_The_Lesser_Nature_Goddesses/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/11_THE_MINOR_GODS_OF_NATURE/09_The_Lesser_Nature_Goddesses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Not one of the goddesses of the Rigveda, with the doubtful exception of the Dawn, can be said to be of any real importance. Sarasvati and Pṛthivï have already been mentioned: in the Sûtras Bhūmi also appears, but with little character of any kind, doubtless as a direct expression for the earth&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1 VS. xxx. 8; ŚB. xiii. 2. 4. 2. Such ideas are common in Babylonian religion. Cf. werwolves, Carnoy, Les Indo-Européens, p. 226.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
