<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;05 THE NATURE OF THE GODS AND DEMONS on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/05_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;05 THE NATURE OF THE GODS AND DEMONS on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/05_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 Nature Gods and Abstract Deities (a) ANTHROPOMORPHISM</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/05_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS/1_Nature_Gods_and_Abstract_Deities_a_ANTHROPOMORPH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/05_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS/1_Nature_Gods_and_Abstract_Deities_a_ANTHROPOMORPH/</guid>
      <description>1
ALREADY in the period of Indo-European unity there had in all probability arisen the conception of anthropomorphic deities of the sky, such as Dyaus, Mitra, or the Aśvins, and it is therefore only natural that in the main the high gods of the Rigveda should be essentially conceived as human, as men of supernatural power, and free from death, but still as subject to birth and akin in their family relation to men.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2 Fetishism</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/05_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS/2_Fetishism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/05_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS/2_Fetishism/</guid>
      <description>The worship of natural objects, whether celestial, ethereal or terrestrial, is sharply to be distinguished from the reverence paid to earthly objects or animals, not as in themselves normally or continually divine, but because for a certain purpose and in certain conditions they are deemed to be filled with the divine spirit. It is clear, however obvious the distinction is as a matter of theory, that in many cases it must be extremely difficult to distinguish the two phenomena.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 Animism and the Spirits of the Dead</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/05_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS/3_Animism_and_the_Spirits_of_the_Dead/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/05_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS/3_Animism_and_the_Spirits_of_the_Dead/</guid>
      <description>1
The worship of natural objects and activities is by no means the whole basis of Vedic belief, even allowing in the fullest degree for the development of myth by the mythopoetic faculty, and for the growth of abstract gods not in any way connected with a natural basis. An independent 1 source of religious feeling lies in the regard paid to the spirits of the dead: it does not seem possible to deny as regards them that from the first two aspects were present in the feelings of those who remained alive: on the one hand, the dead was in need of aid and comfort from the living, but the dead was also a potential source of danger to the living and must be propitiated, even if the soul was that of a dear one, still more so if it were the soul of an enemy or some one whom the living had mishandled.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4 The term Deva</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/05_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS/4_The_term_Deva/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/05_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS/4_The_term_Deva/</guid>
      <description>The word Deva undoubtedly denotes a being connected with the heaven, and there can be doubt only regarding the precise sense which had been developed during the Aryan period when the word was common to the Indians and the Iranians to be. Such evidence as there is suggests that the term had already come to be applied generically as a term for the gods of all kinds, though this must remain doubtful.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
