<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;05 THE NATURE OF THE GODS AND DEMONS on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/05_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;05 THE NATURE OF THE GODS AND DEMONS on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/05_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 Nature Gods and Abstract Deities (a) ANTHROPOMORPHISM</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/05_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS/1_Nature_Gods_and_Abstract_Deities_a_ANTHROPOMORPH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/05_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS/1_Nature_Gods_and_Abstract_Deities_a_ANTHROPOMORPH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ALREADY in the period of Indo-European unity there had in all probability arisen the conception of anthropomorphic deities of the sky, such as Dyaus, Mitra, or the Aśvins, and it is therefore only natural that in the main the high gods of the Rigveda should be essentially conceived as human, as men of supernatural power, and free from death, but still as subject to birth and akin in their family relation to men. But, though it would be wrong to ignore the anthropomorphic 1 character of the gods, the Vedic pantheon has none of the clear cut figures of the Greek, and unlike the Greek deities it is seldom difficult to doubt that the anthropomorphic forms but faintly veil phenomena of nature. The difference is so striking that it is impossible to ascribe it to a mere difference between the records of the two religions, the secular and romantic poetry of Homer on the one hand, and the formal hymns used in the sacrifice of the Rigveda on the other. It is most probable that much of the vagueness of the physical nature of the Greek gods and goddesses is due to their origin either from direct borrowing from the Aegean people of Greece, or from contamination with Aegean deities.&amp;quot; In the process of amalgamation of beliefs it is scarcely surprising that the outlines of the characters of the gods should have been hopelessly blurred in comparison with the much clearer and more transparent figures of the Vedic hymns.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2 Fetishism</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/05_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS/2_Fetishism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/05_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS/2_Fetishism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The worship of natural objects, whether celestial, ethereal or terrestrial, is sharply to be distinguished from the reverence paid to earthly objects or animals, not as in themselves normally or continually divine, but because for a certain purpose and in certain conditions they are deemed to be filled with the divine spirit. It is clear, however obvious the distinction is as a matter of theory, that in many cases it must be extremely difficult to distinguish the two phenomena. A simple example of the difficulty is afforded by the contrast which seems to exist between the reverence paid by the priest to his offering implements, such as the pressing stones and the offering post, and that paid by the warrior to his weapons. In both cases the reverence is that paid to the work of human hands, but it can hardly be held in the case of the warrior that his weapons are conceived as being filled by any external spirit for the time being: rather they have, though made by human hands, when made, a life and reality of their own, which renders it right on special occasions that they should receive due honour and veneration. For the whole time of their existence as such, before they are destroyed by the event of war or abandoned as outworn, they retain this character of their own. On the other hand, the reverence paid to the pressing stones and other implements of the sacrifice seems far more naturally to be attributed to the holy character of the sacrificial ground and of the surroundings through the presence of the god. The sacred strew on which the god is invited to take his seat and all the implements must surely be filled with the divine afflatus for the period of the offering. The offering post in the animal sacrifice is solemnly anointed, and surrounded with a girdle which acts in some measure as clothing. It has&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 Animism and the Spirits of the Dead</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/05_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS/3_Animism_and_the_Spirits_of_the_Dead/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/05_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS/3_Animism_and_the_Spirits_of_the_Dead/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The worship of natural objects and activities is by no means the whole basis of Vedic belief, even allowing in the fullest degree for the development of myth by the mythopoetic faculty, and for the growth of abstract gods not in any way connected with a natural basis. An independent 1 source of religious feeling lies in the regard paid to the spirits of the dead: it does not seem possible to deny as regards them that from the first two aspects were present in the feelings of those who remained alive: on the one hand, the dead was in need of aid and comfort from the living, but the dead was also a potential source of danger to the living and must be propitiated, even if the soul was that of a dear one, still more so if it were the soul of an enemy or some one whom the living had mishandled. It is in no way inconceivable that from the reverence paid to a soul there might spring up the worship of a god analogous to the worship of nature gods: such an origin has been suggested for part at least of the character of Rudra,3 of the Maruts * and of Yama, but in none of these cases have we attained anything like probability. On the other hand, it is probable enough that certain mythical priestly families, including perhaps the Bhrgus, owe their position to the reverence paid to the dead. Nevertheless these families are not gods proper, nor treated as gods in the ordinary sense in the Veda: their human origin is distinctly remembered or believed in.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4 The term Deva</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/05_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS/4_The_term_Deva/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/05_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS/4_The_term_Deva/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The word Deva undoubtedly denotes a being connected with the heaven, and there can be doubt only regarding the precise sense which had been developed during the Aryan period when the word was common to the Indians and the Iranians to be. Such evidence as there is suggests that the term had already come to be applied generically as a term for the gods of all kinds, though this must remain doubtful. What is clear is that in the use of the Rigveda the word has essentially this sense; the Devas stand out against the demons whether Dāsas, Dasyus, or Rakṣases, while the Brāhmaṇas show the term Asura degraded from its old higher sense and opposed to Deva.* The generic sense of Deva is revealed in the negative Adeva which is opposed to Deva and is used of the demon Vrtra.5 So also we have the terms mūradeva used of those who had roots as their gods, and śiśnadeva of those who were phallus worshippers.&amp;quot; It is, therefore, clear that the connexion with the heaven had long been lost. That the term Devas when used in the Rigveda and other Vedic literature normally denotes the narrow circle of the sky gods, and that the term Viśve Devās applies to the gods as a whole, in opposition to this narrower group, is a hypothesis wholly without plausibility or support. It is absurd to suggest that when gods are opposed to demons the sky gods alone are meant, still more absurd to find them alone designated when gods,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
