<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;10 THE GREAT GODS-TERRESTRIAL on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/10_THE_GREAT_GODS-TERRESTRIAL/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;10 THE GREAT GODS-TERRESTRIAL on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/10_THE_GREAT_GODS-TERRESTRIAL/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 Agni</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/10_THE_GREAT_GODS-TERRESTRIAL/1_Agni/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/10_THE_GREAT_GODS-TERRESTRIAL/1_Agni/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;AGNI is clearly in the eyes of the priest only second to Indra in importance: in the Rigveda he has some 200 hymns for himself alone.1 From Indra, however, he is essentially distinguished by his nature; he is intimately connected with the element of which he is the deity, and his nature is therefore far less anthropomorphic; moreover, what there is of human in him is derived, not from the conception of the warrior god, but from that of the ideal priest: if both gods are expected to send fortune and happiness to their votaries, Indra gives rather victory in battle and power, Agni the prosperity and happiness of the home. Moreover, while Agni is assimilated in much to Indra and as usual is accorded several of his feats and his powers, Indra remains comparatively unaffected by the qualities of Agni. Indra also is not, like Agni, the messenger between gods and men, an office, which, if it makes Agni in some ways a god of the closest intimacy with the life of men, still does tend to reduce his status, and renders him in some sense inferior to the other gods. Nor is Soma the normal drink of Agni: he is indeed a Soma-drinker, but only in a minimal degree for a great god, and often because of his connexion with Indra.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2 Bṛhaspati and other forms of Agni</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/10_THE_GREAT_GODS-TERRESTRIAL/2_bRhaspati_and_other_forms_of_Agni/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/10_THE_GREAT_GODS-TERRESTRIAL/2_bRhaspati_and_other_forms_of_Agni/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Bṛhaspati is a god of much importance in the eyes of the Rigveda, since it devotes to him eleven hymns and mentions him, under that name or as Brahmanaspati, about 170 times. He forms with Indra a pair in two hymns. But his character appears very clearly as a compound of the activities of other gods. Thus his appearance is like that of Agni: he has seven mouths, seven rays, a beautiful tongue, he is bright, pure, ruddy, and clear-voiced. He has sharp horns and a hundred wings; he carries an iron axe, wrought by Tvaṣtr, or a golden hatchet, and rides on a car with ruddy steeds. But he is marked out by having a bow whose string is Ṛta, which here doubtless refers to the holy rite, the sacrifice, showing that his weapons are also priestly. He is said to have been born from great light in the highest heaven, and with thunder to have dispelled the darkness, but also to be the half of the two worlds or of Tvaṣṭr, and he is the producer of the gods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 The God Soma</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/10_THE_GREAT_GODS-TERRESTRIAL/3_The_God_Soma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/10_THE_GREAT_GODS-TERRESTRIAL/3_The_God_Soma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The poetry of the Rigveda is mainly connected with the Soma sacrifice, and this fact must be borne in mind in estimating the importance of the god Soma. In its present form the whole of the ninth book of the Samhitā is devoted to him and he has six hymns in other books: moreover he is invoked in parts of four or five others, and also as a joint deity with Indra, Agni, Pūṣan and Rudra. The number of times his name occurs is incapable of accurate calculation, as the name is constantly mentioned without it being possible to say whether the god is really referred to.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4 The Rivers</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/10_THE_GREAT_GODS-TERRESTRIAL/4_The_Rivers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/10_THE_GREAT_GODS-TERRESTRIAL/4_The_Rivers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is perhaps doubtful whether the rivers can claim to be regarded as among the great gods of the Rigveda, but their importance in the mind of the Vedic Indians was perhaps sufficient to justify their treatment in this place. One whole long hymn 3 is accorded to the Sarasvati, and in two verses of it are enumerated her tributaries and other affluents, while the Vipãś and Śutudri claim another hymn 4 of some poetical beauty.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 The Earth</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/10_THE_GREAT_GODS-TERRESTRIAL/5_The_Earth/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/10_THE_GREAT_GODS-TERRESTRIAL/5_The_Earth/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The goddess Pṛthivi plays a singularly restricted part in the Rigveda except in so far as she is invoked along with Dyaus. She has but one short hymn of her own, and a long and interesting hymn ascribed to her in the Atharvaveda is conspicuous rather for its accuracy of enumeration of the sights of the earth than for religious fervour. She is rich in heights, bears the burden of the mountains, and supports in the ground the forest trees. She is great, shining, and firm, and quickens the earth, by scattering rain from the cloud, a fact which shows that she is not rigidly confined to her element, doubtless because she has borrowed an attribute of Dyaus himself. The Brahmanas&amp;quot; follow the Rigveda in referring her name as broad to the fact of her having been extended. In the funeral hymn she is appealed to be tender to the dead as to a child, and she is called kindly mother earth. In the domestic ritual offerings to her as Bhūmi are not rare.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>6 The Sea</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/10_THE_GREAT_GODS-TERRESTRIAL/6_The_Sea/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/10_THE_GREAT_GODS-TERRESTRIAL/6_The_Sea/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All the available evidence points to the fact that the Vedic Indians had little accurate knowledge of the sea, and that none of the tribes were actually settled by the banks of the ocean, but at the same time the legend of the Aśvins and their ships and of the saving of Bhujyu must be allowed, when taken in connexion with a few passages where the sea seems clearly a real sea,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
