<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;5 THE PHILOSOPHY OF THE VEDA on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;5 THE PHILOSOPHY OF THE VEDA on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>26 THE BEGINNINGS OF VEDIC PHILOSOPHY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/26_THE_BEGINNINGS_OF_VEDIC_PHILOSOPHY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/26_THE_BEGINNINGS_OF_VEDIC_PHILOSOPHY/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THE earliest poetry of India already contains many traces of the essential character of the philosophy of India. In nothing indeed does the continuity of Indian life show itself more strikingly than this: the gods of India change, but the alteration of the higher thought is far less marked.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Philosophy in India shows its beginnings as often in the expression of scepticism: the normal belief in the gods here and there seems to have been questioned, and it is not unnatural that the questioning should have arisen in the case of the most human of the gods, him whom the seers most closely fashioned in their own likeness, the vehement Indra. We have not indeed any certain case of a seer who himself doubted the truth of Indra&amp;rsquo;s greatness : 1 no open&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>29 GREECE AND THE PHILOSOPHY OF INDIA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/29_GREECE_AND_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_INDIA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/29_GREECE_AND_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_INDIA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is not to be thought that the early philosophy of Greece exercised any influence on the philosophy of India. Apart from every other consideration, it is clear that the rise of philosophy in Greece was long subsequent to the beginnings of Indian philosophy in the hymns of the Rigveda, and from those hymns the history of that philosophy presents itself in the light of an ordered development. The same reason, which makes it inconceivable that the philosophy of the Upanisads should have been the product of external influences, such as the introduction of extraneous ideas from the warrior class, makes it inconceivable that the development of that philosophy should have been affected by influences from Greece.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
