<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;6 Becoming Agni on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;6 Becoming Agni on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 Agni, Private and Extended</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/1_Agni_Private_and_Extended/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/1_Agni_Private_and_Extended/</guid>
      <description>A blend of natural learning ability, recitation skills, and dedication to hard work creates a successful Veda pandit out of a brahmacarin. In Chapter 2 the Vedic
Becoming Agni 189
student was seen to begin his lifelong bond with Agni by daily agni-karya that he learned on the second day of his initiation ritual. He collects kindling for his guru and looks after one or more fires, offering, for example, seventeen twigs from a branch of a ravi or medi tree with a mantra for each, waiting to see that each is entirely burned, doing an expiation if he has missed a day.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2 The Adhana, Setting the Fires for Srauta Agni-hotra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/2_The_Adhana_Setting_the_Fires_for_Srauta_Agni-hotra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/2_The_Adhana_Setting_the_Fires_for_Srauta_Agni-hotra/</guid>
      <description>A Vedic student’s guru, usually his father or grandfather, determines the tex tual selection and pace of learning Veda. Parents select marriage partners when they are still children, sometimes even at birth. These two decisions, instruction schedules and marriage, are not personal ones. A commitment to set the fires for a career as agni-hotrin and co-sacrificing wife is different, and is perhaps the single most important decision in the lives of a Veda pandit and his spouse.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 The Agni-hotra, Sunset and Sunrise</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/3_The_Agni-hotra_Sunset_and_Sunrise/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/3_The_Agni-hotra_Sunset_and_Sunrise/</guid>
      <description>Milk Offerings
Because of multiple meanings, the term agni-hotra, literally “offering to Agni,” often confuses those outside the sacrificial tradition, including educated Hindus. It is a liquid food offering to Agni, fresh milk or ghee poured twice daily from a havani ladle with a grooved “elephant’s tongue” spout into the
Becoming Agni 195
Figure 6.1. Ladles used to make offerings into Agni, Sriramapuram 1987.
ahavaniya fire. (This ladle appears on the right in Figure 6.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4 Offerings to the New Moon, Full Moon, and Constellations</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/4_Offerings_to_the_New_Moon_Full_Moon_and_Constellations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/4_Offerings_to_the_New_Moon_Full_Moon_and_Constellations/</guid>
      <description>Nocturnal life under the glare of electric lighting is a new experience for many in village India today just as it was a few generations ago in urban Delhi, New York, or London. After sundown, untold thousands of generations knew only the soft glow of an oil lamp supplementing light from stars and the fluc
tuating moon. The ease and power of an electric bulb, once made available to startle the night with human design and will, closed an era of cosmic depen dence.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5 The Agrayana Harvest Sacrifices</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/5_The_Agrayana_Harvest_Sacrifices/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/5_The_Agrayana_Harvest_Sacrifices/</guid>
      <description>In some drought-stricken areas of Andhra and other states of South India hungry folk chastise their deities, even threaten to abandon their worship because they have withheld life-saving rains. Not so in Konasima’s garden zone of abundant Godavari waters where first-fruit harvests are thrilling occa
sions and opportunities to reward the gods with first-taste offerings. The bag ging of new rice, ripened in the autumn crop, brings a joyous festival when everyone thanks the goddess in Durga-puja and the Vaidika ahitagni perform agrayana in a sala, a bamboo screened area just outside each house.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>6 The Catur-masya Seasonal Rituals</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/6_The_Catur-masya_Seasonal_Rituals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/6_The_Catur-masya_Seasonal_Rituals/</guid>
      <description>Another full set of rituals is the observation of a new three-month season every four months, the series known as catur-masya. In Konasima there is near uni formity of days and nights, twelve hours each, the sun rising or setting about six o’clock year round with none of the daylight and darkness fluctuations of climates farther north or south. The seasons change, however, each with a special character, the rapidly accelerating heat of the New Year from March to June (Caitra, Vaisakha, Jyestha), the breaking of heat with the monsoon rainy season (Asadha, Sravana, Bhadrapada), a cool-down for the autumn harvest (Asvina, Karttika, Margasirsa), and the coldest months giving way to spring and another New Year’s festival on Ugadi (Pausa, Magha, Phalguna).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>7 The First Soma and Animal Sacrifice, Agni-stoma</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/7_The_First_Soma_and_Animal_Sacrifice_Agni-stoma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/7_The_First_Soma_and_Animal_Sacrifice_Agni-stoma/</guid>
      <description>Baballa, so often equipped with the right phrase for the occasion, drew upon his experience as soma-yaji, soma-sacrificer, alongside his father and five soma-yaji brothers, and observed that this momentous step into agni-stoma permits the easy progress of a bullock cart on a well-grooved road. He belonged to an elite older generation that cherished the drinking of soma as a closed-circuit drama demanding only the purest and most accomplished of participants to serve the gods.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>8 The Pravargya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/8_The_Pravargya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/8_The_Pravargya/</guid>
      <description>A ritual sometimes inserted into the soma sacrifices between the diksa and the three pressing days is the pravargya, basically an offering to the Asvins and a few other deities of hot milk (cow’s and goat’s) plus ghee and curds. It is often referenced as gharma, heat. Since it should be added during a second or third soma sacrifice, not the soma-initiating agni-stoma for the couple, it has an eccentric place in the sutras.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>9 The Soma-sacrifice Schedule and</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/9_The_Soma-sacrifice_Schedule_and/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/9_The_Soma-sacrifice_Schedule_and/</guid>
      <description>Other Rituals
Vedic ritual texts imagine an ideal progression through a number of sacri fices—extensive and quite expensive—after the agni-stoma. In the modern period there have been few ahitagni who managed more than the initial soma rite. A 1976 publication, Veda Pandits in India, volume 2, Andhra Veda Pandits, listed 401 names with photos, including numerous ahitagni, but largely with out record of srauta careers.45 A valuable 1983 survey by C.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
