<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;6 Becoming Agni on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;6 Becoming Agni on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 Agni, Private and Extended</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/1_Agni_Private_and_Extended/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/1_Agni_Private_and_Extended/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A blend of natural learning ability, recitation skills, and dedication to hard work  creates a successful Veda pandit out of a brahmacarin. In Chapter 2 the Vedic&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Becoming Agni 189&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;student was seen to begin his lifelong bond with Agni by daily agni-karya that  he learned on the second day of his initiation ritual. He collects kindling for his  guru and looks after one or more fires, offering, for example, seventeen twigs  from a branch of a ravi or medi tree with a mantra for each, waiting to see that  each is entirely burned, doing an expiation if he has missed a day. Today his  guru is most probably his father or grandfather and he is therefore doing rou&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2 The Adhana, Setting the Fires for Srauta Agni-hotra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/2_The_Adhana_Setting_the_Fires_for_Srauta_Agni-hotra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/2_The_Adhana_Setting_the_Fires_for_Srauta_Agni-hotra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A Vedic student’s guru, usually his father or grandfather, determines the tex tual selection and pace of learning Veda. Parents select marriage partners  when they are still children, sometimes even at birth. These two decisions,  instruction schedules and marriage, are not personal ones. A commitment to  set the fires for a career as agni-hotrin and co-sacrificing wife is different, and  is perhaps the single most important decision in the lives of a Veda pandit and  his spouse. It must be undertaken jointly and with deep consideration. This  giant step expands upon a lifelong intimacy with fire that began for the boy  with Agni maintenance as a brahmacarin. Now the liaison takes the form of  twice-daily milk offerings and a demand for shared caretaker roles of constant  fire tending with the proper implements.4&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 The Agni-hotra, Sunset and Sunrise</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/3_The_Agni-hotra_Sunset_and_Sunrise/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/3_The_Agni-hotra_Sunset_and_Sunrise/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Milk Offerings&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Because of multiple meanings, the term agni-hotra, literally “offering to Agni,”  often confuses those outside the sacrificial tradition, including educated  Hindus. It is a liquid food offering to Agni, fresh milk or ghee poured twice  daily from a havani ladle with a grooved “elephant’s tongue” spout into the&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Becoming Agni 195&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Figure 6.1. Ladles used to make offerings into Agni, Sriramapuram 1987.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ahavaniya fire. (This ladle appears on the right in Figure 6.1.) Agni-hotra is also  the triadic complex of all three fire-hearths, one or more with active embers or  cooling ashes. It may be, like other sacrificial terms, a personal name, as in the  son of Kapilavayi Rama Sastri and Maruti, Agnihotra Sarma. But it is above all  Agni himself, the god Agni-hotra who receives the libations. In that circular  sense for dedicated ahitagni it is God receiving God.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4 Offerings to the New Moon, Full Moon, and Constellations</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/4_Offerings_to_the_New_Moon_Full_Moon_and_Constellations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/4_Offerings_to_the_New_Moon_Full_Moon_and_Constellations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Nocturnal life under the glare of electric lighting is a new experience for many  in village India today just as it was a few generations ago in urban Delhi,  New York, or London. After sundown, untold thousands of generations knew  only the soft glow of an oil lamp supplementing light from stars and the fluc&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;tuating moon. The ease and power of an electric bulb, once made available to  startle the night with human design and will, closed an era of cosmic depen dence. It also erased a specific kind of knowledge, the awareness of where and  when those spare sources of cosmic illumination appear. India, however, still  remembers what industrialized societies have largely forgotten: lunar cycles  and stellar rhythms.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 The Agrayana Harvest Sacrifices</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/5_The_Agrayana_Harvest_Sacrifices/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/5_The_Agrayana_Harvest_Sacrifices/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In some drought-stricken areas of Andhra and other states of South India  hungry folk chastise their deities, even threaten to abandon their worship  because they have withheld life-saving rains. Not so in Konasima’s garden  zone of abundant Godavari waters where first-fruit harvests are thrilling occa&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;sions and opportunities to reward the gods with first-taste offerings. The bag ging of new rice, ripened in the autumn crop, brings a joyous festival when  everyone thanks the goddess in Durga-puja and the Vaidika ahitagni perform  agrayana in a sala, a bamboo screened area just outside each house. It is done  on a new-moon day following much the same procedure as in the lunar rite  that may either precede or succeed it. As noted in Chapter 5, aging and ailing  ahitagni observe this new-rice ritual to the furthest limit of their capacities,  rekindle fires and perform isti and expiations just for this quintessential cer emony. Baballa and Sundari managed their last agrayana in 1990 when he was  eighty-seven and she was eighty-one. No one eats the new rice until it has been  offered in sacrifice and then only in proper ritual attire and a state of purity.  In the spring, barley is harvested in a minor version of agrayana and a third  grain, syamaka, a rainy season millet, is also honored in first fruits with Soma  the deity (cf. ApSS 6.29.10). Autumn agrayana involves new-rice dough puro dasa made on twelve sherds offered to Indra-and-Agni, another one made on  a single sherd for a second dual deity, Heaven-and-Earth (Dyava and Prthivi),  and a cooked rice portion for the Visvedevas, the All-gods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>6 The Catur-masya Seasonal Rituals</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/6_The_Catur-masya_Seasonal_Rituals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/6_The_Catur-masya_Seasonal_Rituals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Another full set of rituals is the observation of a new three-month season every  four months, the series known as catur-masya. In Konasima there is near uni formity of days and nights, twelve hours each, the sun rising or setting about  six o’clock year round with none of the daylight and darkness fluctuations of  climates farther north or south. The seasons change, however, each with a  special character, the rapidly accelerating heat of the New Year from March to  June (Caitra, Vaisakha, Jyestha), the breaking of heat with the monsoon rainy  season (Asadha, Sravana, Bhadrapada), a cool-down for the autumn harvest  (Asvina, Karttika, Margasirsa), and the coldest months giving way to spring  and another New Year’s festival on Ugadi (Pausa, Magha, Phalguna).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>7 The First Soma and Animal Sacrifice, Agni-stoma</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/7_The_First_Soma_and_Animal_Sacrifice_Agni-stoma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/7_The_First_Soma_and_Animal_Sacrifice_Agni-stoma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Baballa, so often equipped with the right phrase for the occasion, drew upon his  experience as soma-yaji, soma-sacrificer, alongside his father and five soma-yaji brothers, and observed that this momentous step into agni-stoma permits the  easy progress of a bullock cart on a well-grooved road. He belonged to an elite  older generation that cherished the drinking of soma as a closed-circuit drama  demanding only the purest and most accomplished of participants to serve  the gods. As in his reluctance to accept daksina from students and his refusal  of TTD employment, he frequently turned down invitations from local and  regional pandits to be a priest in their sacrifices and accepted only the role of  sadasya who does not drink soma. His dread was the possibility of error.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>8 The Pravargya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/8_The_Pravargya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/8_The_Pravargya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A ritual sometimes inserted into the soma sacrifices between the diksa and the  three pressing days is the pravargya, basically an offering to the Asvins and  a few other deities of hot milk (cow’s and goat’s) plus ghee and curds. It is  often referenced as gharma, heat. Since it should be added during a second or  third soma sacrifice, not the soma-initiating agni-stoma for the couple, it has an  eccentric place in the sutras. The emphasis on heat brings to mind the cosmo&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>9 The Soma-sacrifice Schedule and</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/9_The_Soma-sacrifice_Schedule_and/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/6_Becoming_Agni/9_The_Soma-sacrifice_Schedule_and/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Other Rituals&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Vedic ritual texts imagine an ideal progression through a number of sacri fices—extensive and quite expensive—after the agni-stoma. In the modern  period there have been few ahitagni who managed more than the initial soma rite. A 1976 publication, Veda Pandits in India, volume 2, Andhra Veda Pandits,  listed 401 names with photos, including numerous ahitagni, but largely with out record of srauta careers.45 A valuable 1983 survey by C. G. Kashikar and  Asko Parpola is “Srauta traditions in recent times.”46 In the latter essay, the  Krishna and East Godavari Districts together accounted for well over half (114)  of the roughly 200 ahitagni listed historically for Andhra. It was at that time  estimated that only 120 ahitagni in all of India and Nepal had performed two  or more soma sacrifices, that is, agni-stoma plus any one of the other six varia tions in the list known as the sapta-samstha. Of these 120 more than half were  Andhra pandits, and Konasima was well represented, although there being  no available informant from the two Godavari districts not all were counted.  In the three decades since that tally the Godavari sum has fallen while the  Krishna number has risen markedly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
