<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;15 THE DEMONS on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/15_THE_DEMONS/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;15 THE DEMONS on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/15_THE_DEMONS/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 The Enemies of the Gods</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/15_THE_DEMONS/1_The_Enemies_of_the_Gods/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/15_THE_DEMONS/1_The_Enemies_of_the_Gods/</guid>
      <description>THE enemies of the gods par excellence throughout the Yajurveda, the Atharvaveda, and all the subsequent Vedic literature are beings called Asuras, but this connexion can be traced only in the latest parts of the Rigveda and even there but occasionally. In the singular the meaning is found but three times certainly, used of Varcin,1 Pipru,2 and the wolfish Asura; 3 a fourth case is very doubtful, and may instead refer to Varuna.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2 The Enemies of Man</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/15_THE_DEMONS/2_The_Enemies_of_Man/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/15_THE_DEMONS/2_The_Enemies_of_Man/</guid>
      <description>It is impossible, when we deal with the lesser demons of the Vedic religion, to ascertain with any reasonable certainty the origin of the different conceptions exhibited, for the lack of clearness of the notices given in our sources is in accordance with the fact that the demons are objects of aversion, and that therefore they are not minutely described, but only indicated in vague terms. It is probably true that in many cases the idea of such spirits is born of the idea of the hostile dead, or again the demons are the product of independent creative thought, corresponding to the &amp;lsquo;abstract&amp;rsquo; deities, but they may also often be more naturalistic in their origin.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
