<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;1 The Sriramapuram Agrahara on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/3_Selection_of_characters/1_The_Sriramapuram_Agrahara/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;1 The Sriramapuram Agrahara on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/3_Selection_of_characters/1_The_Sriramapuram_Agrahara/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 Bhamidipati Yajnesvara, “Baballa,”</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/3_Selection_of_characters/1_The_Sriramapuram_Agrahara/1_Bhamidipati_Yajnesvara_Baballa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/3_Selection_of_characters/1_The_Sriramapuram_Agrahara/1_Bhamidipati_Yajnesvara_Baballa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;1903–1993&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3.1.1.1 An Extraordinary Lineage&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Like others in the agrahara, this was a household that kept no small pets, no  cats, no dogs, only bovines. Therefore, when the kurma (tortoise) came to play&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Figure 3.1. Bhamidipati “Baballa” and Sundari, Sriramapuram 1987.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Figure 3.2. Baballa, age eighty-eight, Sriramapuram 1991.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[[58]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;a role in a great srauta ritual, and stayed in the house for some days while  all the preparations were underway, he—or perhaps she, no one was sure— became the target of everyone’s affection. Baballa, sacrificer-to-be, found him  irresistible and admired him daily. “For the ritual of placement we dug a hole,  lined it with shells, let some honey drip onto his shell and placed him looking  at the hole. Face to face with him I recited: ‘You are not required here, you are  free to go.’ The altar bricks for the aruna-ketuka were laid in place above him.  Next morning he was gone. He found the way out.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2 Duvvuri Yajulu (1915–2005) and</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/3_Selection_of_characters/1_The_Sriramapuram_Agrahara/2_Duvvuri_Yajulu_19152005_and/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/3_Selection_of_characters/1_The_Sriramapuram_Agrahara/2_Duvvuri_Yajulu_19152005_and/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;His Descendants&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When Baballa and Sundari, with son Bullebayi and his wife Savitri and their  one-year-old son Prasad, moved to the new agrahara known as Sriramapuram,  their neighbor across the lane was a younger man who had been offering  agni-hotra twice daily for some seventeen years, the last seven of them in a  newly built Sriramapuram house. This ahitagni was Duvvuri Yajnesvara  Paundarika Yajulu, born in Kapilesvarapuram in 1915, another Veda pandit  with a long and colorful family history of Veda and srauta. “Yajulu” is a Telugu  personal name, short for soma-yajulu, Sanskrit soma-yajin, soma-sacrificer.  Since it occurs as a name in several other families, Duvvuri Yajulu will serve  to distinguish him later on, whereas here in this brief sketch he will be simply  Yajulu. His gotra was Atreya. He possessed a generous spirit and had kind  words even for those whom other pandits disparaged.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 Bulusu Cayanulu (1915–1997)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/3_Selection_of_characters/1_The_Sriramapuram_Agrahara/3_Bulusu_Cayanulu_19151997/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/3_Selection_of_characters/1_The_Sriramapuram_Agrahara/3_Bulusu_Cayanulu_19151997/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The fifty-year-old house next-to-last at the far end of the agrahara lane stood  boarded up and empty for a year to allow ghosts and demons time to clear out.  If one had to walk that way it was done quickly with averted gaze. Rituals were  done against “wind,” gali, and dust, a common Telugu expression for ghosts  and other dangerous malevolent forces. Inside the house a few cracked, dried  fragments of clay fireplaces scotched the floor. They should have been cleared  away to assure safe journey onward for the deceased house owner, but he had  died suddenly under an inauspicious constellation. After funerary procedures  the house was hastily abandoned.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4 Samavedam (1932–2008) and Sons</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/3_Selection_of_characters/1_The_Sriramapuram_Agrahara/4_Samavedam_19322008_and_Sons/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/3_Selection_of_characters/1_The_Sriramapuram_Agrahara/4_Samavedam_19322008_and_Sons/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A fourth habitually visible figure in the agrahara, well known and respected  throughout coastal Andhra, was Samavedam Suryanarayana Avadhani, Harita  gotra, resident of Sriramapuram for well over half a century. His grandfa ther was an ahitagni in Mukkamala but neither his Telugu pandit father nor  Samavedam himself chose the life of agni-hotra and srauta, preferring instead  to concentrate on steering sons into Vedic education. “I teach and recite  Veda,” said Samavedam, “and this is all my life.” In fact, both father and son  accomplished the same feat, each carefully preparing two out of four sons for  careers as Veda pandits and seeking as far as possible to marry daughters to  Veda pandits.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
