<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;20 THE SACRIFICES OF THE Śrauta RITUAL on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;20 THE SACRIFICES OF THE Śrauta RITUAL on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 General Characteristics</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/01_General_Characteristics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/01_General_Characteristics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THE rites of the Śrauta ritual have much essentially in common, in addition to the necessity of the use of the three or one at least of the three fires in place of the domestic fire. They necessitate the presence of priests numbering from one up to sixteen, or with the Kauṣitakins seventeen,1 to whom should be added the actual performers of some of the minor actions in the more complicated forms of the ritual, whose number is not defined, and whose menial functions rendered them of no consequence in the eyes of the priests of the higher rank. It is obvious, for instance, that in the slaughtering of the victims there must often have been need for other aid than that of the Adhvaryu and his assistants proper, and the Śamitṛs are occasionally referred to as charged with the actual slaying: more often a general term like servant is used to apply to such helpers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 The Establishment and Re-establishment of the Fires</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/02_The_Establishment_and_Re-establishment_of_the_F/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/02_The_Establishment_and_Re-establishment_of_the_F/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The ritual texts lay down various periods as appropriate for the setting up of the sacred fires, the spring is the scason for a Brahman, the summer for a Kṣatriya, the rainy season for a Rathakara, and the autumn for a VaiŚya, or the cool season is suited for all castes. They also suggest that the proper time is the new moon, especially in conjunction with certain asterisms, but the full moon is also permissible. The essential part of the rite which takes two days is the setting up of the fires: on the first day are set up two sheds, the one for the Garhapatya, the other for the Ahavaniya fire: the actual altar of the first is round, that of the second square: the Dakṣiṇa fire is south of the Garhapatya and is shaped like a half moon. The fire is obtained for the Garhapatya either by friction, or by being borrowed from the house of a wealthy man or distinguished sacrificer. The night of the first day is spent by the sacrificer and his wife in wakefulness to the noise of lutes and flutes. Early in the morning the new fire for the hearths is produced by friction, and a horse is brought to watch and further the process by its presence, doubtless as a symbol of the fire or the sun. Moreover, while the fire is being produced by friction from the wood, Samans may be sung. As soon as the fire appears the sacrificer breathes upon it and inhales it. It is placed on the Garhapatya and 1 Cf. Oldenberg, Prolegomena, pp. 212 ff., * ApŚS. v. 1 ff.; BŚS. ii; MŚS. i. 5; 6. 5;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 The Fire-God Oblation or Agnihotra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/03_The_Fire-God_Oblation_or_Agnihotra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/03_The_Fire-God_Oblation_or_Agnihotra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is the duty of the man who has established his fires, as of the man who has no fires, to offer daily, morning and evening, the Agnihotra: 2 the precise time of offering, whether just before or just after the rising of the sun in the morning, and whether after sunset or after the appearance of the first star in the evening, is a subject of much discussion in the Brahmanas and Sūtras. If the fires were kept perpetually alight, then they required only to be brightened up for each occasion: if not, then the fire must be taken from the Garhapatya, either only every evening, it being used also for the morning, or each time: the Dakṣina might be kept perpetually alight, or taken out daily, or only on the newand full-moon days, on which according to some authorities the sacrificer must himself perform the ritual. The main offering was milk, milked by an Aryan into a pail made by an Aryan: the milk was heated and mixed with water on the Garhapatya, and offered in the Ahavaniya and Garhapatya. At the end the sacrificer eats and offers four water libations to the gods, the Fathers, the seven seers, and Agni on the earth, or to other deities also. The Dakṣiṇa fire received no special honour.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 The New-moon and Full-moon Sacrifices</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/04_The_New-moon_and_Full-moon_Sacrifices/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/04_The_New-moon_and_Full-moon_Sacrifices/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;These sacrifices 1 are of special value as they form the model for all sacrifices of the type called Iṣti, which include an enormous number of offerings for special ends; in all these cases the sacrifice is assumed to be performed precisely as in the newand full-moon offerings, but with the distinction that some special rite is inserted in the place of the essential features of these offerings, which are at the full-moon offering a cake for Agni and Soma, and at the newmoon offering a cake for Agni and Indra. Moreover, at the latter offering some authorities allowed a milk mess made of sweet and sour milk for Indra or Mahendra, while others restricted this offering to one who offered the Soma sacrifice. The new and full moon themselves received no offerings, except in the view of certain authorities who prescribed offerings to the Parvans: the times served only to fix the dates of the offerings, and there was, it is clear, difficulty in deciding exactly when the offerings should be made. Two days were required at new moon, but one might suffice at the full moon. On the first day the ceremonies were in the main preparatory, the making ready of the fires, and the taking of a vow by the sacrificer, which involved abstinence from meat, sleeping on the ground, the cutting of hair and beard, and so on. If the milk mess were to be offered on this day, a twig of PalaŚa or Śami wood was cut to drive away the calves from the cows, for the milking of the latter, a rite which is paralleled in western Europe. The ceremonies of the second day consisted in the preparation of the rice, its pounding and husking, the cooking of the cakes, the preparation of the altar, the girding of the wife of the sacrificer, the looking at a pot of butter, the covering of the altar with the grass, and the setting up of the partitioning sticks which were intended to keep off evil spirits. At the end of these preliminaries the real sacrifice begins; first come fifteen Samidhenī verses accompanying the laying on of kindling wood. The verses are joined into a single whole by the device of pausing after the first half verse of each. Then come two libations of the butter, doubtless in part at least necessary to make the fire burn brightly; between them comes the Pravara, the enumeration of the seers who were claimed as ancestors by the sacrificer-or if he were not a Brahman by his Purohita-and the invitation of the gods, whom Agni is invoked to bring to the offering in the order in which they were to be honoured. After the second of these Aghāras comes the formal choosing of the Hotṛ by the Adhvaryu on the authority of&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 The Four-month or Seasonal Sacrifices</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/05_The_Four-month_or_Seasonal_Sacrifices/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/05_The_Four-month_or_Seasonal_Sacrifices/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The three four-month offerings are connected intimately with the seasons of the year, the VaiŚvadeva being offered in spring, the Varunapraghāsas in the rains, and the Sākamedhas in the autumn, at the beginning of each season. The connexion with the seasons is shown by the formulae, the names of the months which are connected with certain libations, and the formal cutting of the hair which is connected with certain of the rites. The man who first performs them must begin with an Iṣṭi to Agni VaiŚvānara and Parjanya or an Anvārambhaṇiyā Iṣṭi. In each case the sacrifice is introduced by five libations to Agni, Soma, Savitṛ, Sarasvati, and Puṣan. In the first follow offerings to the Maruts, to the All-gods, and to heaven and earth, the first and last of cakes, the second of a milk mess. The season is indicated by the use of a tree with budding branches for the wood for the fire, while the strew is made from plants which are shooting.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 First-fruit Sacrifice (Agrayana Işti) and others</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/06_First-fruit_Sacrifice_Agrayana_Iti_and_others/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/06_First-fruit_Sacrifice_Agrayana_Iti_and_others/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Before partaking of any of the fruits of the fields it is necessary for a man who has established the fires to make offerings. The normal offerings are those of rice in autumn, and barley in spring: alternatives are bamboo seeds in summer, and millet in autumn or the rains in these two cases Soma is the god to whom the offerings are made: in the other case Indra and Agni receive a cake of the new fruits, and the All-gods and heaven and earth also have offerings. In the first case the fee is a garment or a repaired car, in the second the firstborn of the calves cast that year. In place, however, of the ordinary Iṣṭi the newand full-moon sacrifices may be performed, or the Agnihotra made night and morning with the new fruits. Or, again, the rice or barley may be given to a cow to eat, and then the Agnihotra offered with the milk of that cow. In that case the motive of the offering may be taken as merely a desire to secure that the first-fruits shall, in the first place, be used by some one other than man; but it is more probable that we have nothing more here than the not rare practice of giving animals food in place of the deities, or yet more probably that the offering is merely a variety of the normal offering, milk being used instead of the actual first-fruits, a simple explanation, and one perfectly reasonable in itself. The offering of first-fruits then remains a perfectly natural offering to the gods, rather however as the formulae show an offering to secure the safe use of the fruits, than the expression of gratitude to the gods for their gift. That it was felt to be in any way sacramental, or even as inducing a special sense of community, is not to be seen in the Vedic evidence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 The Animal Sacrifice</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/07_The_Animal_Sacrifice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/07_The_Animal_Sacrifice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;According to the Sutras we must distinguish between the animal sacrifice as an independent offering and the sacrifice as connected with the Soma sacrifice the offering of a goat to Agni and Soma in that offering is often treated as the Prakṛti of all animal sacrifices, but in some cases the independent animal offering which is called the NirudhapaŚubandha takes the place of the Agniṣomiya. The rite is to be performed by any man who establishes the fires, before he eats meat, and then yearly or half yearly, in which case the beginning of the bright course of the sun and the end of that period are prescribed by some authorities. The form of the offering is that of the new-moon sacrifice, the victim taking the place of the milk offered to Indra or Mahendra, but there is present another priest, the Maitrāvaruṇa, whose duty it is to give directions to the Hotṛ to say his Yajyā verses. For Indra and Agni, or Surya, or Prajapati, a goat is the victim; it must be perfect, free from blemish, such as the loss of a horn or an eye; but in other offerings than the NirūḍhapaŚubandha are found many other animals, including normally oxen and sheep; and exceptionally, as at the piling of the fire, at the horse sacrifice and at human sacrifices, large numbers of victims are alleged to be offered, mainly if not entirely in theory. For Nirṛti the dove, owl, and hare are offered, to the Rakṣases the black dog, the ass with lop ears, and the unknown taraksu.4 Some animals appear as unfit for ordinary sacrifice, the dog, the durvarāha, &amp;lsquo;bad boar&amp;rsquo;, and edaka, vicious ram&amp;rsquo;. The normal rite occupies two days, of which the former is filled by preliminary rites, the second being the day of the actual sacrifice. The two days however may be compressed into one.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 The Soma Sacrifice</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/08_The_Soma_Sacrifice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/08_The_Soma_Sacrifice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The model form of the Soma sacrifice may be said to be the Agnistoma, which is the simplest form of the one-day Soma sacrifice, that is an offering on which the Soma is offered on one day only, in the morning, at midday, and&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1 Above, Part III, Chap. 18, § 6. * Ibid., § 5. Hubert and Mauss (Année&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;sociol. ii. 81, 82) indeed compare the invocation and consumption of the Iḍā to the Mass and transubstantiation; but this is clearly a grave exaggeration. The Ida is the divine power present in the food when eaten : there is no question of the death and eating of&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 The Pravargya or Hot-milk Sacrifice</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/09_The_Pravargya_or_Hot-milk_Sacrifice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/09_The_Pravargya_or_Hot-milk_Sacrifice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the Soma sacrifice the Pravargya is inserted by the ritual text-books as an element which is to be performed twice a day in the course of the Upasad days, giving, with the normal three Upasads, six performances. But there is great doubt as to whether the rite is necessary, or whether it should be performed also at the first Agnistoma, or not until after one has been performed. The discrepancy of opinion suggests that the rite was originally a separate sacrifice altogether, and this is borne out by the Rigveda, where it seems to have been an offering made in the morning only. From clay chosen from a pit east of the Ahavaniya fire, to which a horse leads the way, a Mahāvīra pot is made, a span high, two spare pots, and various other utensils. A stool of Muñja grass is also made as a throne for the pot. The pot is heated, the milk of a cow and a goat is poured in. Finally, the hot drink is offered to the AŚvins, and two Rauhiṇa cakes are also offered in the morning to the day, in the evening to the night. At the outset of the ceremony the wife of the sacrificer is made to cover her head, but she joins with the rest at the close in the finale of the Saman which is sung. At the end the offering utensils are arranged so as to make up the semblance of a man, the three Mahāvīra&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 The AikadaŚina Animal Offering</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/10_The_aikadashina_Animal_Offering/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/10_The_aikadashina_Animal_Offering/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is a special form of the animal sacrifice which takes the place of the simpler ritual observed in the Agniṣṭoma, when it is preferred to use eleven&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1 i. 22. 14; KB. viii. 3-7.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Ved. Stud. ii. 135.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Cf. ŚB. xiv. 2. 2. 45; 8. 1. 14; TA. v. 8.7; 6. 12. Hence the treatment of the rite in TA. iv and v; Oldenberg, GN. 1915, p. 887.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;• Oldenberg, Rel. des Veda&amp;rsquo;, pp.. 448 ff.;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 Other Forms of Jyotiṣṭoma</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/11_Other_Forms_of_jyotiShToma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/11_Other_Forms_of_jyotiShToma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The ritual texts rank the Agniṣṭoma as the first form of the series of Soma sacrifices which bear the generic title of Jyotiṣṭoma. The list is in their view the Atyagnistoma, the Ukthya, the SodaŚin, the Vajapeya, Atiratra, and Aptoryama or Aptoryama. The number of the series is seven, and it is most probable that the number is simply the sacred seven, and not a trace of an original view. The Atyagniṣṭoma, the Vajapeya, and the Aptoryāma have not the place of forms of the Jyotisṭoma in the older Samhitas, and probably were added to make up the number to seven.1&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 Other Soma Sacrifices of One Day&#39;s Duration</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/12_Other_Soma_Sacrifices_of_One_Days_Duration/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/12_Other_Soma_Sacrifices_of_One_Days_Duration/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Agniṣṭoma is the model on which innumerable other kinds of sacrifice can be formed, in order to bring about certain desires. The Vicvajit is occasionally mentioned in it a man gives all his goods as the fee, or at least a thousand cattle and hundred horses. In the former case he first hands over to his eldest son his share in the property. After the offering he spends twelve nights in different places, three where an Udumbara is, eating fruits and roots only, three among Niṣādas, without eating the grains cultivated by them, three with folk, and three with folk like himself, or according to another view either VaiŚyas or Rajany&amp;hellip; The symbolic nature of the rite is obvious.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 The Vajapeya or Drink-of-Strength</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/13_The_Vajapeya_or_Drink-of-Strength/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/13_The_Vajapeya_or_Drink-of-Strength/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Vajapeya is of especial interest in that it preserves, despite the formalism imposed upon it by its inclusion in the Soma ritual, many traces of very popular origin. It is said by many authorities to be a festival of the autumn, and it is also allowed either to perform it independently, or as the sixth day of a Sarvamedha or universal sacrifice. It consists of one pressing day and at least 18 days of consecration and three Upasad days, so that it takes up at least 17 days and may be spun out to a year. It adds to the ordinary SoḍaŚin form a seventeenth Stotra and Castra, and the number seventeen is also introduced into the Bahiṣpavamāna and Madhyandinapavamāna Stotras in place of the Trivṛt and PañcadaŚa Stomas there normally used. The number of cups in the ordinary rite is increased by the addition of the AnŚu and Adabhya, and also five Vajapeya or Aindra cups; there are added a dappled barren cow for the Maruts, and seventeen goats for Prajapati, hornless but capable of procreation. The sacrificer, his wife, and the priest all wear garlands of gold, which form the fees. The special features of the rite begin with the midday pressing, at which a warrior with seventeen arrows measures out a course for a race, marking the place where the last falls with a twig of Udumbara. Then three horses of the sacrificer are yoked to his chariot, sixteen others are yoked with four horses each, and the sacrificer is victorious in a formal race, during which 17 drums are beaten, and the Brahman climbs up a post, on which is fastened a wheel of Udumbara wood, to sing the Saman of the strong steeds, while the wheel is turned to the right. The horses are given, before and after the race, the offering to Bṛhaspati to smell, to gain its strength. In the second place, along with the cups of Soma there are offered by the Neṣtṛ alternatively cups of Sura, which are purchased from a long-haired man and placed in a special place. Mention is also made of a cup&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14 The Royal Consecration</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/14_The_Royal_Consecration/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/14_The_Royal_Consecration/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The royal consecration is a Soma sacrifice having the usual Dikṣā and Upasad days and preceded by a long series of preparatory rites. It is mythically connected with the consecration of Varuna or with Indra, and it&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1 Rel. des Veda, p. 470.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Keith, Taittiriya Samhita, i. pp. cviii-cxi.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For the sun-wheel see Cook, Zeus, i. 197 ff.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;TB. ii. 7. 6. 1; CB. v. 1. 1. 18. See Macdonell and Keith, Vedic Index, ii. 256.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 The Horse Sacrifice</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/15_The_Horse_Sacrifice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/15_The_Horse_Sacrifice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The horse sacrifice is in the ritual reckoned an Ahina, that is a rite with more than one day on which the Soma is pressed, in this case three. It is an old and famous rite, which kings alone can bring, to increase their realms: we have lists of the great kings of old 5 who were consecrated and who performed the horse sacrifice. The horse chosen must be swift, in front black, behind white, and with a dark mark. The offering begins on the 8th or 9th of Phalguna or in summer. On that day a mess of rice is cooked for the priests, and the king, his four wives, and their four hundred maidens of different ranks&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 The Human Sacrifice</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/16_The_Human_Sacrifice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/16_The_Human_Sacrifice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The human sacrifice as prescribed in two of the ritual texts 2 is based closely on the horse sacrifice; while there the chief victims are the horse, a Gomṛga, and a hornless goat, here a man is added, a Brahman or Kṣatriya bought at the price of a thousand cows and a hundred cattle, and he is permitted like the horse a year of freedom, in which he can do as he wishes, save that he must remain chaste. The offering is to be performed by a Brahman or a Kṣatriya who is not successful. When slain, the chief queen must lie beside the victim as beside the horse: the attempt to find a reference to this practice in the Rigveda 3 is a failure. On the other hand the nominal offering of large numbers of other men, 166 at 11 posts, is mentioned by the Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa, but we have every reason to assume that this is mere priestly imagination, unless, as is possible, the conceptions of the priest were occasionally made real by a king. It is laid down 5 that a king may on this occasion give up his goods and enter into the life of the wandering mendicant, but this seems merely to have been a facultative rule. It must, however, be noted that the rite of an actual slaying of man is not described in the Brāhmaṇas at all: there is in the Śatapatha and the Taittiriya and their Sūtras merely the symbolic offering of men, who are let free like the wild animals at the horse sacrifice, and therefore the actual offering rests merely on Sūtra evidence, the Vaitāna and Śãñkhāyana, and not even on the early Sutras. It is not credible that the Brāhmaṇas should have passed over the rite if they had actually known of it; its mention in the later Sutras is consistent only with the invention of it, as a reasonable complement to the theory of sacrifice which saw an anomaly in the omission of man from the victims.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17 Other Ahina Rites</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/17_Other_Ahina_Rites/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/17_Other_Ahina_Rites/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While the human sacrifice occupies five pressing days, the universal sacrifice, Sarvamedha,3 takes ten, and it is modelled on the offering made of himself by Brahman Svayambhu, in the beginning of things. Its relation to the human sacrifice is held to be the perfection of the former at the human sacrifice, according to Śañkhāyana, the offerer gives away the kingdom with the people at this he gives the earth away also, and in Hillebrandt&amp;rsquo;s view the rite marked the act by which the king left the royal life for the ascetic, as the Buddha afterwards did. It is, however, difficult to take the offering seriously it is based on myth, and seems no more than a purely priestly fiction this is borne out by the fact that it is mentioned only in the latest Sutras, though it figures in the legend of Naciketas.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>18 The Sattras or Sacrificial Sessions</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/18_The_Sattras_or_Sacrificial_Sessions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/18_The_Sattras_or_Sacrificial_Sessions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The rite of twelve days, DvadaŚaha, may be performed either as an Ahina or a Sattra, and all rites with more than twelve pressing days are Sattras the number of years they may be continued extends to thirty-six or more up to 1,000. The Sattras all differ from other forms of the Soma sacrifice, because all the performers must be consecrated and must be Brahmans there is therefore no separate sacrificer: all share in the benefits of the offering each bears the burden of his own errors, whereas at the ordinary sacrifice the sacrificer receives the benefit and the evil results of errors alike. Moreover, they should usually be Brahmans who perform the same kinds of rites, and have the same deity, Tanúnapāt or NaraŚañsa, at the Apri invocation; if not, the deity of the majority is adopted. During the Sattra all other sacrifices cease to be performed by the priests taking part in the rite any sexual intercourse is forbidden, as are swift movements, laughing without holding the hand before the mouth, untruth, connexions with non-Aryans, and so forth. One of them plays the part of sacrificer: the others hold on to him when he does those acts which only one man can perform. The Adhvaryu consecrates the sacrificer, and so on until a student consecrates the Unnetr. The wives of the priests are also consecrated each with her husband. There are no fees instead the priests go south saying as they shake black skins, &amp;lsquo;What here from my life departeth, that, O Agada, I bring to thee as a fee,&amp;rsquo; evidently a device to secure long life. The aims of the Sattras are most&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>19 The Sautrāmaṇī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/19_The_sautrAmaNI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/19_The_sautrAmaNI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Sautrāmaṇi 6 is not a Soma sacrifice, but is classified by the Sutras as a Haviryajña, though its chief characteristic in its form as recorded is the offering of Sura. It has two distinct forms, the Kaukili, which is an independent offering, the other the Caraka, an offering which forms part of another&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is clearly the wedding of sun and earth, a form of that of sky and earth; cf. Brunnhofer, Arische Urzeit, pp. 325- 7; Cook, Zeus, i. 526 ff., 604, 672, 709, 733.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>20 The Piling of the Fire</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/20_The_Piling_of_the_Fire/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/20_The_Piling_of_the_Fire/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The piling of the fire altar is a rite which is regarded as being always available for performance along with the Soma sacrifice, but which is declared to be obligatory only in certain cases, including the Mahāvrata, and even that view is far from being universally prescribed. There can be no doubt that it was by no means a normal or frequent rite: its elaboration is such that no ordinary sacrificer would trouble himself with it, and it must have been only occasionally used. The main authority for it in the Śatapatha Brahmaṇa is a different authority from the chief source of rules on the rest of the sacrificial ritual including the Soma sacrifice, Yajñavalkya: it is attributed to Śandilya, and others mentioned in connexion with it are Tura Kāvaṣeya,3 who performed it on the Karoti, and Nagnajit Gandhāra, names which have been held with some force to point to the North-West, where in conjunction with the fire cult there may have been special activity, perhaps in consequence of contact with Iran.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>21 The Hotr Formulae</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/21_The_Hotr_Formulae/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/21_The_Hotr_Formulae/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The ritual requires in many places the use of the Hotṛ formulae, which are formulae in which the priests are mentioned as being identical with deities and other objects, the formulae being distinguished according to the number of priests so mentioned as Caturhotṛ, Pañcahotṛ, and so on. They are termed offerings, because they represent various sacrifices from the Agnihotra to the Soma offering inclusive. They are often used in the course of important rites, in which case they are normally assigned to the sacrificer, but also they can be employed independently, either by themselves or with the accompaniment of cups of some offering and the cry Svaha. Thus a man, who wishes cattle, must for twelve nights drink hot water, put on a fresh garment and sleep on the ground. Early next morning he goes east, says the DaŚahotṛ, and offers the Caturhotṛ with butter. They can even be used as spells, in which case an offering is made on salt ground, or a break in the earth, and in place of the ordinary Vasat-call harsh words like khat or phat are used. This use is clearly an abuse the formulae are of the nature of Upanisads, and must be treated as representing the desire to substitute mental processes for the tediousness of the sacrifice. But it was inevitable that even they should sink to magic uses.2&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>22 The Expiations</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/22_The_Expiations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/20_THE_SACRIFICES_OF_THE_CRAUTA_RITUAL/22_The_Expiations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the intolerable complications of the Vedic sacrifice, coupled with the tendency to inaccuracy of the Indian mind of the Vedic period, may be found ample excuse for the number of prescriptions which are laid down for the purpose of expiating errors in the sacrifice. In some cases the expiations are elaborate in the extreme in most they are fairly simple. Of the former the most notorious case is that of the Kuṣmaṇḍa, which serves as a means of purification from grave sins, and which is dealt with in detail in the Taittiriya Aranyaka, whereas most of the other expiations are confined to the Sutras or to the later portions of the Brahmaṇas.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
