<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;18 THE NATURE OF THE VEDIC SACRIFICE on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/18_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_VEDIC_SACRIFICE/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;18 THE NATURE OF THE VEDIC SACRIFICE on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/18_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_VEDIC_SACRIFICE/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 The Sacrifice as a Gift</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/18_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_VEDIC_SACRIFICE/1_The_Sacrifice_as_a_Gift/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/18_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_VEDIC_SACRIFICE/1_The_Sacrifice_as_a_Gift/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As we have seen, the Vedic pantheon is essentially a body of great and powerful gods before whom the worshipper realizes to the full his comparative weakness and inability to exist satisfactorily without their constant aid. By the most simple logic he applies to the powers divine the same principle which he applies to other more powerful men, or which are applied to him by his inferiors. He seeks to propitiate them by the process of giving gifts.1 Doubtless, beside this view of the relation of man to the gods, there existed the belief that he could do much for himself by the power of the magic art, which we need not doubt flourished as much then as in later India, and against demons of all kinds magic is freely employed, but the essential distinction of magic and religion is plainly to be seen in the whole of the Vedic religion. Often too in place of using magic, or still oftener in supplement of magic, the aid of the gods is employed in the battle with the demons. In the case of one of the higher gods alone is there any trace of other than a relation of friendship: the aim of the worshipper is to satiate Rudra and to avert his dangerous presence: this fact, which expresses itself in the ritual in many ways, makes a certain degree of difference between the case of Rudra and the other gods, though occasionally some of these, such as Varuṇa, show slight traces of a similar conception of their nature to that of Rudra.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2 The Sacrifice as a Spell</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/18_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_VEDIC_SACRIFICE/2_The_Sacrifice_as_a_Spell/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/18_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_VEDIC_SACRIFICE/2_The_Sacrifice_as_a_Spell/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the theosophy of the Brahmaṇas it is an accepted fact that the sacrifice has a magic power of its own, and that it brings about the effects at which it aims with absolute independence: the old idea of the working upon the good will of a deity has disappeared, and in the philosophy of the Pūrva Mīmānsā,o which is the logical outcome of the Brāhmaṇas, the idea of god is effectively disposed of. But the theosophy of the Brahmaṇas is of no value as religion, and the question arises whether the Rigveda shows any real trace of the belief in the magic efficacy of the sacrifice. Much of the evidence which has been adduced by both Bergaigne and Geldner 10 for the view that the priests claim to control the gods, to capture them in the net of the sacrifice, and make them do their bidding, is clearly without weight: the simple imagery of the poets cannot be pressed to mean more than it says. The later literature, which regards the priest as powerful to control the gods, openly says so,11 and provides the believer with magic devices in order to bind hard the Adityas until they&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4 Communion and Sacrament in the Sacrifice</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/18_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_VEDIC_SACRIFICE/4_Communion_and_Sacrament_in_the_Sacrifice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/18_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_VEDIC_SACRIFICE/4_Communion_and_Sacrament_in_the_Sacrifice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While in the view of Sir J. Frazer the essence of early sacrifice is the magic art of perpetuating the life of the herds and of vegetation and even of man, the gift theory of sacrifice has also been declared to be merely derivative, on the ground that it is really a faded remnant of the sacrifice in which the worshippers eat together of the flesh and blood of the deity, thus renewing and strengthening the bonds between themselves on the one hand and the god on the other. That such a form of sacrifice existed is beyond all doubt attested for the Semites, but not for the Babylonians, and there are traces of it in Greek&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 The Materials of the Sacrifice</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/18_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_VEDIC_SACRIFICE/5_The_Materials_of_the_Sacrifice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/18_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_VEDIC_SACRIFICE/5_The_Materials_of_the_Sacrifice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On the gift theory of sacrifice it is natural that man should offer what he delights to feed upon, and in point of fact this undoubtedly is the rule in the great majority of cases: the Vedic Indians practised agricultural as well as pastoral pursuits, and we find therefore that they offered to the gods, not only milk in its various forms, as curd or melted butter in several varieties, but also grain, barley and rice, which served to make different kinds of cakes, or were mixed with milk or curds to form variegated messes. These materials served to satisfy many needs, but the animal and the Soma offerings were of still greater consequence in the eyes of the priest, though they must have been numerically very few in comparison with the sacrifices of simple materials.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>6 Fire and Sacrifice</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/18_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_VEDIC_SACRIFICE/6_Fire_and_Sacrifice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/18_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_VEDIC_SACRIFICE/6_Fire_and_Sacrifice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The constant interrelation of magic and religion in the Vedic cult is seen in its most complete form in the position of the fire, which serves the double end of the mode in which the sacrifice is brought to the gods, and of the most effective agency for the banning of evil spirits. The Vedic hymns show clearly enough the enormous value of the fire for the driving away of the Rakṣases, and the ritual bears this out in the most marked manner. There is lighted a special fire, the Sūtikāgni, in place of the normal fire for the woman in childbirth it is not used for any offering except for the fumigation of the newly born infant and the warming of dishes, but its object of driving off evil spirits is attested by the list of evil spirits who are banned in the ritual. The haircutting of the child is likewise performed to the west of a fire, which is not used for any offering, though utensils of the rite are put around it. The teacher initiates his pupil and girds on the sacred girdle, which marks his second birth, in the presence of a fire, but in this case the making of an offering in it shows the tendency to mingle religion and magic: the recitation goes on in the presence of a fire. Such a fire is absolutely essential, when the passages recited are of special importance and therefore holiness.&amp;quot; The consecration of the offerer of Soma takes place before a fire; after a death, fire is used to drive away the evil powers, fire is used even in battle, the third of the holy fires of the ritual seems to have been intended from the first to drive away evil spirits: the south is the region of the Fathers and of the demons akin to them, and, when it is being used for offerings to the Fathers, a brand is taken out from it to drive away the evil spirits, which seek to have a share in the sacrifice, 10&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>7 The Performers of the Sacrifice</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/18_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_VEDIC_SACRIFICE/7_The_Performers_of_the_Sacrifice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/18_THE_NATURE_OF_THE_VEDIC_SACRIFICE/7_The_Performers_of_the_Sacrifice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As we have seen, it is an essential part of the Vedic sacrifice that it is a sacrifice for an individual, the Yajamāna, or sacrificer, who provides the means for the sacrifice, and above all the rich rewards for the priests. The king is naturally the chief of sacrificers, for him alone such sacrifices as the royal consecration could be offered, but there are others, members of the royal house, high officers and soldiers among the Kṣatriyas, rich merchants or&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
