<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Nikhil on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/nikhil/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Nikhil on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/nikhil/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>gosava</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/nikhil/gosava/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/nikhil/gosava/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For what it&amp;rsquo;s worth, the ritual does not explicitly præscribe an actual act of incest, just approaching the women with sexual intent.  The phrasing is upá mātáram iyād upá svásāram upá ságotrām (JB 2.113, ĀpŞS 22.13.2, HŞS 17.5.25), with upá √i meaning &amp;ldquo;approach&amp;rdquo; often used in a sexual context.  The translation in the attached image (by an Indian) overstates the original language.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In any case I think this ritual should be a lesson to Vedists that far from expanding Vedism to include the Āraṇyaká-s and the Upaniṣád-s, even certain Brā́hmaṇa-s must sometimes be taken with great suspicion—not being Divinely inspired poëtry, but the words of people who composed and (sometimes centuries later) passed down Divine poëtry&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>nikhil on puruShamedha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/nikhil/nikhil_on_human-sacrifice_in_puruShamedha_chayana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/nikhil/nikhil_on_human-sacrifice_in_puruShamedha_chayana/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The story of Şúnaşşépa from the Āitareya-brāhmaná indicates an unambiguously literal man-sacrifice, and is attested in the Sáṁhitā itself via the hymns of the R̥g-vedá authored by Şúnaşşépa, which make references to his impending doom, as well as R̥g-vedá 5.2.7.  The literal man-sacrifice also survived well into the Sū́tra æra, with both the Şāṅkhāyana-şrāuta-sūtrá (16.13.7) and the Vāitāna-şrāuta-sūtrá (7.2.26) explicitly mentioning a suffocated victim in their coverage of the puruṣa-medhá.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
