<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;09 THE GREAT GODS-AERIAL on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/09_THE_GREAT_GODS-AERIAL/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;09 THE GREAT GODS-AERIAL on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/09_THE_GREAT_GODS-AERIAL/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Indra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/09_THE_GREAT_GODS-AERIAL/01_Indra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/09_THE_GREAT_GODS-AERIAL/01_Indra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;INDRA is the greatest god of the Rigveda, with the solitary exception of Varuna, who may be deemed to equal him in might.1 His connexion with the Soma offering is, however, far closer than that of Varuṇa; he is the subject of 250 hymns, or almost a quarter of the whole of the collection, and he shares with other deities at least fifty more. He is, however, like Varuṇa in one thing he is not a god whose physical nature overwhelms the anthropomorphism of the poets: he has, therefore, become the subject of many myths, which it would be idle to seek to bring into any connexion whatever with the normal basis of his nature.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Trita Āptya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/09_THE_GREAT_GODS-AERIAL/02_Trita_Aptya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/09_THE_GREAT_GODS-AERIAL/02_Trita_Aptya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Trita Aptya is a deity, whose importance in the Rigveda is much less great than the account of the feats attributed to him would at first sight seem to warrant. He is not the subject of any hymn, and his name is mentioned no more than forty times in all. His associations are predominantly with Indra, but also with the Maruts, Agni, and Soma. The name Aptya belongs to him seven times in four hymns.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Apam Na pāt</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/09_THE_GREAT_GODS-AERIAL/03_apAM_napAt/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/09_THE_GREAT_GODS-AERIAL/03_apAM_napAt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Apam Ne pāt&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The deity Apāṁ Napāt, &amp;rsquo; child of the waters,&amp;rsquo; is more distinguished than Trita Aptya by being the subject of one whole hymn in the Rigveda, where his name occurs some thirty times in all. He is essentially connected with the waters, his relation being envisaged in diverse ways: three divine females desire to give him food, he sucks the milk of the first mothers, but he also engenders the embryo within them, as a bull. On the other hand he shines without fuel in the waters; clothed in the lightning he mounts upright the lap of the shining waters; around him the swift golden-coloured waters go. He is golden in form, he comes from a golden womb. His food is ghee, he has in his home a cow which gives him milk. He dwells in the highest place, and grows in secret, and in the hymn addressed to him he is directly identified with the god Agni, but elsewhere, though associated with Agni, he is distinguished from him. In the ritual he is connected with the waters; when the priests go for the waters required for the sacrifice, it is to Apāṁ Napāt that they address their prayer, and to him they offer butter in order to procure suitable waters; offerings are likewise made to him in the case when the sacrificial victim perishes in water, or when the Kārīrīṣṭi, a rain spell, is performed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Ahi Budhnya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/09_THE_GREAT_GODS-AERIAL/04_Ahi_Budhnya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/09_THE_GREAT_GODS-AERIAL/04_Ahi_Budhnya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ahi Budhnya, &amp;rsquo;the serpent of the deep&amp;rsquo;, is closely associated in the few cases, twelve in all, in which his name is found in the Rigveda with the gods Aja Ekapād, Apāṁ Napāt, the ocean, and Savitṛ. His name never occurs save in the hymns to the All-gods, and there it is regularly found among the spirits of the atmosphere, and in the Naighaṇṭuka &amp;rsquo; he is definitely assigned to the middle or aerial region. The only definite traits ascribed to him are that he is born of the waters, sitting at the bottom of the streams in the spaces, language which the normal spirit of the Rigveda no less than the express assertion of Yāska &amp;amp; induces us to refer to the ocean of the air, and not to the earthly waters. His dangerous character is hinted at by the fact that he is implored not to give over his worshippers to evil.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 Matariśvan</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/09_THE_GREAT_GODS-AERIAL/06_matarishvan/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/09_THE_GREAT_GODS-AERIAL/06_matarishvan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The god Mātariśvan, unlike the one-footed goat and the dragon of the deep, is not an ancient god: his name occurs but twenty-seven times in the whole of the Rigveda, and of these instances twenty-one are found in the latest parts of the Rigveda: he occurs five times in book iii, so that he seems to have been a favourite of the Viśvāmitra family, and once in book vi. His connexion with Agni is of the closest: his name is thrice applied to Agni, and it is said of Agni1As germ of the heaven he is named Tanūnapāt; when born he becometh Narāśansa; when in his mother he was fashioned as Mātariśvan, he became the wind&amp;rsquo;s swift flight.&amp;rsquo; He is also identified with Bṛhaspati, and the poets who divide the one into many are said to call it Agni, Yama, Mātariśvan. On the other hand Agni appears as distinct from Mātariśvan : Agni appears to him and to Vivasvant, Mātariśvan brings Agni to Bhṛgu : he brings Agni from the sky, from afar for men, or from the gods. He is also said to produce him by friction and to set him up in human abodes. He is occasionally mentioned in connexion with Indra, and he serves as the messenger of Vivasvant between the heaven and the earth. In the wedding hymn he is asked with other deities to join the hearts of the husband and wife.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 Vayu and Vata</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/09_THE_GREAT_GODS-AERIAL/07_Vayu_and_Vata/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/09_THE_GREAT_GODS-AERIAL/07_Vayu_and_Vata/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The real wind gods of the Rigveda are Vāyu and Vāta, who differ however quite distinctly in character and in importance. Vayu has one whole hymn1 addressed to him, and shares half a dozen with Indra, while Vāta has only two short hymns in the tenth book. The former is the more anthropomorphized of the two gods; hence he is joined with Indra, while Vāta is associated with Parjanya, who in comparison with Indra is an elemental deity. The close connexion of Indra and Vāyu is seen in the fact that Yāska 3 gives Vāyu, or Indra, as the second member of the triad of gods, into which the Nairuktas reduced the Vedic pantheon.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 Parjanya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/09_THE_GREAT_GODS-AERIAL/08_Parjanya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/09_THE_GREAT_GODS-AERIAL/08_Parjanya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Parjanya, like Vata, is a god whose natural character is obvious and undeniable. He has three hymns in the Rigveda and his name occurs some thirty times, but in other passages it has beyond doubt the simple sense of rain cloud. More often, however, the rain cloud is made into a real person, often in theriomorphic shape: thus he is a bull who roars and impregnates the plants, and his roaring waters delight the earth. But, as the waters are normally conceived as feminine, he becomes in other cases a barren cow, or even a productive cow. He is the rain giver, and is besought to bestow rain, but in his actions he is subject to the control of Mitra and Varuna. He also thunders and smites trees and evildoers in anger, and, when he quickens the earth with his seed, the winds blow, and the lightning flashes. He is often associated with Vata, as Vayu with Indra. As a rain god plants spring up through him, and he is also credited with the increase of cattle, of mares, and of women. He is even exalted as an independent monarch, the ruler of all the world, in whom are established the three worlds and all beings. From another point of view he is essentially the father, and even the divine father. &amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 The Waters</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/09_THE_GREAT_GODS-AERIAL/09_The_Waters/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/09_THE_GREAT_GODS-AERIAL/09_The_Waters/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Four hymns of the Rigveda and many verses praise the waters as goddesses,* but they have little personality and the element is nearly always plainly to be recognized. Their anthropomorphic form is the Apsaras, who will be treated below. They are mothers, or young wives: they flow in channels to the sea, but they are also celestial: they abide in the seat of the gods and of Mitra and Varuna: Varuṇa moves in the midst of them, looking down on the good and base deeds of men. In them Agni dwells and they are his mothers. They cleanse and purify the worshipper, even from moral sins such as lying, cursing, and violence. They bestow long life and wealth and immortality.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 Rudra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/09_THE_GREAT_GODS-AERIAL/10_Rudra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/09_THE_GREAT_GODS-AERIAL/10_Rudra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Still less than Viṣṇu has Rudra the greatness which in the later literature attends him. He is the subject of but three hymns in the Rigveda, shares one with Soma, and is mentioned in all only about seventy-five times. In the Rigveda he has braided hair, like Pūṣan, beautiful lips, firm limbs; his colour is brown, and he is multiform. He is essentially radiant (śuci), bright as the sun or gold, resplendent, the Asura of heaven; he wears golden ornaments and sits on a chariot seat. The Yajurveda and the Atharvaveda have much more to tell of his appearance: the latter calls his belly blue, his back red, his neck blue, and mentions his mouth and his teeth. The Yajurveda 7 calls him copper coloured and red, and his neck is blue-black (nilagriva), though his&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 The Maruts or Rudras</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/09_THE_GREAT_GODS-AERIAL/11_The_Maruts_or_Rudras/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/09_THE_GREAT_GODS-AERIAL/11_The_Maruts_or_Rudras/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Maruts share in the greatness of Indra, and, therefore, they have a prominent place in the Rigveda, thirty three-hymns being exclusively theirs, while they share seven with Indra, and one each with Puṣan and Agni. They are essentially a troupe, thrice seven or thrice sixty in number, the children&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1 Cf. Durga&amp;rsquo;s later patronage of Thugs (Garbe, Beitrāge zur ind. Kulturgeschichte, pp. 185 ff.), Hermes, patron of thieves, and Laverna in Rome (Roscher, Lex. I. ii. 2872; II. i. 1917).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
