<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;11 Mantras on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/11_Mantras/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;11 Mantras on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/11_Mantras/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 The Meaninglessness of Mantras</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/11_Mantras/01_The_Meaninglessness_of_Mantras/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/11_Mantras/01_The_Meaninglessness_of_Mantras/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mantras are not mysterious statements with deep meanings. They have no meaning because they are not statements and they are not statements because they are not language. Language is a human faculty which is concerned with &lt;em&gt;meaning&lt;/em&gt; in its primary sense. In natural language, the domain of meaning is part of an intricate system. We shall take a closer look at this system in the next section, but it may be illustrated first by three expressions of language, each belonging to a different category:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Language, Syntax and Recursiveness</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/11_Mantras/02_Language_Syntax_and_Recursiveness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/11_Mantras/02_Language_Syntax_and_Recursiveness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When I use the term ‘language’, what I have in mind is languages such as English or Sanskrit, modern or classical, world languages or tribal languages. Languages change and evolve over time. They are born and they die. They belong to or originate in a specific community though they may be adopted by others and become widespread. But language is a system in which everything hangs together, &lt;em&gt;où tout se tient&lt;/em&gt; as de Saussure put it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Steps Beyond Kautsa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/11_Mantras/03_Steps_Beyond_Kautsa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/11_Mantras/03_Steps_Beyond_Kautsa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Kautsa gave four reasons for the meaninglessness of mantras. (1) The sound of mantras may not be changed unlike in language where sounds may change provided meaning remains the same. (2) The order of elements in mantras may not be changed, unlike in Sanskrit where word order is to a large extent free. (3) If mantras were meaningful, it would have to be conceded that they are often contradictory or inconsistent with each other. That is not uncommon in language, where it is common for speakers to say different things, but it becomes an embarrassment when dealing with canon formation, i.e. the establishment of a source of authority. (4) There is a tradition to transmit the sounds of mantras but not their meanings, unlike the connection between sounds and meanings in language that is sometimes taught but generally picked up by children. It is the last reason with which I have been chiefly concerned in the previous section and to which we shall return most often.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Pragmatics, Speech Acts and Bird Song</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/11_Mantras/04_Pragmatics_Speech_Acts_and_Bird_Song/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/11_Mantras/04_Pragmatics_Speech_Acts_and_Bird_Song/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If mantras are not language, for the analysis of which specialized disciplines such as linguistics, philology or literary criticism have been developed, where do we find more adequate concepts and categories to study them successfully? Can we learn something from logic or philosophy?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A popular approach to the study of mantras has been &lt;em&gt;pragmatics&lt;/em&gt;. I am not referring to the pragmatism of William James, John Dewey or other philosophers, but to a discipline that is closely related to logic and that deals with so-called indexicals. Bertrand Russell called them ‘egocentric particulars’. These expressions of language do not refer to the outside world but to the speaker in his or her immediate context or situation. Examples are: ‘I’, ‘you’, ‘here’, ‘now’ or ‘to-morrow’. What is the difference between these and other expressions of language? If the reader and I say ‘tree’, both of us refer to the same thing. If we both say ‘I’, the reader refers to the reader and I refer to myself. If we say ‘you’, the reader refers to me and I refer to the reader. In both cases, we use the same words but do not refer to the same things.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 The Gāyatrī Mantra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/11_Mantras/05_The_gAyatrI_Mantra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/11_Mantras/05_The_gAyatrI_Mantra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Gāyatrī mantra is called after its metre (&lt;em&gt;Five: Rigveda&lt;/em&gt;): it consists of three verses of eight syllables which are long ‘—’ or short ‘^’ as in the following scheme:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/000022.png&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;How close mantras are to ritual is shown by the teaching of the Gāyatrī mantra which takes place during the initiation ritual of &lt;em&gt;upanayana&lt;/em&gt;. Similar in formation to &lt;em&gt;upaniṣad&lt;/em&gt; (‘sitting near’), &lt;em&gt;upanayana&lt;/em&gt; means ‘taking near’. ‘Near’ may again be to the teacher, here called &lt;em&gt;ācārya&lt;/em&gt;, or to the stage of studenthood after which the student is called a &lt;em&gt;brahmacārin&lt;/em&gt;. There are many ceremonies after which the teacher takes the boy’s hand and makes him look at the sun. After numerous other exchanges, variously described in various manuals, student and teacher sit north of a fire, the student facing east, that is, looking at the teacher, and the teacher facing west. The teacher then makes him repeat the first verse:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
