<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;05 Rigveda on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/05_Rigveda/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;05 Rigveda on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/05_Rigveda/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Gods, Composers and Metres</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/05_Rigveda/01_Gods_Composers_and_Metres/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/05_Rigveda/01_Gods_Composers_and_Metres/</guid>
      <description>The Rigveda is an anthology of poems, selected from the early traditions of families and clans and then gradually expanded. The reader is already familiar with some lines and phrases quoted in preceding chapters. We must now pay attention to a few topics that are practical and somewhat technical for us though they were of great significance to the composers.
The first is of our own making: our numerical references such as ‘7.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 A Speculative Poem</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/05_Rigveda/02_A_Speculative_Poem/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/05_Rigveda/02_A_Speculative_Poem/</guid>
      <description>I shall now fulfil a promise: RV 10.129 which presents itself without deity or poet. The poem belongs to the late Rigveda when the Veda reflected a great variety of ideas, cultures and sections of society. It mentions its metre: Triṣṭubh. It is not a puzzle or riddle like some other long poems of the same period, belonging to the first or the tenth circle. I would rather describe it as thinking aloud.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 The Scientific Study of the Veda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/05_Rigveda/03_The_Scientific_Study_of_the_Veda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/05_Rigveda/03_The_Scientific_Study_of_the_Veda/</guid>
      <description>In the last two chapters, we have looked at two controversies between Euro-American scholars about the Vedas. One is concerned with Vedic society, the other with the Soma. Both might seem to illustrate the irrelevance of infighting between Americans, Britons, Dutch- and Frenchmen to our august topic. But those inclined to think so would miss the point. The differences of opinion rest at least in part on categories that transcend contemporary national or political boundaries and are universal features of knowledge.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
