<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;05 Rigveda on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/05_Rigveda/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;05 Rigveda on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/05_Rigveda/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Gods, Composers and Metres</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/05_Rigveda/01_Gods_Composers_and_Metres/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/05_Rigveda/01_Gods_Composers_and_Metres/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Rigveda is an anthology of poems, selected from the early traditions of families and clans and then gradually expanded. The reader is already familiar with some lines and phrases quoted in preceding chapters. We must now pay attention to a few topics that are practical and somewhat technical for us though they were of great significance to the composers.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The first is of our own making: our numerical references such as ‘7.64.4’ or ‘10.135’. In the first, ‘4’ refers to a verse (&lt;em&gt;rḳ&lt;/em&gt;) or line of a verse, ‘64’ to the poem and ‘7’ to the ‘circle’ (&lt;em&gt;maṇḍala&lt;/em&gt;) of the Rigveda. If there are only two numbers as in ‘10.135,’ they refer to a circle and a poem. Recall that there are ten circles so that the first number should always be one of these. The early ‘family traditions’ are mostly of circles 2 to 7, the core of the Rigveda. Metaphysical speculations such as ‘1.164’, occur in circles 1 and 10 which contain the latest parts of the Rigveda and additions of various sorts such as 10.90.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 A Speculative Poem</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/05_Rigveda/02_A_Speculative_Poem/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/05_Rigveda/02_A_Speculative_Poem/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I shall now fulfil a promise: RV 10.129 which presents itself without deity or poet. The poem belongs to the late Rigveda when the Veda reflected a great variety of ideas, cultures and sections of society. It mentions its metre: Triṣṭubh. It is not a puzzle or riddle like some other long poems of the same period, belonging to the first or the tenth circle. I would rather describe it as thinking aloud. I shall quote its most recent and reliable translation, that of 1999 by Joel Brereton, adding Wendy Doniger’s sage comment on poems that puzzle: ‘Good. They are meant to puzzle.’&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 The Scientific Study of the Veda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/05_Rigveda/03_The_Scientific_Study_of_the_Veda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/05_Rigveda/03_The_Scientific_Study_of_the_Veda/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the last two chapters, we have looked at two controversies between Euro-American scholars about the Vedas. One is concerned with Vedic society, the other with the Soma. Both might seem to illustrate the irrelevance of infighting between Americans, Britons, Dutch- and Frenchmen to our august topic. But those inclined to think so would miss the point. The differences of opinion rest at least in part on categories that transcend contemporary national or political boundaries and are universal features of knowledge. Dumézil exhibits not nationalism but rationalism, Wasson combines rationalism with empiricism in another discipline, Gonda empiricism, and Brough comes closest to combining both. Of course, a good rationalist respects the facts and a good empiricist respects logic, otherwise they would not be scientists or thinkers—in any civilization.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
