<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;28 THE PHILOSOPHY OF THE UPANISADS on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/28_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_UPANISADS/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;28 THE PHILOSOPHY OF THE UPANISADS on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/28_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_UPANISADS/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 The Origin of the Upanisads</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/28_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_UPANISADS/01_The_Origin_of_the_Upanisads/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/28_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_UPANISADS/01_The_Origin_of_the_Upanisads/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;NATIVE tradition1 derives the term Upanisad, by means which will not bear scrutiny, from roots which yield as its sense either that which destroys innate ignorance, or that which leads to the Brahman. It is more important to note that from an early period the utmost stress is laid on the secret character of the instruction contained in these works: the rule is that they are the highest mysteries, and that their doctrines should not be imparted to any pupil, other than a son, who has not already studied with the teacher for a year and who does not intend himself to become a teacher. The same view is enforced by the facts recounted in the texts: when the deepest part of the discussions arrives, the two concerned go apart and talk of the new doctrine of action as the source of human fate.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 The Extant Upanisads</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/28_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_UPANISADS/02_The_Extant_Upanisads/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/28_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_UPANISADS/02_The_Extant_Upanisads/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The texts which have come down to us are certainly not the beginning of the intellectual activity of the time: they bear every trace in their manner and matter of representing the result of many discussions, and deviations of opinion among the priestly schools. The doctrines have been handled and&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A. E. Gough in his Philosophy of the Upanishads explains their demerits as due to racial intermixture.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For a recent claim for the Dravidians, see G. W. Brown, Studies in honor of Bloomfield, pp. 75 ff. Frazer (ERE. 8. v.) states the case for intermingling&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 The Interpretation of the Upanisads</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/28_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_UPANISADS/03_The_Interpretation_of_the_Upanisads/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/28_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_UPANISADS/03_The_Interpretation_of_the_Upanisads/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It was attempted by the great philosopher Śankara to find in the Upani- ṣads the expression of a single simple doctrine, carried out consistently through all, and in his commentary on the Vedanta as set out in the Brahma Sūtra of Badarāyaṇa it is his object to interpret that Sutra and to bring out at the same time the doctrines of the Upanisṣads, the whole forming a great system of philosophy in which no contradictions should exist. The plan adopted by the philosopher for this purpose was simple: he found in the Upanisads the principle that knowledge was of two kinds, wholly different. On the one hand the higher knowledge recognized the existence of absolutely nothing save the Brahman or the Atman, the one unity, which was at once real, thought, and bliss. The force of these terms must be understood in a special sense reality is not something outside the Brahman: no predication is possible of the Brahman, for predication involves diversity and in the Brahman there is no diversity. Thought or consciousness, which is not an attribute of, but the essence of the Brahman, does not mean actual activity, the vous voyoews of Aristotle on the most probable view of that famous doctrine: it is consciousness without any object or subject, and therefore differs so entirely from the very nature of consciousness as not in our view to deserve the name at all. The bliss also is that of being which has no consciousness of any kind and no feeling, and therefore is merely a metaphorical expression. This single thing is all that the world really is, the one Brahman which is the Atman. All the multiplicity of phenomena is unreal: the saving truth which redeems the individual from the constant stream of births is the recognition of this fact, that he himself is really the one Atman, not related as part to it, but solely and absolutely it. In the expression That thou art&amp;quot;,&amp;quot; which is enunciated in the Upanisads, is set out the fundamental fact of all existence, the indivisible unity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 The Problem and Conditions of Knowledge</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/28_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_UPANISADS/04_The_Problem_and_Conditions_of_Knowledge/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/28_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_UPANISADS/04_The_Problem_and_Conditions_of_Knowledge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is an essential feature of the Upanisads that, though they make, as we have seen, little or no advance in logical doctrine, they do tentatively raise and deal in some measure with the question of the source of knowledge of the Brahman or Atman. The view of the Brahmaṇas, of course, is that knowledge is to be found in the Vedas, and the authority of the Vedic texts is not discussed. In the Upanisads, however, we find that the question of the means of knowledge is definitely raised: the three Vedas or the four, which are sometimes recognized, are not always recognized as the sources of complete knowledge Cvetaketu, despite much Vedic learning, cannot solve the question of transmigration, Narada admits to Sanatkumāra his incompetence to understand the Atman. The Taittiriya Upanisad1 expressly reduces the knowledge&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 The Nature of the Absolute</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/28_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_UPANISADS/05_The_Nature_of_the_Absolute/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/28_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_UPANISADS/05_The_Nature_of_the_Absolute/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Upanisads are essentially concerned with the endeavour to describe the nature of the absolute, and the rich abundance of attempts to succeed in this end, proved by the references to conflicting theories in the Upanisads, is clear proof of the busy mental activity of the period. From the earliest Upanisad we have, the view is clear that there is a unity, that it is necessary further to grasp the nature of that unity, and that the proper names of the unity are either the Brahman or the Atman. The two ideas whose history we have seen in the Brahmanas are used constantly in alternation with each other. It is clear that they must have been felt to be practically akin.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 The Absolute and the Universe</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/28_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_UPANISADS/06_The_Absolute_and_the_Universe/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/28_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_UPANISADS/06_The_Absolute_and_the_Universe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The theory of Yajnavalkya asserts, as we have seen, that the absolute is unknowable and not definable by any empirical predicates. It, therefore, becomes obviously a pressing question to connect the empirical and the real universes: the gulf between the two is only accentuated by asserting, in so determined a manner, that there is a deep division between the one and the many. The relation of the universe as known to the one is, however, the problem which all philosophies find insoluble in greater or less degree, and the efforts of the Upaniṣads to bridge the difference are not at all satisfactory. The answer given in fact is merely that the absolute is the same as the world, or that the world is the product of the Brahman. The difficulty, however, arises, in considering these passages of the Upanisads, which present the doctrines of cosmogonism and pantheism in close and inextricable union, to know whether we have here efforts to explain the Brahman understood in the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 Māyā and Prakṛti-Illusion and Nature</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/28_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_UPANISADS/07_mAyA_and_prakRti-illusion_and_Nature/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/28_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_UPANISADS/07_mAyA_and_prakRti-illusion_and_Nature/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(a) ILLUSION&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the doctrine of Yajnavalkya we have seen the tendency of the Upani- ṣads to assert over again, and in still more emphatic terms, the unity of the world, which the poets of the Rigveda already foreshadowed, and to deduce from it the conclusion that the world is nothing that is real in the full sense of the word, since everything in it is not ultimately to be regarded as having a truth of its own. In what sense, then, can the empiric world be said to exist? This Yājñavalkya leaves vague, but in his exposition to Maitreyi of the doctrine that after death there is no consciousness he uses terms to which later at least great weight was attached. A duality is necessary, he argued, for one to see another, smell another, hear another, and so forth, and in death no such duality is present; the phrase, however, which he uses in this contention is &amp;lsquo;where there is a duality as it were (iva)&amp;rsquo;, and it may be deduced, not unfairly, from the addition of the qualification that he was not prepared to admit as absolutely certain the existence of the duality. Later in the Upani- ṣad we have similar wording, &amp;lsquo;when there seems to be another&amp;rsquo;, the same&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 The Supreme and the Individual Souls</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/28_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_UPANISADS/08_The_Supreme_and_the_Individual_Souls/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/28_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_UPANISADS/08_The_Supreme_and_the_Individual_Souls/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the philosophy of Yajñavalkya the identity of the supreme and the individual souls is carried to the extreme extent, but at the same time the term soul is deprived of any distinct meaning. The identity of the soul of man and the absolute is due to the mere fact that, by reducing the soul to nothing save what may be termed the mere abstraction of subjectivity, or of the transcendental unity of apperception, the soul becomes nothing but an aspect of a process. It is perfectly legitimate then to identify the supreme and the individual souls, but we are really carried no further by this than the occasional remarks of the Bṛhadaranyaka Upaniṣad, which regards the universe as made up of nothing except subject and object. It is in fact perfectly true that all the world can be regarded as distinguished as subject and object, but, unless we are able to show that this is the sum total of all that we can know, it is clearly impossible for philosophy to stop there. The actual existing world of thought, emotion, and action requires explanation and investigation. In the Vedanta the matter is solved comfortably by the doctrine of the two forms of knowledge: on the upper stage the identity of the self and the absolute is recognized, on the lower there is found to be a personal deity, Hiranyagarbha, and personal selves, who are indeed the absolute self, but fall under the influence of conditioning facts, the Upadhis, mind, the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 The Four States of the Soul</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/28_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_UPANISADS/09_The_Four_States_of_the_Soul/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/28_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_UPANISADS/09_The_Four_States_of_the_Soul/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The soul, despite its close connexion with the body, which we have traced in detail, is also enabled by its nature to approach closely the absolute. The spirit is most remote from the absolute in its normal waking activities: in that case the senses and the mind are at work, but when there is sleep the senses and the mind are merged in the breath. A further distinction is then made between the condition of the soul in the sleep of dreams, and in deep dreamless sleep, in which the soul enters into the purest light, and then as a consequence of its own nature emerges again from it. These three stages alone are found in the oldest Upanisads, and it is not till the latest Upanisads that a fourth is added in accordance with the constant tendency further to subdivide.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 The Doctrine of Transmigration</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/28_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_UPANISADS/10_The_Doctrine_of_Transmigration/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/28_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_UPANISADS/10_The_Doctrine_of_Transmigration/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The origin of the doctrine of transmigration is one of the most difficult problems of Indian philosophy: its extraordinarily firm hold on the mind of part at least of India, which is shown by the fact that Buddhism rests on the doctrine as an essential presupposition, makes it natural to seck the view in the earliest period of Indian religion, and this desire to find metempsychosis in the beginnings of Indian belief takes two forms. On the one hand there have been seen direct references to metempsychosis in the Rigveda, and on the other there have been traced there ideas which explain the genesis of the conception.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 The Way of Salvation</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/28_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_UPANISADS/11_The_Way_of_Salvation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/28_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_UPANISADS/11_The_Way_of_Salvation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the view of the Buddhist the world is misery, and the whole end of man is to remove the misery of existence from himself by the destruction of that desire, which leads ever from birth to birth. But the wholesale pessimism of the Buddhist is by no means characteristic of the Upanisṣads: to find real pessimism in them, as apart from mild expressions of the unsatisfactoriness of the finite compared with the infinite, is impossible. It is also impossible, therefore, to trace to the empirical despair of the world the growth of pessimism; the most that in this regard can be said is that the tendency to take a pessimistic view of life may have been favoured among the upper classes of the Indians by the effect of the climate and admixture with the aborigines, which was steadily taking place and was weakening the mental character of the racc. Of the latter fact there can be no doubt the genius of the Upanisads is different from that of the Rigveda, however many ties may connect the two periods. The emancipation theories of the Upaniṣads must, therefore, be traced to some more intellectual ground.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 The Ethics of the Upanisads and Yoga</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/28_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_UPANISADS/12_The_Ethics_of_the_Upanisads_and_Yoga/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/28_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_UPANISADS/12_The_Ethics_of_the_Upanisads_and_Yoga/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In comparison with the intellectual activity of the Brahmans the ethical content of the Upanisads must be said to be negligible and valueless. The total impression conveyed by the Upanisads is that of an intellectual exercise, whose aim was the attainment partly of immediate goods, partly of the highest good, normally the happiness of heaven which was often materially enough conceived, and there is made no attempt to make the theoretical philosophy a ground of morality of any sort. There are, here and there, moral maxims enunciated, but these are of no consequence and rise in no way above popular morality. On the contrary, the essential fact is expressed by Indra in his dialogue with Pratardana: the possession of knowledge makes a man independent of all morality, the slaying of an embryo, the murder of a&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 The Significance of the Philosophy of the Upanisads</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/28_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_UPANISADS/13_The_Significance_of_the_Philosophy_of_the_Upani/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/28_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_UPANISADS/13_The_Significance_of_the_Philosophy_of_the_Upani/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What judgement are we to pass on the main thought of the Upanisads? Are they really the expressions at an early date of the deepest principles of philosophy, or are they merely of historical value, interesting pictures of the early thought of man, important not per se, but because of their dominating influence on the future philosophy and life of India? The two interpreters, who have of recent times been most impressed by the nature of that philosophy as idealism, have passed the most diametrically opposed views on the question: Gough was impressed with the necessity of explaining the defects of the subject of which he treated by the admixture of blood among the Indians, and the corrupting influences of a low order of civilization, while Deussen is lost in admiration of the Upanisads, as was Schopenhauer before him: &amp;lsquo;Eternal philosophical truth&amp;rsquo;, he says, &amp;lsquo;has seldom found more decisive and striking expression than in the doctrine of the emancipating knowledge of the Atman &amp;rsquo; He claims that Yajñavalkya had anticipated the view of Schopenhauer regarding immortality as indestructibility without continued existence; he regards the view of the nature of the self as an anticipation of the doctrine of Kant; he defends the doctrine of transmigration as the best expression of the true state of matters in the terms of empirical thought, while recognizing that such an expression is misleading: nay, he argues that the Kantian argument regarding immortality, based on the realization of the moral law within us, points not to ordinary immortality, but rather to the process of transmigration, and transmigration has been solemnly upheld as philosophic doctrine at the present time by competent authorities at the present time by competent authorities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
