<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;15 Vedic Insights on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/15_Vedic_Insights/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;15 Vedic Insights on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/15_Vedic_Insights/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Towards Universality</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/15_Vedic_Insights/01_Towards_Universality/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/15_Vedic_Insights/01_Towards_Universality/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is often maintained that progress is a Western notion. But the term ‘Western’ is as misleading as ‘Eastern’ or ‘Oriental’. I discovered this in California when I noted that Japan was not in the east but in the west. All such terms are subjective: they throw no light on the locality of the user and provide no information about the locality of the place to which they refer. Unlike ‘Western,’ &lt;em&gt;progress&lt;/em&gt; says something about what happens or does not happen in the world. The Vedas do not mention progress, but did not regard themselves as ‘eternal’ or ‘of non-human origin’ (&lt;em&gt;apauruṣeya&lt;/em&gt;), ideas that originated in the post-Vedic philosophy of the Mīmāṃsā. They depict their human composers, tell us stories about their eventful lives and describe developments that take place around them. It is I who is asking: did they make progress within that long Vedic period which lasted from ca. 1700 to 450 BCE?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 The Powers of Language</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/15_Vedic_Insights/02_The_Powers_of_Language/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/15_Vedic_Insights/02_The_Powers_of_Language/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We have seen that the greatest contributions of the Indian sciences were in the understanding of language. To grasp their origins, we have to go back further than the Prātiśākhyas, the Padapāṭha and the Sound Pattern of Language to the Rigveda where the earliest meaning of &lt;em&gt;bráhman&lt;/em&gt; was ‘sublime language’. It is connected with one god, Bṛhaspati, and two goddesses, Vāc and Sarasvatī, barely touched upon in my account so far. I have not neglected the sounds of language or linguistics, but never tried to derive a general conclusion from all that is said with respect to these topics in the Veda.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 The Limitations of Language</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/15_Vedic_Insights/03_The_Limitations_of_Language/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/15_Vedic_Insights/03_The_Limitations_of_Language/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We return from having sat, briefly, at the feet of three gurus: Bhartṛhari, Wilhelm von Humboldt and Roman Jakobson. The third expressed himself most clearly, but only Bhartṛhari seems to have had an understanding of what the present section is about. This is because he was inspired by the Rigveda. It was there that he found awareness of the limitations of language and of what language may &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; be able to express. It is a necessary component of the richness of language studies that I tried to call up from afar in previous sections.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Conclusions</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/15_Vedic_Insights/04_Conclusions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/15_Vedic_Insights/04_Conclusions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;anupāsitavṛddhānāṃvidyā nātiprasīdati&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘Science does not smile on those who neglect the ancients.’&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Bhartṛhari&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Vedic sciences and insights paved the way for the sciences of ritual and language. Both took account of the relevant facts and exhibited theoretical sophistication which included the uses of an artificial language. It is not easy to judge the merits of their insights. What we can say is that contemporary scientists working on language and the cognitive sciences have amassed vast amounts of information and reached deep insights of which their Vedic colleagues could have had no inkling. Did some of their insights go beyond present understandings? Can their ideas on &lt;em&gt;upāṃśu&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;aniruktagāna&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;tūṣṇīm&lt;/em&gt;, breathing, mantras and the rest be understood and explained by other types of modern scientists—physiologists, neurologists and others as yet unborn?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
