<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;23 THE ABODES OF THE DEAD on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/4_THE_SPIRITS_OF_THE_DEAD/23_THE_ABODES_OF_THE_DEAD/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;23 THE ABODES OF THE DEAD on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/4_THE_SPIRITS_OF_THE_DEAD/23_THE_ABODES_OF_THE_DEAD/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 The Nature of the Dead</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/4_THE_SPIRITS_OF_THE_DEAD/23_THE_ABODES_OF_THE_DEAD/1_The_Nature_of_the_Dead/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/4_THE_SPIRITS_OF_THE_DEAD/23_THE_ABODES_OF_THE_DEAD/1_The_Nature_of_the_Dead/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is not altogether easy to derive from the Rigveda a precise conception of the nature which was attributed to the spirits of the dead by the mind of the people or of the priest, and it is natural to assume that the ground for this difficulty is to be traced to the variation of both popular and ecclesiastical opinion. The modern view of the spirits and their abode is extremely varied and confused, and it would be ill-judged to assume that it was otherwise in the earlier Vedic religion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2 The Places of the Dead</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/4_THE_SPIRITS_OF_THE_DEAD/23_THE_ABODES_OF_THE_DEAD/2_The_Places_of_the_Dead/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/4_THE_SPIRITS_OF_THE_DEAD/23_THE_ABODES_OF_THE_DEAD/2_The_Places_of_the_Dead/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;5&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[Part IV&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The chief place of the dead in the conception of the Rigveda1 is unquestionably heaven: the soul leaves the body on death, and by the path of the Fathers it goes to the place where there is eternal light, endowed with lustre like that of the gods. It is said to go as by a car or by wings: more completely the Atharvaveda pictures the dead man as borne up by the Maruts, with gentle breezes fanning him, and cooled by showers until he recovers his complete body, and meets with the Fathers in the highest heaven, where with Yama they dwell. The heaven is called also the home, but the idea can hardly be pressed to the view that the going to heaven is a return home: it is rather that the man reaches in the highest heaven a new and abiding abode. The connexion of this journey of the souls with the actual burning of the body is always a vague one, but the reality of the connexion of soul and body is proved by the emphasis laid in the Brahmaṇas&amp;quot; on the necessity for the due collection of the bones of the dead, and the need of replacing them symbolically in cases where they may happen to be lost.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 The Transmutation of the Dead</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/4_THE_SPIRITS_OF_THE_DEAD/23_THE_ABODES_OF_THE_DEAD/3_The_Transmutation_of_the_Dead/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/4_THE_SPIRITS_OF_THE_DEAD/23_THE_ABODES_OF_THE_DEAD/3_The_Transmutation_of_the_Dead/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Rigveda and the Vedic literature of the period of the Samhitas and the Brāhmaṇas presents us with no clear proof of the belief in the transmigration of the dead: the scanty evidence which has been adduced to prove the contrary view will be discussed hereafter, but in this place it is important to note certain really popular beliefs of which there are traces in that literature and in that of the Sutras. The most important piece of evidence is late: it is recorded by Baudhayana that the birds at the offering to the dead should receive lumps of food, just like the Fathers, on the ground that in the form of birds the Fathers go about. It must, however, be admitted that this is not enough to prove a real popular belief. The idea of the incarnation of men as snakes is clearly to be accepted for the later period, but for the actual Vedic period it is not demonstrated, and it must in all likelihood be deemed to be an idea which entered the religion of the Veda with the advance of aboriginal influences. A more interesting case is recorded in the ritual for the final burial of the bones of the dead; if they cannot be found, then a garment is spread out, and, if a beast alights on it, it is treated as representing the bones of the dead. But this usage which is recorded for us at a late period cannot be pressed very far. To this scanty evidence may be added such support as can be obtained from such stories as that of a mother, who, dying in the absence of her son, lies in wait for him in the shape of a newly created jackal to warn him of danger. The proof does not come to much, and none of it is of early date. Of the soul becoming a plant or passing into a plant we have no early evidence save such as may be derived from the solitary address to the dead man in the Rigveda &amp;amp; which tells him to go to the plants with his members, and the isolated statement that the Fathers lie about the roots of the plants.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
