<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;09 Brāhmaṇas Andāraṇyakas on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/09_brAhmaNas_andAraNyakas/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;09 Brāhmaṇas Andāraṇyakas on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/09_brAhmaNas_andAraNyakas/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Villages, Forests and the Ecology</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/09_brAhmaNas_andAraNyakas/01_Villages_Forests_and_the_Ecology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/09_brAhmaNas_andAraNyakas/01_Villages_Forests_and_the_Ecology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In Chapter 1 I have referred to a hypothetical period of 9,000 years during which the indigenous lineages of the subcontinent of South Asia remained widespread in both tribal and caste populations. Whether it was actually 9,000 years or more or less is irrelevant from our Vedic point of view. Other facts are more significant in our present context: Chapter 3 showed that caste was assigned to the Vedas by a post-Vedic and caste-obsessed society. Sedentary villages, on the other hand, pre-dated the Vedas. One such village with a history of some 5,000 years is well-known: the Neolithic village of Mehrgarh (Frontispiece, near 8).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Brāhmaṇas and Āraṇyakas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/09_brAhmaNas_andAraNyakas/02_brAhmaNas_and_AraNyakas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/09_brAhmaNas_andAraNyakas/02_brAhmaNas_and_AraNyakas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We have seen that the term &lt;em&gt;Brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; is used in several senses. The meaning with which we are concerned in this chapter is one of them: a Vedic composition in prose. In the Yajurveda, that composition is mainly concerned with interpretations of mantras in ritual terms. In the Rig-, Sāma- and Atharva-Vedas, a Brāhmaṇa is more like a separate unit—what we have in mind when we think of a ‘book’. But all these compositions continue to be oral and orally transmitted, sometimes with the old accents. To be a composer one now had to be not only a ritual expert, preferably a priest, but also a scholar, familiar with the tradition. No wonder that such people were called &lt;em&gt;Brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt;. They were no longer sages, they were specialists who composed Brāhmaṇas or pieces thereof, and liked to be the advisers of rulers or chieftains. In all these capacities, being specialists did not prevent them from holding forth about anything that took their fancy. Like authors of successful books, they could count on an audience. They are in many respects like &lt;em&gt;authors&lt;/em&gt;, only they did not write; but they expressed their opinions forcefully, putting themselves in their compositions, and they became &lt;em&gt;authorities&lt;/em&gt;. That is what brahmins, as I may now call them, always remained, in India as elsewhere where we find them during the post-Vedic periods. Khmer, Javanese, Balinese, Thai and other brahmans remained ritual experts and advisors to rulers or chieftains.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Locating Obscurities, Esotericism and Irrationalities</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/09_brAhmaNas_andAraNyakas/03_Locating_Obscurities_Esotericism_and_Irrational/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/09_brAhmaNas_andAraNyakas/03_Locating_Obscurities_Esotericism_and_Irrational/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Parokṣakāmā hi devā&lt;/em&gt;ḥ: ‘The gods love what is out of sight!’&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I don’t know what the gods love, but we have to widen our perspective if we wish to understand, not only who were the brāhmaṇa authors of these early prose compositions of the Veda and to what kind of society they belonged, but what was in their minds insofar as it is distinct from what is in our own. Some people say: we cannot know, and stop there. I say: we must explore the unknown. This implies that we must begin to tolerate uncertainty. We want to find out what our Brāhmaṇa composers know but we are also aware that they do not know what we know. One thing we find is that they had different ideas about &lt;em&gt;conveying&lt;/em&gt; knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
