<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;21 THE DOMESTIC RITUAL on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/21_THE_DOMESTIC_RITUAL/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;21 THE DOMESTIC RITUAL on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/21_THE_DOMESTIC_RITUAL/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 The General Character of the Domestic Sacrifices</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/21_THE_DOMESTIC_RITUAL/1_The_General_Character_of_the_Domestic_Sacrifices/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/21_THE_DOMESTIC_RITUAL/1_The_General_Character_of_the_Domestic_Sacrifices/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THE householder of the Vedic period was expected to maintain a fire normally in his dwelling, sometimes, however, in a special place outside the actual house. The establishment of such a fire was normal on marriage, on the division of the property of a family, the return of a student from his studentship, or the death of the head of the family, when his eldest son was expected to kindle a new fire. The fire might be produced by friction, but normally it was obtained from the house of a wealthy man, or from one who made many sacrifices. It was the duty of the householder, his son, wife, daughter, or pupil to keep it alive: if it was allowed to go out, it had to be rekindled by friction or reborrowed. If its existence had been interrupted for twelve days, a completely new establishment was prescribed. From it on going a journey the householder took leave and greeted it on his return, kissing his eldest son thereafter to the accompaniment of formulae, while daughters were kissed on the head, not the lips, in silence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2 The Various Offerings</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/21_THE_DOMESTIC_RITUAL/2_The_Various_Offerings/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/21_THE_DOMESTIC_RITUAL/2_The_Various_Offerings/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;7&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The daily offerings of the householder include offerings at night and morning to Agni and Prajapati, and Surya and Prajapati respectively there is, however, great divergence as to the nature of the offerings, usually rice or barley, and the exact deities and times of offering. Further, there are five great offerings to be performed; the first is the Devayajña, that for the gods made in the fire morning and evening, when the meal is ready. The second, that called Bhutayajña or Bali,&amp;rsquo; is offered on the ground for all manner of beings; in the version of Gobhila, the first is for earth, the second for Vayu, the third for the All-gods, the fourth for Prajapati, then the fifth is offered in the waterholder for the god of the waters, the sixth at the middle posts for plants and&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 Birth Ceremonies and others</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/21_THE_DOMESTIC_RITUAL/3_Birth_Ceremonies_and_others/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/21_THE_DOMESTIC_RITUAL/3_Birth_Ceremonies_and_others/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As is natural the domestic ritual devotes much space to the minute description of large number of rites, mainly magical in essence, which accompany the child from even before birth to its death. In the third or fourth month or even later after pregnancy takes place the rite for quickening a male child, Pumsavana, the essence of which consists in the placing in the nostril of the wife by her husband of a Nyagrodha shoot, which he purchases in due form and which is pounded, either by a young girl, or a student or a wife who is keeping a vow, or a Brahmabandhu, a term which is perhaps best taken as a Brahman&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4 Studentship</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/21_THE_DOMESTIC_RITUAL/4_Studentship/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/21_THE_DOMESTIC_RITUAL/4_Studentship/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A Brahman child in the eighth year from conception or birth, a Kṣatriya in the eleventh, a VaiŚya in the twelfth, should be received as a student by a teacher: the period can be increased to 16, 22, and 24 years respectively, but after that a youth has lost the right to say the Savitri verse, and should not be associated with, taken as a pupil, permitted to sacrifice, or accepted as a sonin-law if the Savitri is lost for three generations, the right of the sacraments is lost, and can only be regained by the performance of the Śrauta rite called the Vratya Stomas. The ceremony of the reception is performed with much form before a fire newly lighted by friction or taken from the household fire: north of it are laid the necessary utensils, a stone, a fresh garment, a skin,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 Marriage</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/21_THE_DOMESTIC_RITUAL/5_Marriage/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/21_THE_DOMESTIC_RITUAL/5_Marriage/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The duty of the Vedic Indian to marry is assumed by all the texts, and the domestic ritual gives precise rules for the performance of the legitimate and honourable form of marriage,&amp;quot; ignoring as a rule the irregular forms based upon capture, violence, or mere mutual love without parental approval, which are recognized by the law books in various forms, Gandharva, Asura, PaiŚāca, and Rākṣasa, as well as the romantic form of nominal self-choice by the bride of a suitor, the Svayamvara which bears traces of a test of skill of suitors by the king or other parent of high rank similar to that of Kleisthenes. The youth should obtain permission from his parents or his teacher to marry: only one Sūtra prescribes the numbers of brides, three for the Brahman, two for the Ksatriya, and one for the VaiŚya, and in one view a Śūdra for each: this refers clearly to a rule by which each caste could have a wife of its own and one of each inferior caste. The later texts prescribe that the maiden must be of the same caste and land, but not of the same Gotra as the father or a sapindā on the mother&amp;rsquo;s side, rules which are difficult to define with precision.&amp;quot; Maidens with names of stars, rivers, or trees are to be avoided, as are those with names with r or l as the penultimate consonant. The physical marks are most important, but, as it is difficult to be sure of them, the maiden may be given eight or nine lumps of earth chosen from different places, and, as she choses, her disposition can be gauged. The bridegroom should be of good family and character, have good bodily signs, be healthy and learned. As considerations in marriage family ranks above intelligence, beauty, and wealth.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
