<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;5 From Kakinada to Vijayawada and Beyond on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/3_Selection_of_characters/5_From_Kakinada_to_Vijayawada_and_Beyond/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;5 From Kakinada to Vijayawada and Beyond on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/3_Selection_of_characters/5_From_Kakinada_to_Vijayawada_and_Beyond/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 The Kapilavayi Family</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/3_Selection_of_characters/5_From_Kakinada_to_Vijayawada_and_Beyond/1_The_Kapilavayi_Family/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/3_Selection_of_characters/5_From_Kakinada_to_Vijayawada_and_Beyond/1_The_Kapilavayi_Family/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The white Andhra University van was surrounded by excited towns folk pressing close to peer through its windows. Something nefarious must be under way, particularly since a Foreign woman was inside with  three men. The sound of chanting was unsettling. After the recording  session was completed, the crowd was told that the dora from America,  his wife, and a professor from Andhra University were scholars seeking  to learn about the Vedas from the young pandit assigned to parayana in  the nearby temple here in Simhacalam, and that the van afforded the  only quiet place for recording. The recitant so generous with his time and  expertise on that December evening in 1980 was Kapilavayi (Kapilavai)  Venkatesvara Sastri.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2 Yajnesvara Agnihotra Sastri (1909–1983)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/3_Selection_of_characters/5_From_Kakinada_to_Vijayawada_and_Beyond/2_Yajnesvara_Agnihotra_Sastri_19091983/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/3_Selection_of_characters/5_From_Kakinada_to_Vijayawada_and_Beyond/2_Yajnesvara_Agnihotra_Sastri_19091983/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The brothers’ narrative begins with an astonishing family history that reads  like the plot of a Salman Rushdie novel. A nineteenth-century ahitagni named  Kapilavayi Venkata Somayajulu and his wife Subbalaksmi Somidevamma  raised five sons and three daughters in Kakinada, the town where Mitranarayana  is now the sole remaining ahitagni.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Their first son, Pedda Rama Sastri (1889–1987) lived for ninety-eight years. He was an extraordinarily dynamic Veda pandit but remained a lifelong bachelor and was therefore ineligible for a single  consecrated fire let alone aspirations to tretagni.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A second son born to Venkata  and Subbalaksmi was also a renowned Veda pandit, did marry and maintain  the grhya (smarta agni), but never set three fires as his father had done. He was  Chinna Rama Sastri (1904–85), a contemporary of Baballa. Chinna (Little or  Younger) Rama followed Pedda (Big or Elder) Rama in birth order.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A third son was born and then twenty-one years after Pedda a fourth son arrived. Named Yajnesvara, this youngest was taught Veda by his oldest brother  Pedda, whose age made him equivalent to biological as well as spiritual  father. He too excelled and went on to become Yajnesvara Agnihotra Sastri  (1910–83), Kasyapa gotra, famous throughout South India for his sponsor ship of Veda and srauta.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sponsorship, supervision, promotion, boosterism  are all the right words. Although fully qualified through precocious acquisition of Veda in the best of places in India he, like his older brother Chinna  Rama Sastri, he did not accomplish adhana and therefore not agni-stoma, not  from lack of desire but rather from sibling blockade. He could not set fires  because his two older brothers had not done so. As compensation he became  an expert srotriya and the most impressive promoter of srauta in the modern  history of India.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 Venkatesvara Sastri and Family</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/3_Selection_of_characters/5_From_Kakinada_to_Vijayawada_and_Beyond/3_Venkatesvara_Sastri_and_Family/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/3_Selection_of_characters/5_From_Kakinada_to_Vijayawada_and_Beyond/3_Venkatesvara_Sastri_and_Family/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Both contemporary Kapilavayi brothers inherited their father’s passion for the  life of srauta and benefited from a childhood spent not only learning Vedas but  being on the move with their father, uncles, and others, observing sacrifices  ordinary and extraordinary. From seven to twelve years of age Venkatesvara,  born in 1953, learned the Taittiriya Samhita with Apastamba and from thirteen to fifteen he undertook the three khandas—adhvaryava, hotriya, and audgatriya—with the aid of a well-worn palm-leaf bundle about twenty inches thick,  “the Srautam” in Sanskrit Telugu script of his grandfather. His next task was  the Rg Veda, Sakala sakha, with Asvalayana. After that came the Atharva Veda,  Saunaka sakha, which he completed in 1979 at age twenty-seven with much inspiration from Lanka. The Sama Veda was not omitted and he learned portions of what he claims, in accord with his father, to be three different sakha or variants thereof. It was these that he recited in the van in 1980 recounted at  the beginning of this segment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4 Rama Sastri and Family</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/3_Selection_of_characters/5_From_Kakinada_to_Vijayawada_and_Beyond/4_Rama_Sastri_and_Family/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/3_Selection_of_characters/5_From_Kakinada_to_Vijayawada_and_Beyond/4_Rama_Sastri_and_Family/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The second son of Yajnesvara Agnihotra grew up with the free-spirited  demeanor of a self-confident younger brother. He is a completely open and  guileless man. Although he frequently participates in rituals with his brother,  four years older, the distance between Annavaram and Simhacalam assures  him freedom to live his own quite similar life in another popular pilgrimage  town, serving parayana as an Athar Veda pandit in the temple of Satyanarayana.  Perhaps in a form of obeisance to Venkatesvara, whose business cards read  “Catur-vedin,” Rama Sastri, with virtually identical training, although weighted  somewhat more in the direction of the Atharva Veda, including its Brahmana,  claims only “Tri-vedin,” master of three and not all four Vedas.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 Srauta-kaksa, Ritual Rivalry</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/3_Selection_of_characters/5_From_Kakinada_to_Vijayawada_and_Beyond/5_Srauta-kaksa_Ritual_Rivalry/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/3_Selection_of_characters/5_From_Kakinada_to_Vijayawada_and_Beyond/5_Srauta-kaksa_Ritual_Rivalry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over several decades both contemporary Kapilavayi brothers have narrated with out hesitation the ritual rivalry in which their father was engaged. What is termed  srauta-kaksa, rivalry in both performance and knowledge of srauta, is as old as  the rituals.[^11]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The expectation of a great many texts, the new or full-moon sacrifice  every fortnight, for example, is that the sacrificer has enemies, one adversary in particular who is to be brought to mind. For the Kapilavayi family it is the  Dendukuris of Vijayawada, Krishna District, who serve this age-old function, particularly after Yajnesvara built his house there in 1975. Evidence of this divisive  relationship comes mainly from debates in assemblies that occurred long ago.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
