<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;4 Becoming a Veda on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/4_Becoming_a_Veda/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;4 Becoming a Veda on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/4_Becoming_a_Veda/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 A Tumult of Veda and the Brahmacarin</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/4_Becoming_a_Veda/1_A_Tumult_of_Veda_and_the_Brahmacarin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/4_Becoming_a_Veda/1_A_Tumult_of_Veda_and_the_Brahmacarin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Senior Konasima Veda pandits and others who were youngsters in the 1960s  recall the days when there was “a tumult of Veda” heard before dawn as freshly  bathed gurus and brahmacarin faced one another to immerse minds and voices  in ever-continuing lessons. Chapter 2 provided a brief overview of the trans&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;mission of Veda from an older to a younger generation and the progression of  the student from his initial portion of the Taittiriya Samhita to his examination  and certification as a Veda pandit. Chapter 3 gave numerous examples of indi vidual development. There is more to be said of this evolution and the larger&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2 The Work of the Text</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/4_Becoming_a_Veda/2_The_Work_of_the_Text/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/4_Becoming_a_Veda/2_The_Work_of_the_Text/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The process of retaining successive phrases of text, however, is familiar to out siders only in part. The small boy with impressionable brain cells has a calling  and faces a syllabus unbelievably daunting in its totality. True, he is adding  but one line at a time. Nevertheless, pressure from the cumulative weight of  successive days is enormous, the task being so formidable that the dropout  rate is high. The survivor of early learning is enrolled in something close to a  degree program broken into eighty-two “questions,” the classical Telugu panna,  from Sanskrit prasna. This might be compared with a sequence of eighty-two  “courses,” all of them charged to memory. As noted in Chapter 2 the Konasima  syllabus for the Vedic student, anticipating the examination system, begins  with the third or fourth kanda of the Taittiriya Samhita, those two sections  considered to be softest for starters. The seven kanda are memorized in five  portions, making up forty-four panna, or slightly more than half of the syl&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 The Sama-vartana: Graduation Day</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/4_Becoming_a_Veda/3_The_Sama-vartana_Graduation_Day/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/4_Becoming_a_Veda/3_The_Sama-vartana_Graduation_Day/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When Lanka was judged by his guru, Baballa’s father, to have completed the  Taittiriya curriculum he could then go home, put behind him those long  daily walks in darkness between Mukkamala and Nedunuru, eat his own  mother&amp;rsquo;s evening meals, and await his examination by a Veda pandit review&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[[148]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;board.But first there was a marker for this momentous occasion, sama-vartana,  the “return” from the guru’s house. The focus was a ritual bath, snana, when  he received the title snataka, one who has undergone the well-earned bath. It  was a graduation ceremony with a tonsure, shaving of head and facial hair by  the barber, bathing, applying sandal paste and perfumes to his body and kol to  his eyes, putting on two new garments and earrings, first the right, then the  left, new chappals for his feet, and a garland that he placed on his own neck. At  hand were an umbrella and his staff. Finally, he took a mirror and checked out  his appearance, makeup and all. The brahmacarin vow of celibacy was over and  he was now free to marry. The entire day was spent indoors behind the pen for  the agni-hotra cow, shielded from the sun, and he could move about only after  sundown and sandhya-vandana.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4 Advanced Degrees</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/4_Becoming_a_Veda/4_Advanced_Degrees/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/4_Becoming_a_Veda/4_Advanced_Degrees/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The career of the long-married Veda pandit, soon to be united with his wife,  now follows a trajectory with multiple options. The Taittiriya Samhita is trans mitted in several forms, vikrti, “modifications” of the “original” or model text.  The student began with the continuous (samhita) recitation (patha). After  completing samhita-patha he then proceeded to pada-patha, the same text over  again broken down to separate words, pada, without regard to grammatical  rules that alter certain initial and final letters when they are adjoining. Then  he could continue for a third time with the same text in krama-patha, a step-by step recitation. The first and second recitation patterns are normative; most  teenage students opt for a krama-patha examination and certification.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 The Sabha: Debating in an Assembly of Veda Pandits</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/4_Becoming_a_Veda/5_The_Sabha_Debating_in_an_Assembly_of_Veda_Pandits/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/4_Becoming_a_Veda/5_The_Sabha_Debating_in_an_Assembly_of_Veda_Pandits/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A sabha is an assembly of Veda pandits that meets in a particular venue on  scheduled occasions, often annually. At the turn of the millennium it seemed  that all the Vedic communities were either instituting a new sabha or reviving  a moribund one. The word, in use since the Rg Veda with the general meaning of assembly or congregation, is in common parlance, as in the two houses  of parliament of modern India, the upper or Rajya Sabha and lower or Lok  Sabha, respectively, the assemblies of the states and the people. A new Vedic  sabha was founded in the name of Duvvuri Yajulu March 28, 2005, when  some seventy Veda pandits gathered in the Sriramapuram agrahara to observe  his ninetieth birthday. Already ninety-four on the Telugu calendar, the blind  and memory-less Yajulu was enduring the final days before his death a few  months later. His family and colleagues wished to found this new sabha in his  name to honor him while he still could participate, even without his faculties.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
