<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;03 Civilization and Society on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/03_Civilization_and_Society/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;03 Civilization and Society on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/03_Civilization_and_Society/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Absence of Caste in the Vedas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/03_Civilization_and_Society/01_Absence_of_Caste_in_the_Vedas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/03_Civilization_and_Society/01_Absence_of_Caste_in_the_Vedas/</guid>
      <description>The Vedas depict a small civilization, beginning to settle on Indic soil. The small groups of which it consisted kept their Indo-European language, together with its poetic techniques, mythologies, the cults of fire and Soma and the knowledge of horses and chariots. That latter knowledge had been carried along with language across the mountain barriers that separate Central Asia from the Indic subcontinent. It was carried not by hordes of invaders, but in the minds of small groups of men who established alliances with local women.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 Vedic Evidence and Scholarly Discussions</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/03_Civilization_and_Society/02_Vedic_Evidence_and_Scholarly_Discussions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/03_Civilization_and_Society/02_Vedic_Evidence_and_Scholarly_Discussions/</guid>
      <description>Three lines of an early Rigvedic invocation of the Aśvins, divine twins who travel through space in their horse-drawn chariot, provide a picture of early Vedic civilization in a nutshell. In so doing, they make use of three of the four terms that underlie the later social system:
‘Promote the bráhman and promote poetic inspirations. Slay the demons, drive away pain and illness. Drink the pressed Soma in harmony with Sun and Dawn, o Aśvins!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 Varying Terminologies and the first ‘Vedic Villages’</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/03_Civilization_and_Society/03_Varying_Terminologies_and_the_first_Vedic_Villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/03_Civilization_and_Society/03_Varying_Terminologies_and_the_first_Vedic_Villa/</guid>
      <description>The mere occurrence of terms such as brāhmaṇas or ‘brahmans’ proves nothing about caste or caste distinctions. The Rigveda speaks of them often, but the term refers to various kinds of learned people, including ‘sages’, ‘poets’ and ‘priests’. The term kṣatriya has no settled meaning either, neither in the Rigveda, nor in later Vedic compositions. The Taittirīya Saṃhitā of the Black Yajurveda mentions kṣatṛ which is a chamberlain or doorkeeper. The Tāṇḍya Brāhmaṇa of the Sāmaveda refers to ‘eight brave persons that hold up the kingdom’.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 Rathakāra and a Note on Women</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/03_Civilization_and_Society/04_rathakAra_and_a_Note_on_Women/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/03_Civilization_and_Society/04_rathakAra_and_a_Note_on_Women/</guid>
      <description>From what we have mentioned in Part I about the great prestige of experts who knew how to train horses or construct chariots with wheels with spokes—both specialized tasks that reflect a high level of technology—we would expect them to occupy an important, or at least a special place in early Vedic society. They might be assigned to a high caste had the notion of caste then existed. Would the chariot-maker give us an idea of Vedic society before the caste system?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
