<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;03 Civilization and Society on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/03_Civilization_and_Society/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;03 Civilization and Society on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/03_Civilization_and_Society/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Absence of Caste in the Vedas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/03_Civilization_and_Society/01_Absence_of_Caste_in_the_Vedas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/03_Civilization_and_Society/01_Absence_of_Caste_in_the_Vedas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Vedas depict a small civilization, beginning to settle on Indic soil. The small groups of which it consisted kept their Indo-European language, together with its poetic techniques, mythologies, the cults of fire and Soma and the knowledge of horses and chariots. That latter knowledge had been carried along with language across the mountain barriers that separate Central Asia from the Indic subcontinent. It was carried not by hordes of invaders, but in the minds of small groups of men who established alliances with local women. Language and ritual were transmitted from father to son. Fathers insisted that sons learned Vedic until transmission became ritualized (as illustrated by the Gāyatrī mantra at the end of Chapter 11). We hear little about the mother or the institution of marriage until the end of the Rigveda. Women came from many sections of the indigenous population and spoke various languages. They may have been ‘widely extending’ nymphs like Urvaśī, but at first they did not know Vedic and rarely, or ever, composed Vedas. Though matriarchal and matrilineal clans and tribes must have existed, it is not obvious that the general Indic pattern of dependence of women on men was in existence also. That pattern was formulated explicitly in post-Vedic times by the code of Manu or &lt;em&gt;Manu Sm&lt;/em&gt;ṛ&lt;em&gt;ti&lt;/em&gt; of the second century CE: as a child, a girl must remain under her father’s control, as a woman, under her husband, and when her husband is dead, under the sons. None of these restrictions may have existed or imply that a caste system existed in the Vedas.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Vedic Evidence and Scholarly Discussions</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/03_Civilization_and_Society/02_Vedic_Evidence_and_Scholarly_Discussions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/03_Civilization_and_Society/02_Vedic_Evidence_and_Scholarly_Discussions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Three lines of an early Rigvedic invocation of the Aśvins, divine twins who travel through space in their horse-drawn chariot, provide a picture of early Vedic civilization in a nutshell. In so doing, they make use of three of the four terms that underlie the later social system:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘Promote the &lt;em&gt;bráhman&lt;/em&gt; and promote poetic inspirations. Slay the demons, drive away pain and illness. Drink the pressed Soma in harmony with Sun and Dawn, o Aśvins!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Varying Terminologies and the first ‘Vedic Villages’</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/03_Civilization_and_Society/03_Varying_Terminologies_and_the_first_Vedic_Villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/03_Civilization_and_Society/03_Varying_Terminologies_and_the_first_Vedic_Villa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The mere occurrence of terms such as &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt;s or ‘brahmans’ proves nothing about caste or caste distinctions. The Rigveda speaks of them often, but the term refers to various kinds of learned people, including ‘sages’, ‘poets’ and ‘priests’. The term &lt;em&gt;kṣatriya&lt;/em&gt; has no settled meaning either, neither in the Rigveda, nor in later Vedic compositions. The Taittirīya Saṃhitā of the Black Yajurveda mentions &lt;em&gt;kṣat&lt;/em&gt;ṛ which is a chamberlain or doorkeeper. The Tāṇḍya Brāhmaṇa of the Sāmaveda refers to ‘eight brave persons that hold up the kingdom’. The list ends with &lt;em&gt;kṣat&lt;/em&gt;ṛ and &lt;em&gt;saṃgrahīt&lt;/em&gt;ṛ. According to P.V. Kane, they are the names of high officers of some sort. Similar observations could be made with regard to other names that became caste names in the later hierarchy. But the chief difficulty is not that we would get entangled in a fruitless and abstract discussion of social systems. What we have to know first is who were the speakers of Vedic and the composers of the Vedas. We know that composing Vedas took place almost entirely within the continent, and that the Vedic language was a branch of Indo-Iranian that had come into existence a little earlier and further to the north. Those earlier peoples may have composed ‘Vedas’, but they are at best the precursors of the Vedas as we know them. The latter were composed by descendants of those precursors, as well as others and a variety of intermediaries as we have seen.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Rathakāra and a Note on Women</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/03_Civilization_and_Society/04_rathakAra_and_a_Note_on_Women/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/03_Civilization_and_Society/04_rathakAra_and_a_Note_on_Women/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From what we have mentioned in Part I about the great prestige of experts who knew how to train horses or construct chariots with wheels with spokes—both specialized tasks that reflect a high level of technology—we would expect them to occupy an important, or at least a special place in early Vedic society. They might be assigned to a high caste had the notion of caste then existed. Would the chariot-maker give us an idea of Vedic society &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; the caste system? It should not be difficult to find information about this since there is a common term that refers to that chariot-maker: &lt;em&gt;rathakāra.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
