<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;19 RITES ANCILLARY TO THE SACRIFICE on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/19_RITES_ANCILLARY_TO_THE_SACRIFICE/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;19 RITES ANCILLARY TO THE SACRIFICE on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/19_RITES_ANCILLARY_TO_THE_SACRIFICE/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 The Consecration</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/19_RITES_ANCILLARY_TO_THE_SACRIFICE/1_The_Consecration/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/19_RITES_ANCILLARY_TO_THE_SACRIFICE/1_The_Consecration/</guid>
      <description>THE Dikṣā is a rite which has to be performed by the sacrificer and his wife before the Soma sacrifice. It is carried out in a hut near the fire: the sacrificer bathes, has his hair cut, is anointed, puts on a fresh garment, is girded with the sacred cord, and sits down on a black antelope hide, in which there resides, in the view of the tradition, holy power. His head is covered, an antelope horn is tied to his garment, and it is prescribed that, when he suffers from itch, he is to use that only with which to scratch himself.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2 The Avabhṛtha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/19_RITES_ANCILLARY_TO_THE_SACRIFICE/2_The_avabhRtha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/19_RITES_ANCILLARY_TO_THE_SACRIFICE/2_The_avabhRtha/</guid>
      <description>6
As the Dikṣā is the beginning of the Soma sacrifice, so the end of it and also of many other offerings is the Avabhṛtha, or concluding bath&amp;rsquo;. The word is found already in the Rigveda,3 and undoubtedly in the original sense, and the practice must therefore be assumed to have existed from the earliest period of the Vedic religion. The meaning of it is clear: it is the carrying down to the waters of the various things which are to be disposed of after the offering is over.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 Taboos</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/19_RITES_ANCILLARY_TO_THE_SACRIFICE/3_Taboos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/19_RITES_ANCILLARY_TO_THE_SACRIFICE/3_Taboos/</guid>
      <description>6
4
While the bath has the power of removing what is attached to a man&amp;rsquo;s person, and thus is often used before undertaking a rite, as before the Dikṣā itself by the sacrificer, by bridegroom and bride before marriage, and by a woman after the spell to produce offspring has been performed for her, it is also necessary to avoid its use to prevent the removal of the holy power, which has been attained by some means or other.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4 The Forms of Prayer</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/19_RITES_ANCILLARY_TO_THE_SACRIFICE/4_The_Forms_of_Prayer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/19_RITES_ANCILLARY_TO_THE_SACRIFICE/4_The_Forms_of_Prayer/</guid>
      <description>The Rigveda shows quite clearly that the conception of prayer for aid to a god without the performance of any sacrifice was quite natural and intelligible. The heroes of its narratives of the deeds of the Aśvins in special seem to have been specially eager in their prayers for the aid they desired. But the priests were, from the earliest period of the later Samhitas and probably earlier, ready to find the exact formulae with which the deity should be addressed in every stage of trouble, and, what was still more important, to lay down the nature of the necessary offering.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
