<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;शाखाः on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/shAkhA/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;शाखाः on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/shAkhA/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>अनुषक्त-मन्त्र-पाठः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/shAkhA/anuShakta-mantra-pAThaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/shAkhA/anuShakta-mantra-pAThaH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ऋगवद-समवद-च&#34;&gt;ऋग्वेदे सामवेदे च&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Other than these mantra-pāṭha-s of the KYV, we also have comparable supplementary mantra-collections among the Sāmavedin-s in their Mantrabrāhmaṇa and the famous khila of the RV.&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2019/02/10/notes-on-the-bhadra-sukta-a-hymn-for-felicity-to-the-vedic-pantheon/&#34;&gt;MT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;यजरवद&#34;&gt;यजुर्वेदे&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Several sub-schools of the Taittirīya school of the Kṛṣṇayajurveda possess their own collections of mantra-s distinct from their saṃhitā-s known as the mantra-pāṭha-s. These include mantra-s that are often found in other traditions but not in their own saṃhitā or brāhmaṇa. Additionally, they also include some mantra-s which are unique to these mantra-pāṭha-s. For example the famous Yajurvedic version of the Śrīsūkta is found in the mantra-pāṭha of Bodhāyana. However, most practitioners in South India do not correctly use the accents of this sūkta and seem to be unaware that the KYV version of this sūkta occurs in this text. The mantra-paṭha-s of the &lt;strong&gt;Āpastamba, Bodhāyana, Vaikhānasa and Hiraṇyakeśin&lt;/strong&gt; sub-schools have come down to us. The mantra-s in them are typically deployed in gṛhya rituals directed by instructions from their gṛhyasūtra-s. However, the Vaikhānasa-mantra-pāṭha is distinctive in having a late terminal part that is used in the iconic worship of Viṣṇu by the Vaikhānasa-s. The Hiraṇyakeśī-mantra-pāṭha has a ṛk-saṃhitā as part of it and is used by the Hiraṇyakeśīn-s of Maharashtra and Tamil Nadu in their rituals to this date. In someways this is reminiscent of the &lt;strong&gt;hautra-pariśiṣṭha&lt;/strong&gt; of the Āpastamba-s that is used by Yajurvedin-s to supplement the role normally performed by the Ṛgvedin hotṛ.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>वेदशाखा-स्पर्धा</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/shAkhA/shAkhA-spardhA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/shAkhA/shAkhA-spardhA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Particularly, brAhmaNa-s (procedural texts) contradict and even deride each other. Examples:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;yAjNAvalkya in shatapatha-brAhmaNa, referring to other shAkhAs&amp;rsquo; practices, says: &amp;ldquo;तदु तथा न कुर्य्यात्&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;yAjJNavalkya derides charaka-s in many places. Eg: &amp;ldquo;अथ पृषदाज्यं। तदु ह चरकाध्वर्यवः पृषदाज्यमेवाग्रेऽभिघारयन्ति। &amp;ldquo;प्राणः पृषदाज्यमि&amp;quot;ति वदन्तस्, तदु ह याज्ञवल्क्यं चरकाध्वर्युरनुव्याजहा&amp;quot;रैवं कुर्वन्तं प्राणं वा अयमन्तरगाद&amp;quot;ध्वर्युः &amp;ldquo;प्राण एनं हास्यती&amp;quot;ति - ३.८.२.[२४] स ह स्म बाहू अन्ववेक्ष्याह । &amp;ldquo;इमौ पलितौ बाहू, क्व स्विद्ब्राह्मणस्य वचो बभूवे&amp;quot;ति। न तदाद्रियेत। उत्तमो वा एष प्रयाजो भवति। इदं वै हविर्यज्ञ उत्तमे प्रयाजे ध्रुवामेवाग्रेऽभिघारयति।&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;Also, in puruSamedha where different persons are symbolically dedicated y to different devatas, while a brAhmaNa is dedicated to brAhma, shUdra to tapas, etc; a caraka is dedicated to duSkRta!!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;some AV shAkhAs are quite antagonistic to other AV shAkhAs - jajala and other shAkhAs criticized by shaunaka/ paippAlada&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;The AV practitioners are associated with the role of the Brahman but in reality have their own parallel śrauta tradition.&amp;rdquo; - (&lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2020/01/02/the-roots-of-vai%E1%B9%A3%E1%B9%87avam-a-view-from-the-numerology-of-vedic-texts/&#34;&gt;MT&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;pa~ncaviMsha brAhmaNa cursing kaushitakas to go into oblivion&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;harmonization&#34;&gt;Harmonization&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;By the sUtra perdiod, these rivalries were harmonized by mechanisms such as &amp;ldquo;नहि निन्दा न्यायः&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
