<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;27 THE THEOSOPHY OF THE BRAHMANAS on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/27_THE_THEOSOPHY_OF_THE_BRAHMANAS/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;27 THE THEOSOPHY OF THE BRAHMANAS on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/27_THE_THEOSOPHY_OF_THE_BRAHMANAS/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 The General Character of the Brahmana Philosophy </title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/27_THE_THEOSOPHY_OF_THE_BRAHMANAS/1_The_General_Character_of_the_Brahmana_Philosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/27_THE_THEOSOPHY_OF_THE_BRAHMANAS/1_The_General_Character_of_the_Brahmana_Philosophy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THE value of the Brāhmaṇas as sources of philosophy is difficult to determine with any accuracy They are works in which the imagination of successive generations of priests has been allowed to run riot: there is no moderation in their conception, and no great Brahmana is, as far as can be judged, the production of a single mind 1 The one great merit of Greek philosophy, the appearance of clear-cut ideas expressed in works of individual authorship, is wholly wanting for us in the Brahmaṇas, and the question constantly obtrudes itself to what extent we can believe that the priests by whom these texts were composed and handed down held the views which they wrote down In many cases it may be taken that they did not; the works abound in their explanations of rites with all sorts of absurdities, which we need not accuse the priests of being so foolish as not to recognize as absurdities; but the question of the dividing line between profoundity and absurdity presents itself with the greatest frequency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2 The Highest Principle of the Universe</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/27_THE_THEOSOPHY_OF_THE_BRAHMANAS/2_The_Highest_Principle_of_the_Universe/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/27_THE_THEOSOPHY_OF_THE_BRAHMANAS/2_The_Highest_Principle_of_the_Universe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the period of the Brāhmaṇas the god Prajapati occupies without doubt or question the position of the creator god, the supreme god of the world. The commencement of legend after legend proclaims his creative activity, often figured under the form of the practising of fervour, a reminder of the cosmic heat, whence came forth the power enclosed in the shell according to the view of the hymn of creation. The world egg appears as producing the heaven and the earth from its two parts, and, as Hiranyagarbha, it is the form of Prajapati, in which he proceeds to immediate creation of living beings of all kinds, and the ordering of the universe. These tales, of which there is no end, often tell us that Prajapati felt at the end of his efforts that he was empty, and had to be filled up again, always by some ritual process. The details of these stupid myths are wholly unimportant: it is enough to note that he is constantly the creator, the ruler, and the preserver of the world and is accepted by every Brahmana of the period as being the lord of the world: he is, it may be added, without any ethical importance: the conception of him is purely intellectual, that of the unity of the universe, and the choosing&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 The Theory of the Sacrifice</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/27_THE_THEOSOPHY_OF_THE_BRAHMANAS/3_The_Theory_of_the_Sacrifice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/27_THE_THEOSOPHY_OF_THE_BRAHMANAS/3_The_Theory_of_the_Sacrifice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Amid an infinity of varied details the Brāhmaṇas present a perfectly definite body of opinion as to the fundamental nature of the sacrifice, and in connexion with the sacrifice of the gods, the Asuras, the seers, and men. This theory is the most characteristic and independent part of the Brahmaṇas : in the speculations as to the unity of the universe and the god in whom that unity finds expression, the Brahmaṇas are only inheritors of the speculation of the Rigveda, but in the doctrine of the sacrifice they develop a theory which may have been held in germ at least in the age of the Rigveda, but which is not expressed there and which doubtless in considerable measure is a new creation. This is indicated by one fundamental fact; the sacrifice in the Brāhmaṇas is a piece of magic pure and simple: this is assuredly not the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4 The Ethics of the Brahmaṇas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/27_THE_THEOSOPHY_OF_THE_BRAHMANAS/4_The_Ethics_of_the_brahmaNas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/5_THE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_VEDA/27_THE_THEOSOPHY_OF_THE_BRAHMANAS/4_The_Ethics_of_the_brahmaNas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the strict sense of the word there is no theory of ethics in the Brāhmaṇa literature: the question of the nature of right action does not seem ever to have in any degree influenced the speculations of the curious spirits which framed the remarkable theory of which the outlines have been sketched above. It was, indeed, natural that the first element of the speculative thought of India should in the main be directed to problems of pure speculation, as was also the case in Greece, but the dominating feature in the philosophy of India is that the question of right conduct never attained the dignity of a subject to be propounded for serious consideration. In the Rigveda, while the hymns of creation and the other efforts to arrive at a philosophical account of the universe have beside them the expression in the hymns to Varuna of the prevalence of moral order and the punishment of sin, the latter conception cannot be found in living force any longer in the Brahmaṇas, a fact which has unwisely been used as a proof that early India was exposed to Semitic influences later not felt.1&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
