<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;5 Becoming a Householder on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/5_Becoming_a_Householder/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;5 Becoming a Householder on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/5_Becoming_a_Householder/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 The Voices of Women</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/5_Becoming_a_Householder/1_The_Voices_of_Women/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/5_Becoming_a_Householder/1_The_Voices_of_Women/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The bridge over the Billakurru canal is packed tight with all imaginable colors  flowing in brilliant sun, a kaleidoscope of scintillating saris and glistening  bangles on girls and women thronging the road toward Jaganathota. It is the  long-awaited Tadithota festival, an assembly of gods from fourteen villages  in a spacious palm orchard some three miles from Sriramapuram. Shouting  troupes of men lug giant prabha, garlanded bamboo and papier-mâché floats  for every village god and goddess, each grand enough to carry several riders  along. Formerly they were thirty feet tall with masts strapped on bullock carts  but the new god of electric wires reduced their vertical scale. As if to compen sate, each village increased its amplified drum-and-bugle legion in competi&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2 Marriage</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/5_Becoming_a_Householder/2_Marriage/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/5_Becoming_a_Householder/2_Marriage/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A marriage (vivaha) is a splendid spectacle, everyone liberated from routines,  moving about with the electricity of a holiday outing, brilliant costumes, some  outrageous colors, an aroma of spices loading the air as Cooking Brahmans  labor to prepare vast quantities of food. And yet a marriage also means solemn  rituals with long midnight hours of mantras, fire offerings, seemingly end&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;less recitations of pedigrees. “Marriage is performed out of paramartha, the  highest truth, and it must be continued always with sraddha, faith. Achieving  brahma-loka, the heaven of Brahma, is the whole import of marriage. In a mar riage ceremony happiness is not only for the bride, groom, and relatives. It is  a matter of joy for the entire community.” This earnest declaration by Duvvuri  Yajulu was seconded by others of both genders. Marriage enables the girl to  develop into the coveted role of a su-mangali, an auspicious married woman,  one who has, in T. N. Madan’s apt phrase, “a beneficent influence on the lives  of other people.”7&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 Children and Their Life-cycle Rites</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/5_Becoming_a_Householder/3_Children_and_Their_Life-cycle_Rites/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/5_Becoming_a_Householder/3_Children_and_Their_Life-cycle_Rites/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the center of the main room of the spacious and immaculate new house  a three-month-old baby is constantly rocked side-to-side in a wooden cradle  by his grandmother, Maruti, then swung vigorously head-to-toe in a green  hammock suspended from the ceiling. He sends out no cry for Dramamine.  Maruti has just performed a minor rite, something like an extra samskara,  life-cycle rite. The baby started making fists with his hands, as if squeezing  imaginary balls, so relatives came to be fed with fist-sized lumps (Telugu  mudda) of cooked rice. Here, as in every household, babies steal center stage  from older children running about. In Chapter 6 the diksa consecration is  detailed, a srauta ritual in which both sacrificer and wife are reborn, stammer ing and making fists like babies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4 Livelihood</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/5_Becoming_a_Householder/4_Livelihood/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/5_Becoming_a_Householder/4_Livelihood/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Long walks on rain-drenched roads from Nedunuru to Vyaghresvaram allow  the traveler to see the ways the local folk make their living. Coffee-colored  mud trying with every step to suck chappals from feet, bursts of showers send ing rivulets into shoulder ponds, jade leaves of tapioca gleaming in sporadic  sunlight, scenes heightened every few hundred meters by vistas of a score of  women bent over rice transplants, their brilliant red, yellow, and blue saris  shouting over the passionate green of the fields. Well ahead is the harvest sea son when lines of men will move at a steady trot, balancing loads of this paddy  on their heads, aiming for a far corner of the field where bullock carts wait for  the next load. Never a tractor in any of these expanses. This tropical hike in  part follows the same track as Lanka half a century ago trudging to and from  his Veda lesson of the day. The village of Mukkamalla bustles. A woman at the  well filling her brass lota douses all her neighbors within a hundred meters  with salty invectives. A boy of perhaps nine years swings a massive hammer  onto the glowing ruby iron on his father’s anvil. He will do this every day for  another fifty years, performing his duty, in the parlance of the Gita, even as  another nine-year-old acts according to his dharma by reciting back the fourth  kanda of the Taittiriya Samhita.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 Old Age, Retirement, and Thoughts on Renunciation</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/5_Becoming_a_Householder/5_Old_Age_Retirement_and_Thoughts_on_Renunciation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/5_Becoming_a_Householder/5_Old_Age_Retirement_and_Thoughts_on_Renunciation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In his green-canopied house under beckoning palms in Nedunuru Lanka  was asked how he was feeling. “Jirna!” he replied, summoning the Telugu  and Sanskrit word for digestion. Never a complainer, he was not indicating  stomach or bowel problems but a larger, insoluble one. “I am being digested  by Time” was his message. When he used the familiar metaphor of food for  the untreatable process of aging he might have been reflecting the Taittiriya  Upanisad refrain he learned about the age of ten: aham annam, aham annam,  “I am food, I am food!”15 As noted in Chapter 3, Lanka announced that he  would die at age seventy-two because that was his father’s age at death in 1947.  Also, a mrtyu-cakra, death chart, prepared for him by an astrologer, indicated  severe negative effects from the planet Rahu. But what seemed like Rahu’s  fatal illness was countermanded by Atharva Veda mantras that he knew by  heart. Medicine prescribed for his diabetic condition might have had some thing to do with a return to health. Two years later he and Anasuya discontin&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>6 Death and Beyond</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/5_Becoming_a_Householder/6_Death_and_Beyond/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/5_Becoming_a_Householder/6_Death_and_Beyond/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The subject of death and dying has its own folklore in India, and here the Veda  pandits are not immune. To begin, the vocabulary of thanatos, like that of  eros, is circumvented to every extent possible. Terms for the burning ground  (smasana), cremation (antyesti), ancestor rituals (sraddha), and funeral priest  (apara-vetta) all require pronominal circumlocutions (“there,” “then,” “those,”  “that one,” respectively). The word for widow (vedhava) is unspeakable. Unlike  the easy discussion of Vedas and Sutras, pandits are uncomfortable talking  about current funerals with procedures found in texts separated from auspi cious rites of passage. When a certain temporal distancing has intervened, a  few terms regain normal use, such as words for annual and monthly obser&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
