<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;12 Ritual on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/12_Ritual/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;12 Ritual on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/12_Ritual/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Mantra and Kalpa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/12_Ritual/01_Mantra_and_Kalpa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/12_Ritual/01_Mantra_and_Kalpa/</guid>
      <description>Much of what we found in the preceding chapter is formulated briefly, but clearly, in a post-Vedic work of uncertain date, the Ṛgvidhāna: ‘The mantras attain the (desired) result by the correct method (vidhi) in the brāhmaṇa; they give success, when they are employed in the right ritual manner (vidhivat)’ (translated by J. Gonda).
At the end of the previous chapter we have studied the upanayana initiation during which the Gāyatrī mantra is taught to a young student.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 The Exclusion of Śrauta from Anthropology in English</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/12_Ritual/02_The_Exclusion_of_shrauta_from_Anthropology_in_E/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/12_Ritual/02_The_Exclusion_of_shrauta_from_Anthropology_in_E/</guid>
      <description>We have mainly looked at Śrauta rituals (Seven: Yajurveda) which are described in the Śrauta Sūtras. The other important component of kalpa are the Gṛhya or ‘domestic’ rites which include birth, initiation, marriage, funeral ceremonies and other life-cycle ceremonies. They were not included in Table 1 (Four: The Four Vedas) but incorporate the upanayana ceremony of which we needed an approximate idea because it provided the ritual background and context for the Gāyatrī mantra.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 Self-Embedding and Other Animals</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/12_Ritual/03_Self-Embedding_and_Other_Animals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/12_Ritual/03_Self-Embedding_and_Other_Animals/</guid>
      <description>One difficulty for ritual theory that Hubert and Mauss did not confront is that rituals form a hierarchy and rites at the top of it may last a thousand years or more. To state such a fact, we need recursiveness for statements cannot be infinitely long. Recursiveness is needed to explain language as we have seen. But recursiveness occurs in ritual also and there is a link between grammar and ritual theory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 How the Priests Work Together</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/12_Ritual/04_How_the_Priests_Work_Together/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/12_Ritual/04_How_the_Priests_Work_Together/</guid>
      <description>Vedic ritual is a cooperative activity between priests on behalf of the patron or yajamāna, who is almost always accompanied by his wife. He will remunerate the priests at the end for their work by giving them a dakṣiṇā or ritual gift. This is how Vedic rituals in general are often characterized, and illustrated by descriptions of the more spectacular occasions, such as the Royal Consecration or the famous aśvamedha or horse sacrifice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 Human Sacrifice</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/12_Ritual/05_Human_Sacrifice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/12_Ritual/05_Human_Sacrifice/</guid>
      <description>Most Śrauta rituals require the sacrifice of goats. In the Puruṣa poem, the animal is human and it raises the question: did human sacrifice exist in India? We might start with the noun medha which refers in the Rigveda to the juice of meat or the marrow and later to any animal sacrifice. The term puruṣamedha, coined like aśvamedha or horse sacrifice, is mentioned in the Yajur- and Atharva Brāhmaṇas. The Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa is quite explicit on it and how could it not?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
