<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;12 Ritual on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/12_Ritual/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;12 Ritual on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/12_Ritual/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Mantra and Kalpa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/12_Ritual/01_Mantra_and_Kalpa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/12_Ritual/01_Mantra_and_Kalpa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Much of what we found in the preceding chapter is formulated briefly, but clearly, in a post-Vedic work of uncertain date, the Ṛ&lt;em&gt;gvidhāna&lt;/em&gt;: ‘The mantras attain the (desired) result by the correct method (&lt;em&gt;vidhi&lt;/em&gt;) in the &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt;; they give success, when they are employed in the right ritual manner (&lt;em&gt;vidhivat&lt;/em&gt;)’ (translated by J. Gonda).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;At the end of the previous chapter we have studied the upanayana initiation during which the Gāyatrī mantra is taught to a young student. I have argued that the way it is learned is totally different from the manner in which children learn or rather pick up their native natural language. But just as mantras derive their effectiveness from ritual, and not from language, no Vedic rite should be performed without mantras. In ritual, mantras are also treated differently from the sentences of a language. In the utterance of the latter, shouting, whispering or silence are options that individuals may use on whatever occasions they wish. If I cannot be heard, I may decide to raise my voice. If I wish to inspire confidentiality, I may whisper. But in ritual contexts, the occasions are fixed. When offerings are made, the accompanying mantra ends with &lt;em&gt;vauṣa&lt;/em&gt;ṭ! ‘May (Agni) lead the offerings to the gods!’ The priest should shout the second syllable ṢAṬ! at the top of his voice. In a larger number of contexts, mantras are recited mentally (&lt;em&gt;manasā&lt;/em&gt;), more specifically &lt;em&gt;upāṃśu&lt;/em&gt;, ‘articulated but inaudible’ (&lt;em&gt;Seven: Yajurveda&lt;/em&gt;), which is distinguished from the ritual being performed &lt;em&gt;tūṣṇīm&lt;/em&gt;, ‘in silence’.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 The Exclusion of Śrauta from Anthropology in English</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/12_Ritual/02_The_Exclusion_of_shrauta_from_Anthropology_in_E/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/12_Ritual/02_The_Exclusion_of_shrauta_from_Anthropology_in_E/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We have mainly looked at Śrauta rituals (&lt;em&gt;Seven: Yajurveda&lt;/em&gt;) which are described in the Śrauta Sūtras. The other important component of &lt;em&gt;kalpa&lt;/em&gt; are the Gṛhya or ‘domestic’ rites which include birth, initiation, marriage, funeral ceremonies and other life-cycle ceremonies. They were not included in Table 1 (&lt;em&gt;Four: The Four Vedas&lt;/em&gt;) but incorporate the &lt;em&gt;upanayana&lt;/em&gt; ceremony of which we needed an approximate idea because it provided the ritual background and context for the Gāyatrī mantra. One reason for the exclusion of life-cycle ceremonies from the present account of Vedic ritual is that these types of ceremony occur worldwide. Though their forms vary greatly, their social functions and significance are well understood since Arnold van Gennep whose ideas were developed by a group of British, American, and other anthropologists that include Victor Turner, Mary Douglas, Clifford Geertz and others. Life-cycle ceremonies may be explained in terms of boundaries that are crossed. I shall confine myself to the Śrauta rituals not only because they are, in Vedic India, more basic, but also because they cannot be explained with the help of the conceptual machinery of these anthropologists. It is here that the theories of ritual of many scholars of religion and of social scientists, especially in the English-speaking world, break down. The other reasons for not including the domestic rituals here is that the only remarkable features they possess beyond ‘liminality’ are influenced by or modelled on Śrauta rites.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Self-Embedding and Other Animals</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/12_Ritual/03_Self-Embedding_and_Other_Animals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/12_Ritual/03_Self-Embedding_and_Other_Animals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One difficulty for ritual theory that Hubert and Mauss did not confront is that rituals form a hierarchy and rites at the top of it may last a thousand years or more. To state such a fact, we need recursiveness for statements cannot be infinitely long. Recursiveness is needed to explain language as we have seen. But recursiveness occurs in ritual also and there is a link between grammar and ritual theory. The grammarian Patañjali, author of the &lt;em&gt;Great Commentary&lt;/em&gt; on Pāṇini’s grammar, was the first to arrive at that important insight. He wrote that neither rites, nor forms of language can be enumerated because no such enumeration would reach the end. Ritual and language can only be described and explained by treatises that provide &lt;em&gt;rules&lt;/em&gt;. Such rules are called &lt;em&gt;sūtra&lt;/em&gt; and that is what the Śrauta Sūtras and Pāṇini’s grammar are therefore called.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 How the Priests Work Together</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/12_Ritual/04_How_the_Priests_Work_Together/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/12_Ritual/04_How_the_Priests_Work_Together/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Vedic ritual is a cooperative activity between priests on behalf of the patron or &lt;em&gt;yajamāna&lt;/em&gt;, who is almost always accompanied by his wife. He will remunerate the priests at the end for their work by giving them a &lt;em&gt;dakṣiṇā&lt;/em&gt; or ritual gift. This is how Vedic rituals in general are often characterized, and illustrated by descriptions of the more spectacular occasions, such as the Royal Consecration or the famous &lt;em&gt;aśvamedha&lt;/em&gt; or horse sacrifice. But when we witness the more commonly and frequently performed Śrauta rituals, and study their history, another and different picture emerges.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Human Sacrifice</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/12_Ritual/05_Human_Sacrifice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/12_Ritual/05_Human_Sacrifice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most Śrauta rituals require the sacrifice of goats. In the Puruṣa poem, the animal is human and it raises the question: did human sacrifice exist in India? We might start with the noun &lt;em&gt;medha&lt;/em&gt; which refers in the Rigveda to the juice of meat or the marrow and later to any animal sacrifice. The term &lt;em&gt;puruṣamedha&lt;/em&gt;, coined like &lt;em&gt;aśvamedha&lt;/em&gt; or horse sacrifice, is mentioned in the Yajur- and Atharva Brāhmaṇas. The Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa is quite explicit on it and how could it not? There is nothing with which the Brāhmaṇas do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; deal, as we have seen. In 1882, the learned translator of these texts, Julius Eggeling, had some worthwhile things to say on them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
