<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Source Notes on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Source Notes on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>00 PREFACE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/00_PREFACE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/00_PREFACE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;‘It is analytic and attempts to shed light … absurd statements circulate’: Rigveda 1.164.44 puts &lt;em&gt;iṇgayanti&lt;/em&gt; in context on &lt;em&gt;pp.&lt;/em&gt; 295–7.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘Kurt Gödel and Alfred Tarski’ : Feferman and Feferman 2004.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘W. H. Auden’ : Auden 1948.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘Robert Gardner’ : Gardner 1992.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘The chief result was AGNI, &lt;em&gt;The Vedic Ritual of the Fire Altar&lt;/em&gt;’ : The long title of &lt;em&gt;AGNI,&lt;/em&gt; included in the Bibliography, will be abbreviated into ‘Staal, CV and Itti Ravi 1983.’&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>01</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;‘Yājñavalkya, a Vedic sage, taught his wife Maitreyī’ : Brhad-Āraṇyaka Upaniṣad (BĀU) 2.4.12, 4.5.15 as translated by Olivelle, Patrick. 1996, 1998. &lt;em&gt;Upaniṣads. Translated from the Original Sanskrit&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 30, 71. I shall make frequent use of this excellent book and refer to it simply as ‘Olivelle.’—I have added ‘of specifics’ for clarity (shown by the context).—‘Yājñavalkya was a native of Kosala’ and ‘the eastern fringe of the Vedic area’: Witzel 1997: 313–15.—Witzel, Michael. 2003. ‘Yājñavalkya as ritualist and philosopher, and his personal language,’ in Adhami, S. (ed.), &lt;em&gt;Paitimāna. Essays in Iranian, Indo-European, and Indian Studies in Honor of Hanns-Peter Schmidt.&lt;/em&gt; Vols I–II. Casta Mesa CA: Mazda Publishers, 2003, pp. 103–143, goes much deeper into the different personalities of Yājñavalkya, his ideas, style and personal language. #91.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;‘Oral traditions provide us with information on localities and civilization …’ : Falk 1981 on ruins.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘Figure 7 provides us with small models of toy carts’ : Kenoyer in &lt;em&gt;Rad und Wagen&lt;/em&gt;. Mackay, R. and R.E.M. Wheeler. 1938. &lt;em&gt;Further Excavations at Mohenjo Daro&lt;/em&gt;. Delhi: The Archaeological Survey of India. Chariots in the Near East: Richter 2004.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘The Rigveda derives from the terminology of chariots and spokes’ : RV 1.164.11 which will be quoted on &lt;em&gt;pp.&lt;/em&gt; 334–5.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;‘It begins to be visible in late Vedic works and in the Post-Vedic &lt;em&gt;Dharma Sūtras …&lt;/em&gt; and … in the law book of Manu’ : Olivelle 1999 and 2004 are the most recent and reliable translations into English. For Dharma in Indic civilization from the Vedas onward: Olivelle, Patrick. (ed.), 2004, Special Issue of the &lt;em&gt;Journal of Indian Philosophy&lt;/em&gt; 32/5–6: 421–870. #335. ‘Nor is there evidence for ‘free Aryans and subjugated indigenous people’: Kulke and Rothermund 1998: 34, 39.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;‘Yājñavalkya is said to have received his mantras directly from the Sun’ : a theme of the Chandogya Upaniṣad with respect to OM; below, &lt;em&gt;pp.&lt;/em&gt; 127–8.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘The Bharata chieftains are portrayed as practitioners of a multilateral policy’ : Witzel 1997b: 262–4. The names of Bharatas, Kurus, Pañcalas and others are recited during performances of Vedic ritual: below, &lt;em&gt;p.&lt;/em&gt; 75. &lt;em&gt;Bharat&lt;/em&gt; did not only become the name of India but spread with Vedic fire rites over large parts of Asia as the name of one of the fires: Strickmann, Michel. 1983. ‘Homa in East Asia’ in Staal, CV and Itti Ravi 1983, II: 418–55 records various forms: &lt;em&gt;Pitara&lt;/em&gt; in Japan (which has nothing to do with ‘fathers’), &lt;em&gt;Baratha&lt;/em&gt; in Tibet, etc.:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;‘Other Vedic compositions … about which Renou wrote: ‘One cannot grasp’ : Renou 1953: 34.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘The anthology by Wendy Doniger remains the most accessible’ : Doniger 1981. On Wendy herself: Doniger 1998.—‘The reader who wants more and knows German’: Geldner (1951, 1957) and #352.—‘Renou has also translated most of the hymns in French’: Renou (1955–69).—‘No one can find anything without the concordance’: Rau (1969). Now see also: Brereton and Jamison (above, &lt;em&gt;Preface:&lt;/em&gt; xxix).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;‘The Sāmaveda takes all its words from (the Rigveda)’ : Renou 1952 on those that do not so derive.—‘The Sāmaveda or Veda of Melodies or Chants … set to music’: van der Hoogt 1929; Faddegon, Barend. 1951. &lt;em&gt;Studies in the Sāmaveda&lt;/em&gt;, Part I, Amsterdam: North-Holland Publishing Company, is solid and often entertaining.—‘The reason is not that two melodies are mentioned in the Rigveda by name’: RV 10.181.1–2 mention Rathantara and Brhat.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;‘Sāyaṇa, a scholar of a deep and wide-ranging knowledge’ : Renou 1947: 9 quotes Sāyaṇa’s words from his commentary on the Taittiriya Saṃhita: &lt;em&gt;bhittisthānīyo yajurvedaś citrasthānīyāv itarau&lt;/em&gt;.—‘Stephen Lindquist is right that we should sometimes’: Stephen Lindquist ‘On Shattered Heads and Daft Robbers: Rethinking Sakalya in BĀU 3’, forthcoming, in Proceedings of the Fourth International Vedic Workshop at the University of Texas, Austin (see &lt;em&gt;Preface,&lt;/em&gt; xxx).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘He (Harold Bailey) once made a passing suggestion’ : 1984. ‘Vedic &lt;em&gt;kṣumpa&lt;/em&gt;—and connected data.’ Joshi, S.D. (ed.), &lt;em&gt;Amṛ**tadhārā: Prof. R.N. Dandekar Felicitation Volume&lt;/em&gt;. Delhi: 17–20.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;‘The composer-priests were Āṅgirasas and Bhārgavas’ : clans of priests and composers of circles of the Rigveda discussed by Witzel 1997b: 262, 292. H.W. Bailey related the word Āṅgirasas to English &lt;em&gt;angel&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘These were spectacular finds …’ : Bhattacharyya, Durgamohan. 1957. ‘A Palm-Leaf Manuscript of the Paippalāda Samhitā: Announcement of a Rare Find’. &lt;em&gt;Our Heritage&lt;/em&gt; 5:81–86. 1970. Paippalāda Samhitā &lt;em&gt;of the Atharvaveda. Volume Two. Edited from Original Manuscripts with Critical Notes.&lt;/em&gt; Calcutta: Sanskrit College. Bhattacharyya, Dipak. 1997. &lt;em&gt;The&lt;/em&gt; Paippalāda Samhitā &lt;em&gt;of the Atharvaveda. Edited from Original Manuscripts with Critical Notes.&lt;/em&gt; Calcutta: Sanskrit College. &lt;em&gt;Volume Two. Edited from Original Manuscripts with Critical Notes.&lt;/em&gt; Calcutta: Sanskrit College.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;‘The civilization of the Brāhmaṇas and Āraṇyakas or ‘Forest Books’ … illustrates at the same time that &lt;em&gt;forest&lt;/em&gt; continued to be contrasted with &lt;em&gt;village&lt;/em&gt;’ : Malamoud 1976 treats forests and villages, Sprokhoff 1981 and Rau 1997 villages.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘He (Agni) could not cross the Sadānīrā’ : Satapatha Brāhmaṇa 1.4.1.14.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘We have seen that the term &lt;em&gt;Brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; is used in several senses … one of them: a Vedic composition in prose’ : Rau 1957, 1970 and 1976 examine the society that is depicted in these Brāhmaṇas. Since at least 1962, more than a hundred scholarly studies have been devoted to the society of the Brāhmaṇas and related topics, especially ritual, by Klaus Mylius. They are listed in Göhler, Lars (ed.), 2005. &lt;em&gt;Indische Kultur im Kontext: Rituale, Texte und Ideen aud Indien unde der Welt. Festschrift Professor Klays Mylius,&lt;/em&gt; Wiesbaden: Otto Harrassowitz: 457–473. Mylius was the most well-known Vedic and Sanskrit scholar in what was formerly known as the German Democratic Republic. It explains some Marxist phrases, easily abstracted, and would fit in the wider historical perspective of India at the time of the Brāhmaṇas as studied by Basu 1969, outdated in parts.—‘That is what brahmins always remained, in India as elsewhere’: Skilling, Peter. 2007. ‘King, Sangha, and Brahmans: Ideology, Ritual and Power in Pre-Modern Siam’ in Harris, Ian, (ed.), 2007. &lt;em&gt;Buddhism, Power and Political Order&lt;/em&gt;. London and New York: Routledge: 182–215, is much more detailed and specific.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;‘The term occurs first at the end of the Vedic period’ : ‘The ascetics who have firmly determined their goal through a full knowledge of the Vedānta, have their being purified by the discipline of renunciation’ (Muṇḍaka Upaniṣad 3.2.6, tr. Olivelle).—‘One of the earliest of these is the philosophy of Bhāskara’: Ingalls, Daniel H.H. 1967. ‘Bhāskara the Vedāntin,’ &lt;em&gt;Philosophy East and West. A Journal of Oriental and Comparative Thought&lt;/em&gt;: 61–7 says it is replete with ‘vitriolic references’ against Śaṇkara.—‘His Vedanta is called A-dvaita Vedānta because its position is “non-dual”’: the term &lt;em&gt;advaita&lt;/em&gt; was coined by Yājñavalkya: Witzel 2003 in #3.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;‘If it is true that mantras and ritual have no meaning …’ : even Alper, Harvey. P. 1989. &lt;em&gt;Understanding Mantras&lt;/em&gt;. Albany: State University of New York (SUNY) Press, an impressive collection of articles and the most authoritative bibliography until that date, does not arrive at a clear conclusion of what mantras are. He does pay reasoned attention to a variety of views and opinions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘Language is a system in which everything hangs together’ : De Saussure, Ferdinand. 1915, etc. &lt;em&gt;Cours de Linguistique Générale&lt;/em&gt;. Publié par Charles Bally et Albert Sechehaye. Paris: Payot. I have not found the phrase &lt;em&gt;où tout se tient&lt;/em&gt; in this book but it expresses his basic insight which is tantamount to saying that language is a &lt;em&gt;synchronistic&lt;/em&gt; system—a reaction against the &lt;em&gt;diachronistic&lt;/em&gt; philology of his predecessors. Pāṇini also presents a &lt;em&gt;synchronistic&lt;/em&gt; system but for different and erroneous reasons: he believed that Sanskrit did not change—a belief that de Saussure did not share. Beliefs however do not matter: what counts in science are the results, not what scientists say or believe about it. (‘Newton’s Lesson’: Staal. 1993, 94. &lt;em&gt;Concepts of Science in Europe and Asia,&lt;/em&gt; Chapter 1. Leiden: International Institute for Asian Studies.)—It would not be surprising for &lt;em&gt;tout se tient&lt;/em&gt; to apply to language if it applied to the universe. Evidence is mounting; but it has not been demonstrated.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;‘Much of what we found in the preceding chapter … &lt;em&gt;Ṛgvidhāna&lt;/em&gt;: “The mantras attain the desired result”’ : Gonda, J. 1951. &lt;em&gt;The&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Ṛgvidhāna&lt;/em&gt;, Utrecht: Oosthoek, 1.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘Unlike mantras, ritual consists of acts. I can do no more than give a rough idea’ : ‘The Syntactic study of Vedic ritual’: the chapter on ‘Ritual Structure’ in Staal, CV and Itti Ravi 1983, II: 127–35, was perhaps the first sketch of that idea but it was very incomplete. Forerunners in anthropology, sociology and religious studies include Hubert and Mauss 1899 (pp. 224–5); and in the sister discipline of linguistics, the Sanskrit grammarians and Chomsky, Noam 1957. &lt;em&gt;Syntactic Structures&lt;/em&gt;. The Hague: Mouton, which inspired major advances in linguistics and led to new disciplines such as the cognitive sciences. In a wider context, emphasis on syntax characterizes mathematics and modern logic.—On Vedic ritual the scientific literature is immense, starting as it does with the Vedic treatises, the commentaries of Sāyaṇa (‘The Role of the Yajurveda’: Chapter 7, &lt;em&gt;pp.&lt;/em&gt; 118–121), which are basically ritual-oriented even where the Vedas are not, and modern studies that started to flourish in the nineteenth century with Albrecht Weber (brother of the more well-known sociologist Max) and are now flourishing not only in India but wherever the Vedas are seriously studied. Dictionaries include Renou 1954 and more detailed: Sen, Chitrabhanu. 1978, 1982. &lt;em&gt;A Dictionary of the Vedic Rituals based on the&lt;/em&gt; Ś&lt;em&gt;rauta and Gṛhya Sūtras&lt;/em&gt;. Delhi: Concept Publishing Company. Many of Mylius’ articles and recensions (#149) deal with Vedic ritual, e.g.: Mylius, Klaus. 2000. &lt;em&gt;Das altindische Opfer&lt;/em&gt;. Wichtrach: Institut für Indologie.—Rather than talk/write/think about ritual, one should participate in or witness one, and if that is not feasible (which in India it sometimes is), stay in one’s armchair with Staal, CV and Itti Ravi 1983, Volume I until sleep prevails.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;‘All the larger Soma rituals are characterized by sequences of rites which I have called “Soma Sequences”’ : described in Staal, CV and Itti Ravi 1983, I, throughout the later chapters.—‘You are the bed for coupling Rik and Sāman for the sake of procreation:’ &lt;em&gt;p.&lt;/em&gt; 183 with note.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘The ritual has been, has been produced/It is born, it has grown’ : Staal, CV and Itti Ravi 1983, I: 625 and Taittirīya Samhitā 3.2.7.2m.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;‘Science is universal, but the concept of science varies in different cultures’ : Staal. 1993, 1994. #195.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘Imagine we want to transform a rectangle into a square with the same area’ : Staal 1999 and 2001a.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘There may be links between that large unit and scientific developments in Africa, but not with Meso-American Cultures’ : Paz 1995: 91.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘The Vedic sciences are not objects that moderns are at liberty to make up’ : Torella (ed.), 2001 treats the Vedic sciences as part of the history of Indic sciences by various authors in Section II, Part I. Flood (ed.), 2003 has a chapter on four Indian sciences in which the initial periods deal with Vedic sciences: Linguistics by Staal, Mathematics by Takao Hayashi, Calendar, Astrology and Astronomy by Michio Yano and Medicine by Dominik Wujastyk.—This was anticipated by a more adventurous list: freely after Olivelle 166–7.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;‘The phrase “narrowing religious outlook” comes from’ : Jawaharlal Nehru. 1946. &lt;em&gt;The Discovery of India&lt;/em&gt;. New York: The John Day Company, 568 ff.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘The Powers of Language’ : originally inspired by Renou 1955, ‘Les pouvoirs de la parole dans le Ṛgveda’ which emphasized &lt;em&gt;vāc manasā&lt;/em&gt;, discussed throughout this book. Related notions include &lt;em&gt;pratibhā&lt;/em&gt;, ‘intuition’ (Gonda 1963b and 1963a in general), &lt;em&gt;guru,&lt;/em&gt; ‘teacher’ (Gonda 1965a), &lt;em&gt;upaniṣad&lt;/em&gt; (p. 158), etc.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘Where the sages fashioned language with their thought … filtering it like parched grain’ : Rigveda circle 9 deals with filtering the Soma liquid.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;‘A natural end might consist in the story of what happened to the Vedas after the Vedas’ : Renou 1960b did provide such a survey though ‘he could not have mentioned more recent events’ (p. 304).—‘Much is now known about the arrival of Vedism in South India’: Mahadevan, T.P. Forthcoming.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘These periods are of special interest because they carried traces to:’ South-east Asia, including on Thailand, with Khmer information Skilling 2007 (# 149) and on Bali: Hooykaas 1966, 1983 a. and b., all referring to other works by the same author. In Bali, an apparently post-Vedic version of the Taittirīya Upaniṣad was found.—‘These and other contemporary developments’: Arnold has remained unpublished; Kashikar and Parpola 1983; Knipe 1997 and 2004; Mahadevan and Staal 2003, 2005; Raghavan 1957. ‘Present Position of Vedic Chanting and Its Future’, &lt;em&gt;Bulletin of the Institute of Traditional Cultures&lt;/em&gt; (Madras): 49–69; Smith 1984, 1994, 2000, 2001; Witzel 1992. Staal 1961, etc.; T.P. Mahadevan. Forthcoming. Staal, CV and Itti Ravi 1983. Galewicz 2004 should be added.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>18 APPENDICES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/18_APPENDICES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/18_APPENDICES/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Needham 1976 : 22–4, 95–6; Chemla and Shuchun 2004, ‘Présentation du Chapitre 9’ especially pages 674 and following.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Heath 1956. Vol.I : 349–50.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>READINGS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/19_READINGS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/0/Source_Notes/19_READINGS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;‘If I had to recommend a single general book about the Vedas … certainly outdated’ : Renou 1953.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Half a century later and taking account of the enormous increases in knowledge and insight, but for those who read German: more than half of Witzel, Michael. 2003. &lt;em&gt;Das alte Indien&lt;/em&gt; (‘Ancient India’).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;München: C.H. Beck.—‘For those who read German, Geldner remains the best guide:’ Geldner, Karl Friedrich. 1951–57. &lt;em&gt;Der Rig-Veda aus dem Sanskrit ins Deutsche übersetzt und miet einem laufenden Kommentarversehen&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
