<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;16 Buddhism on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/5_THE_VEDAS_AND_BUDDHISM/16_Buddhism/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;16 Buddhism on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/5_THE_VEDAS_AND_BUDDHISM/16_Buddhism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Why Buddhism?</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/5_THE_VEDAS_AND_BUDDHISM/16_Buddhism/01_Why_Buddhism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/5_THE_VEDAS_AND_BUDDHISM/16_Buddhism/01_Why_Buddhism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Kāśyapa or Mahākāśyapa, whose first name was Pippali, was born in Magadha around the fifth century BCE. His name comes from &lt;em&gt;kaśyapa&lt;/em&gt; which means ‘tortoise’ and is a non-Indo-European word. His father, Kapila, was a rich brahman, perhaps a descendant of a Vedic family of Indic origins. &lt;em&gt;Kapila&lt;/em&gt; is a Vedic colour term referring to a brownish hue, perhaps derived from &lt;em&gt;kapi&lt;/em&gt; or ‘monkey’. His mother’s name was Sumanādevī. He married Bhadrā Kāpilānī, a girl from Śākala but the marriage was not consummated. Both decided to retire from the world and went their own ways as was not uncommon during those Upaniṣadic times at the end of the Veda. They left their names which provide us with some information, but a great deal more is known about Kāśyapa.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 History, Geography and an Inkling of Nirvāṇa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/5_THE_VEDAS_AND_BUDDHISM/16_Buddhism/02_History_Geography_and_an_Inkling_of_nirvANa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/5_THE_VEDAS_AND_BUDDHISM/16_Buddhism/02_History_Geography_and_an_Inkling_of_nirvANa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Questions concerning the early relations between Buddhism and the Vedas are highly controversial and can only be answered by taking a closer look at history and geography.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We also have to widen the perspective. Jainism is demonstrably older than Buddhism and did certainly exist at the time of the Upaniṣads. Jainism is generally ascribed to Mahāvīra, an older contemporary of the Buddha, but Jaina sources mention many precursors of which one, Pārśva, is historical, pushing the date back to the ninth century BCE—the time of the Yajurveda. For the Buddha’s death or &lt;em&gt;nirvāṇa&lt;/em&gt; (a term that means ‘enlightenment’ or ‘extinction’, literally ‘blowing out’, and does not occur in the early Upaniṣads), we have two chronologies, the long and the short. The long one assigns it to around 486 BCE. The short one assigns it to around 368 BCE. There is no controversy about his place of birth, which is Kapilāvastu, a place below the lower foothills of the Himalayas, located close to the modern border between India and Nepal. From there the Buddha made his way southwards and reached the kingdom of Magadha with which we have been familiar since the map of Figure 2 where it is indicated by Mg. It is south-east of the Ganges near Pāṭaliputra, modern Patna. The later portions of the Rigvedic Aitareya Brāhmaṇa were familiar with this area and tell us that the Vedic sage Viśvāmitra adopted Magadha tribes that were living there. During this period, major clearance of jungle areas took place, facilitated by the increased use of iron tools. It led to an expanse of rice cultivation with a surplus in production which allowed lavish spending on large rituals such as those performed by King Janaka, a figure known to the composers of the Bṛhad-Āraṇyaka Upaniṣad and in Buddhist sources which does not prove much since both refer to the past often.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 About the Vedas and Buddhism</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/5_THE_VEDAS_AND_BUDDHISM/16_Buddhism/03_About_the_Vedas_and_Buddhism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/5_THE_VEDAS_AND_BUDDHISM/16_Buddhism/03_About_the_Vedas_and_Buddhism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Are we getting immersed in details, history and geography, and losing the forest for the trees? I have three general quotes to keep the reader on our track of discovery, two from modern scholars, one from Indian philosophy and a small Indic diversion to widen the perspective before we take a plunge into deeper waters.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Rigveda went further than deriving pleasure from poetry and poetics. It presents us with a positive outlook on life that is not absent from the Sāmaveda, becomes more turbid in the Yajurveda and returns in the Upaniṣads. I am not preaching a return to the Vedic life or adoption of the Buddhist path. I am looking for light they may throw on each other and what we can learn from this. Here a quote about the spirit of the Rigveda from Wendy Doniger in her chapter on ‘Realia’ is useful. It does more than that label suggests and was written, I am sure, without the author giving Buddhism a thought:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Entering the Order, Women and Sexualities</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/5_THE_VEDAS_AND_BUDDHISM/16_Buddhism/04_Entering_the_Order_Women_and_Sexualities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/5_THE_VEDAS_AND_BUDDHISM/16_Buddhism/04_Entering_the_Order_Women_and_Sexualities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Buddhism consists of three parts: Buddha, Dharma and Sangha. We have touched upon the former two but it is the Sangha or Order that exhibits the most important differences between Buddhism and the Vedas. Institutionalization like that of the Buddhist Sangha existed already in Jainism. But Jainism remained isolated and conservative and never seems to have posed a challenge to Vedic Indians. The Rigveda describes wandering sages, but they do not seem to belong to sectarian groups and the Vedic nomads were wandering anyway.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Ahiṃsā and the Public Domain</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/5_THE_VEDAS_AND_BUDDHISM/16_Buddhism/05_ahiMsA_and_the_Public_Domain/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/5_THE_VEDAS_AND_BUDDHISM/16_Buddhism/05_ahiMsA_and_the_Public_Domain/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In spite of the special cases that have just been described, the Buddhist teaching or Dharma is open to everyone: it is &lt;em&gt;public&lt;/em&gt;—like the Upaniṣads became eventually. The Aṇguttara Nikāya, an early Buddhist Pali text, declares: ‘Three things are hidden and not public: the wife, the mantras of Brahmans and erroneous views. Three things shine in public and are not hidden: the moon, the sun and the dharma.’ This is a magnificent piece of public relations though it did not prevent the eventual disappearance of Buddhism from India after ca. 1,000 CE.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 Eschatology and Karmic Arithmetic</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/5_THE_VEDAS_AND_BUDDHISM/16_Buddhism/06_Eschatology_and_Karmic_Arithmetic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/5_THE_VEDAS_AND_BUDDHISM/16_Buddhism/06_Eschatology_and_Karmic_Arithmetic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are now ready to return to the thesis of Gananath Obeyesekhere, discussed in Chapter 10: in matters of life and death around the world, rebirth is the default option. I showed in that context that rebirth does occur in the Vedas but did not comment on Gananath’s other thesis: the Buddhist concept of rebirth is ethical unlike the Vedic varieties. I believe that is only partly true. Vedic ideas about rebirth display features that are ethical such as notions of merit and demerit. They refer to ‘ritual’ and ‘good’ acts at the same time because they are not clearly distinguished from each other. The same is true of Buddhism as we shall now see.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 Conceptual Problems</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/5_THE_VEDAS_AND_BUDDHISM/16_Buddhism/07_Conceptual_Problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/5_THE_VEDAS_AND_BUDDHISM/16_Buddhism/07_Conceptual_Problems/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We may now turn to the more exalted level of philosophy in the Vedas and Buddhism. Both seem to accept an absolute. That applies in the Vedas primarily to the Upaniṣads and in Buddhism especially to some philosophies. The common perception is that the Upaniṣadic &lt;em&gt;brahman&lt;/em&gt; is positive. It is described as ‘fullness’, &lt;em&gt;pūrṇam&lt;/em&gt;, as we have seen. The corresponding Buddhist negative is expressed as ‘emptiness’ (&lt;em&gt;śūnyatā&lt;/em&gt;). It plays an important role in Buddhism unlike the ‘nothing’ of the CU, furthest away from Buddhism in time and space, where no special attention is paid to it. The BĀU accepts an absolute to which it refers as &lt;em&gt;neti neti&lt;/em&gt; as we have seen. It seems to exhibit the distinction made in some European philosophies between metaphysics or ontology, which deals with what there is (e.g., an absolute), and epistemology, the theory of knowledge, which asks how we can know or describe it, e.g., ‘in the negative’, as by &lt;em&gt;neti neti&lt;/em&gt;. The distinction is obsolete because it cannot be expressed in Chinese and is, therefore, not universal, as A.C. Graham has shown.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 Dharma and Cakra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/5_THE_VEDAS_AND_BUDDHISM/16_Buddhism/08_Dharma_and_Cakra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/5_THE_VEDAS_AND_BUDDHISM/16_Buddhism/08_Dharma_and_Cakra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Buddhism made use of Vedic terms and concepts not only because it was part of the current language. It also inherited and made judicious use of the spoked wheel (&lt;em&gt;cakra&lt;/em&gt;) of early Indo-Aryans and Indo-Europeans. It accounts for the name of the Buddha’s first exposition of his doctrine as &lt;em&gt;Dharma-cakra-pravartana&lt;/em&gt;, ‘the setting into motion of the wheel of Dharma’. &lt;em&gt;Pravartana&lt;/em&gt; is derived from &lt;em&gt;vartana&lt;/em&gt; which comes from the verbal root &lt;em&gt;v&lt;/em&gt;ṛ&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;—and was used around 1380 BCE in Kikkuli’s Mitanni treatise to refer to the ‘turns’ that horses are taught to take in the course of their domestication as we have noted in Chapter 1. The wheel of the Buddhist Dharma, was set into motion by the Buddha in the Deer Park at Sarnath, outside Benares. It is depicted in Theravāda and Mahāyāna Buddhist art, beginning with Sanchi and throughout the Buddhist world. It has even been adopted by the Bonpos of Tibet but they turn it in the other direction.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 The First University and Buddhist Logic</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/5_THE_VEDAS_AND_BUDDHISM/16_Buddhism/09_The_First_University_and_Buddhist_Logic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/5_THE_VEDAS_AND_BUDDHISM/16_Buddhism/09_The_First_University_and_Buddhist_Logic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After the Vedas, Sanskrit became the language of learning with Prakrit or Prakrits as close seconds in Buddhist circles. Many traditions remained oral but after Aśoka (268–231 BCE), writing began to be used. With the development of cities, some became known for their Sanskrit learning. Most famous were Kāśī, Varāṇasī or Benares in the north and Kānchīpuram in the south. Buddha’s first sermon, the &lt;em&gt;Dharma-cakra-pravartana&lt;/em&gt; of the previous section, took place at Sarnath, just outside Benares. Kānchī became a centre of Buddhist learning later. During my last visit to its numerous temples, I came upon a large image of the Buddha kept in the garden of the police station.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 Final Conclusions</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/5_THE_VEDAS_AND_BUDDHISM/16_Buddhism/10_Final_Conclusions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/5_THE_VEDAS_AND_BUDDHISM/16_Buddhism/10_Final_Conclusions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Vedas are not all of a piece and it would be unreasonable to expect a single final conclusion about them. What I can do is make a few remarks about Buddhism and the Vedas and try to place them in a wider perspective.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Vedic civilization does not offer us a founder, order or doctrine. Buddhism provides the Buddha and the Sangha, but if we look at its many schools and ramifications, it is clear that it does not offer a single doctrine either. There are many similarities in ideas propounded by the Vedas and doctrines taught by Buddhist schools at different points during their long careers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
