<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;घोराङ्गीरसः on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/GA/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;घोराङ्गीरसः on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/GA/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>adhikAra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/GA/adhikAra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/GA/adhikAra/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
Limitation The गायत्री-मन्त्र is a वैदिक-मन्त्र. All वैदिक-मन्त्र-s, as a general rule, require the following:
One has to be of त्रैवर्णिक descent. (From various sources, one surmises that the adhikāra for veda comes from being descended from a ṛṣi with whom the veda is associated.) One has to undergo उपनयन to become a द्विज. One must acquire that वेदमन्त्र from a गुरु, who himself has satisfied all 3 conditions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RShi-IP</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/GA/RShi-IP/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/GA/RShi-IP/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
Some are upset with the phrase, “your knowledge systems” below. Is it really so offensive? The 100s of references to Āṅgirasas, Bhāradvājas, Gotamās, Kāṇvas, Bhṛgavas, Jamadagnis, Vāsiṣṭhas, Viśvāmitras/Kuśikas, Agastis, Ātreyas, Kaśyapas throughout the Veda are not in vain.
All of the aforementioned Ṛṣi groups are survived by descendants till today who are still learning this body of scripture. Anyone can read the Veda, sure. But you can’t help but notice right away (if you are not reading it mindlessly) that the Veda is the ancestral heritage of a group that still survives by Īśvara’s Will &amp;amp; grace, despite whatever hate you may throw at it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ऋषिकाः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/GA/RShikAH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/GA/RShikAH/</guid>
      <description>A basic point that many don’t understand is that a general Adhikāra in Veda for a Class does not arise from a few members of said Class being Brahmavādinīs or being Ṛṣikās.
Secondly, the Ṛṣikā argument is very misleading when you realize that many of the alleged Ṛṣikās are non-human. Where the Ṛṣikā is indeed human, often, the mantras attributed to her are literally quotations or form part of a dialogue that is not in praise of a deity.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
