<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;घोराङ्गीरसः on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/GA/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;घोराङ्गीरसः on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/GA/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>adhikAra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/GA/adhikAra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/GA/adhikAra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/GhorAngirasa/status/1264891339491041280&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;limitation&#34;&gt;Limitation&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The गायत्री-मन्त्र is a वैदिक-मन्त्र. All वैदिक-मन्त्र-s, as a general rule, require the following:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;One has to be of त्रैवर्णिक descent. (From various sources, one surmises that the adhikāra for veda comes from being descended from a ṛṣi with whom the veda is associated.)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;One has to undergo उपनयन to become a द्विज.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;One must acquire that वेदमन्त्र from a गुरु, who himself has satisfied all 3 conditions.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If a SC follows all the vidhis then ?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BrAhmaNa continuity</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/GA/brAhmaNa-continuity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/GA/brAhmaNa-continuity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/GhorAngirasa/status/1789916114614427705&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Anyone who ignores the Brāhmaṇa texts of the Veda &amp;amp; the Karmakāṇḍa, and treats them as if they are non-existent, in their overall narrative on the meaning of the Veda, no matter how eloquent they are or sagacious they sound, cannot be authoritative, let alone a Ṛṣi.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Problem is even those who affirm the Vedatvam of the Brāhmaṇa texts ignore their importance &amp;amp; their overall interpretative framework makes Śrauta rituals &amp;amp; Karmakāṇḍa redundant &amp;amp; meaningless.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eternity, mantra context</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/GA/eternity_mantra-context/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/GA/eternity_mantra-context/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The element of personal authorship in the वेदमन्त्र-s, where the words of a mantra are directly relevant and meaningful to the immediate context of the ऋषि who visualizes it from within, does not contradict the pre-existence or eternity (if you will) of the वेद.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;An example to understand: Tradition clearly tells us that विश्वामित्र &amp;ldquo;saw&amp;rdquo; a particular सूक्त when attempting to cross the confluence of 2 rivers (RV 3.33 &amp;ldquo;प्र पर्व̍तानाम् उश̱ती&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;). He addresses the rivers with a particular intention in real time.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reading vedas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/GA/reading-vedas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/GA/reading-vedas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://threadreaderapp.com/thread/1270233886564298753.html&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We can only hope that people take the advice in a friendly spirit.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The veda is not your typical “spiritual book”. The sam̐hita portions are NOT to be read like:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;bhakti-stutis/stotras&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Instructive texts such as smṛtis including gītā or upadeśas in purāṇas &amp;amp; itihāsas.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The veda is not to be treated as a text that speaks to “Hindus” generically.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The mantras in the veda are not directions on what to do or avoid.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Nor are they a straightforward discussion of “spiritual truths”.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The mantras have a deep meaning that isn’t easy to discern.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The mantra portion of the veda&lt;br&gt;&#xA;is inseparable from the ritual portion of the veda.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;One cannot ignore that when trying to understand the mantras.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RShi-IP</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/GA/RShi-IP/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/GA/RShi-IP/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://threadreaderapp.com/thread/1592021473803255809.html&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Some are upset with the phrase, “your knowledge systems” below. Is it really so offensive? The 100s of references to Āṅgirasas, Bhāradvājas, Gotamās, Kāṇvas, Bhṛgavas, Jamadagnis, Vāsiṣṭhas, Viśvāmitras/Kuśikas, Agastis, Ātreyas, Kaśyapas throughout the Veda are not in vain.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All of the aforementioned Ṛṣi groups are survived by descendants till today who are still learning this body of scripture. Anyone can read the Veda, sure. But you can’t help but notice right away (if you are not reading it mindlessly) that the Veda is the ancestral heritage of a group that still survives by Īśvara’s Will &amp;amp; grace, despite whatever hate you may throw at it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>vasiShTha-vishvAmitra-rivalry</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/GA/vasiShTha-vishvAmitra-rivalry/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/GA/vasiShTha-vishvAmitra-rivalry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/GhorAngirasa/status/1793882872555966501&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The historical narrative is riveting but ultimately means nothing if you can’t tie it back to what really matters. For those who follow Sampradāyas, the historical adventures of the Ṛṣis become aids for soteriological &amp;amp; metaphysical lessons.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If one reads the Veda as a whole together with the tradition that has been passed with it, one will understand that even Ṛṣi Vasiṣṭha went through serious tribulations &amp;amp; felt guilt for lapses on his part - lapses which are hinted in the Śruti as arising from a desire for more. Vasiṣṭha’s rāgā (desire) for Rājapaurohityam under the dominant Sudāsa was realized through his son Śakti. However, someone else had to pay a price for the competitive streak of these lofty men of great ritual &amp;amp; spiritual caliber—Viśvāmitra.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ऋषिकाः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/GA/RShikAH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/GA/RShikAH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A basic point that many don’t understand is that a general Adhikāra in Veda for a Class does not arise from a few members of said Class being Brahmavādinīs or being Ṛṣikās.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the Ṛṣikā argument is very misleading when you realize that many of the alleged Ṛṣikās are non-human. Where the Ṛṣikā is indeed human, often, the mantras attributed to her are literally quotations or form part of a dialogue that is not in praise of a deity. In contrast, in the overwhelming majority of Ṛṣi sūktas, a deliberate intent to praise the deity or address some supernatural entity can be readily inferred.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
