<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Articles on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Articles on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2003 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>bhakti - GA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/bhakti_GA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/bhakti_GA/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
The arrogant V1s &amp;amp; the true devotee of questionable heritage trope:
kavaSa ailUSa who was expelled by the RSis from a sattra on account of his maternal heritage (she was a dAsa woman; I suspect druhyu heritage). Expelled to the desert &amp;amp; suffering from thirst he sees the aponaptrīya sūkta and in the desert, the waters of the sarasvatI run to him.
The innocent, naive devotee whose silly actions still please the deity: kaNNappa nAyanmAr&amp;rsquo;s spitting water on rudra as ablution to a creative mind, can be said to be prefigured in the story of apālā who chews the soma plant with her teeth to press out the juice indra!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>taittirIya-atharva-interaction</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/taittirIya-atharva-interaction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/taittirIya-atharva-interaction/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
Note on possible taittiriya and atharvan interaction:
Taittiriya brāhmaņa 2nd aşțakā contains the so called upahoma mantras. The sūtrakāras give viniyogas for some but not all. The commentator simply mentions to take laingika viniyoga (i.e. as indicated in the mantra).
The 4th anuvāka of 4th adhyāya contains a set of mantras which is a cure for kilāsa taken to be śvetakuşțha or vitiligo. The mantra alludes to the herbs rajani, rāmā, kŕşņā and asikni.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Texts in translation</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/texts_in_translation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/texts_in_translation/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
List of Vedic Texts and Translations into English, German, and French: Version 8
Kristoffer af Edholm1 2022
In this list the texts have been arranged according to position within the four Vedas.2 Texts that are not directly connected to a Veda are listed at the end. Within each Veda, the Śruti-texts are listed first: Saṃhitās, Brāhmaṇas, Āraṇyakas, and Upaniṣads;3 then the Smṛti-texts, including the six Vedāṅgas: Kalpa (Śrauta-Sūtras, Gṛhya-Sūtras, Dharma-Sūtras, and Dharma-Śāstras or Smṛtis), 4 Śikṣā (Prātiśākhya) (phonetics), Vyākaraṇa (grammar), Nirukta (etymology), Chandas (metrics, prosody), and Jyotiṣa (astronomy).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>पौरुषेयत्वे नैयायिकाः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/pauruSheyatve_naiyAyikAH_freschi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/pauruSheyatve_naiyAyikAH_freschi/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
Nyaya authors of an earlier time (namely Gautama, Vätsyāyana and Uddyotakara) have attempted to prove the reliability of the Veda author out of partial tests, through which the general reliability of an author can be inferred. But how to test the Veda, which deals with perceptible things, such as dharma?
Gautama, Vātsyāyana and Uddyotakara inferred the validity of the Veda out of the fact that the same rṣis (said to be their draṣṭr̥ and pravaktr̥ &amp;lsquo;seers and transmitters&amp;rsquo; in NBh ad 2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>भाषा-भेदः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/bhAShA-bhedaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/bhAShA-bhedaH/</guid>
      <description>उज्ज्वलाभिप्रायः Have been deliberately avoiding reading too much of Vedic language outside of Rigveda (there too only Archaic-marked verses by Arnold mainly). Overall, I think Vedic Sanskrit is not one cross-intelligible language. And now I feel I can clearly tell the deviations and similarities of the brAhmaNa language from Rigvedic, and thus can read it without the fear of corrupting my understanding of the Rigvedic language and idiom.
Rudolph Roth, in the preface to the seven-volume Sanskrit Wörter- buch (1853-95), compiled jointly with Otto von Böhtlingk, had been clear that the poets of the Rigveda &amp;ldquo;speak a language divided from that of the Brahmaņas (which scarcely differs from the so-called classical Sanskrit) by a chasm as wide as that which separates the Latin of the Salic hymns from that of M.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>वेद-नित्यत्वे वैयाकरणाः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/veda-nityatve_vaiyAkaraNAH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/veda-nityatve_vaiyAkaraNAH/</guid>
      <description>(अत्र कोरड-सुब्रह्मण्य-पत्रम् आश्रितम्। )
Under तेन प्रोक्तम् ( पा 4-3-101) - Patanjali says -वेदs are not authored , rather they are नित्य &amp;mdash;
तेन प्रोक्तम्
प्रोक्तग्रहणम् अनर्थकम् (वा) ग्रन्थे च दर्शनात् (वा)
भाष्यम् &amp;ndash;
छन्दोऽर्थं तर्हीदं वक्तव्यम् ।
न हि छन्दांसि क्रियन्ते , नित्यानि छन्दांसि ।
कर्तुः अस्मरणात् तेषामित्यर्थः
&amp;ndash; कैयटः।
छ्न्दोऽर्थमिति चेत्तुल्यम् (वा)
भाष्यम् &amp;ndash;
छन्दोऽर्थम् इति चेत् तुल्यम् एतद् भवति ।
ग्रामे ग्रामे कालकं कालापकं च प्रोच्यते तत्र +अदर्शनात् । न च तत्र प्रत्ययो दृश्यते ।</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
