<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;1 THE SOURCES on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;1 THE SOURCES on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 THE RIGVEDA AND THE ARYANS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/01_THE_RIGVEDA_AND_THE_ARYANS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/01_THE_RIGVEDA_AND_THE_ARYANS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THE oldest and most important of the sources for Indian religion is the collection of 1,028 hymns known as the Rigveda Samhita, which has been handed down to us in the Śakala recension. Preserved in its early stages by oral tradition and long regarded as too sacred to be reduced to writing, the text affords abundant internal proof of the general accuracy with which it was preserved. Moreover, an invaluable form of control exists in the texts of the other Vedas, the Yajurveda in its different recensions, the Samaveda, and the Atharvaveda, all of which contain much of the matter of the Rigveda. The older view, that in these texts might be found traces of earlier forms of the verses of the Rigveda, has not borne close examination and comparison in detail with a very few possible exceptions the variations which are found in these texts from the Rigveda can be unhesitatingly classed as products either of an inferior tradition on the one hand or of deliberate alteration on the other. Similarly the efforts which have been made by Hillebrandt 2 to prove that, in a stage earlier than that recorded, the Rigveda was a definitely practical collection of hymns, arranged according to their connexion with the crificial ritual, must be pronounced to have failed. Whereas all the other amhitas, except the Atharvaveda, which occupies a peculiar position, are definitely in their non-Brahmana portions manuals of the chants and formulae&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 THE LATER SAṀHITĀS AND THE BRĀHMAŅAS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/02_THE_LATER_saMhitAs_AND_THE_brAhmaNas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/02_THE_LATER_saMhitAs_AND_THE_brAhmaNas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;ALREADY in the Rigveda there are signs of considerable elaboration of ritual and of the employment of a number of priests at the sacrifice, and the later Samhitās and the Brāhmaṇas reveal to us a time when the functions of the priesthood have been definitely divided up and apportioned among sets of priests. The manual acts of the sacrifice are ascribed to the Adhvaryu priest and his assistants and are accompanied by muttered formulae, in prose or verse, styled Yajus: in addition at the greatest sacrifices, such as the Soma sacrifice, singers chant Sāmans, and reciters recite Śastras, while the Brahman priest supervises the whole performance, usually in silence. On this division of functions is based the division of the later Samhitās: the Samans are preserved in the song books of the Samaveda, the Yajuses in the Yajurveda, and the Atharvaveda is held to be connected with the Brahman priest, while the Śastras were composed of verses taken from the Rigveda. From the point of view of religion the Samaveda is mainly interesting for its form: the words which were sung were almost invariably taken from the Rigveda, but they were eked out as shown in the song-books, Gānas, with all kinds of interjections, doubtless for musical purposes, which must have converted their character in the most marked degree. The sense of the words cannot possibly have been understood in the mutilated form in which the chants were sung, and the conclusion is inevitable that their religious value lay not in the substance but in the form, so that the Sāmans have been compared, not altogether unaptly, to the revival hymns beloved by the African negro in the new world. In them doubtless the religious excitement of the priest found its fullest scope for expression.1 That this form of chant was old need not be doubted: there are clear traces in the Rigveda itself in the strophic and metrical form of certain of the hymns, that they were from the first intended for something more lively than mere recitation. With this fact accords the generally close relation of the Samaveda and the Rigveda, which renders it probable that that was of the first of the later Saṁhitās to take definite form.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 THE LATER LITERATURE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/03_THE_LATER_LITERATURE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/03_THE_LATER_LITERATURE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FOR the latest stages of the Vedic religion on its practical side the authorities are the Śrauta and the Gṛhya Sūtras,1 which deal with different but complementary spheres, and which incidentally preserve for us a considerable amount of formulae, prose and verse, which by accident or other cause have not found a place in any of the Samhitās preserved to us. The necessity of some manuals for the actual practice of the great complicated rites of the sacrifice must have been felt from an early period, but we have not now extant any of these manuals. The Śrauta Sūtras which are now extant are all without excention later than the older Brāhmaṇas, and, while the ritual which they reveal is in general harmony with that supposed by the Brāhmaṇas, it would be idle to suppose that it actually represents it with perfect accuracy. This can be seen by one simple point: the Brahmanas often show that on questions of the exact mode of the performance of certain rites there were considerable difference of opinions in some cases the Brāhmaṇas reject definitely certain views, in others they allow varied views to stand as equally legitimate, but in the Sūtras in the great majority of such cases merely one view is laid down, the others having presumably come to be disapproved in the school in which the Sūtra arose. On the other hand, the Sūtras often give optional forms of procedure for which the Brāhmaṇas contain no hint, evidence of the development of practice in the schools. Moreover, there is clear proof that no Sūtra represents rigidly any one Samhita: even when, as is normal, a Sūtra follows generally some Samhitā it is quite ready to accept portions of its material from another.2 The Sutras, therefore, while often giving valuable confirmation and explanation of the Brahmaṇas, cannot be regarded as contemporary evidence of the practices of the Brāhmaṇas, and this conclusion based entirely on the ritual is confirmed by many lines of evidence. In addition to dealing with many rites which seem clearly elaborations and modifications of older rites, the Sutras in language are markedly more modern than the Brahmaṇas, approximating closely to the classical speech, from which they differ in the main in the use of forms of incorrect grammatical formation.3 From this fact a conclusion may fairly be drawn with regard to their chronology: it&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
