<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;25 THE CULT OF THE DEAD on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/4_THE_SPIRITS_OF_THE_DEAD/25_THE_CULT_OF_THE_DEAD/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;25 THE CULT OF THE DEAD on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/4_THE_SPIRITS_OF_THE_DEAD/25_THE_CULT_OF_THE_DEAD/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 The Living and the Dead</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/4_THE_SPIRITS_OF_THE_DEAD/25_THE_CULT_OF_THE_DEAD/1_The_Living_and_the_Dead/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/4_THE_SPIRITS_OF_THE_DEAD/25_THE_CULT_OF_THE_DEAD/1_The_Living_and_the_Dead/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THE attitude of the Vedic Indian to his dead is one of distinctive and pronounced individuality. The constant anxiety lest from the dead should come injury to the living is perfectly obvious, but it must be admitted that it does not show any trace of being due to the direct fear of the spirit of the dead: it is the fear of death which marks the attitude of the Indian: the dead has not a hostile nature, but the thing which has affected him is to be feared. It is, therefore, intelligible that the Indian in the Vedic period looks, despite his dread of death, with affection and esteem upon his ancestors, and that much of his existence should be concerned with the means of securing them nourishment. That food is required especially on certain occasions, not less often than once a month and occasionally at other times in a certain portion of the rainy season the dead are conceived as leaving the abode of heaven and coming to the houses of their kin to seek for food. On the other hand if the men care for their Fathers, it is but natural that these Fathers should be deemed to be anxious to aid and assist them, and the companionship of the blessed dead with the gods encourages the belief that they have power to aid, even as the gods have power. The Fathers generally are often referred to in the Rigveda and the later literature as invoked to confer boons, similar to those which the gods convey, and, though they are distinctly differentiated by a multitude of things, and especially by cult, from the powers of heaven, nevertheless, for the purpose of being a very present help in tribulation, they appear to be ranked as not unworthy of invocation with, or even without, the gods. Like the gods, men pray to them for success, for the defeat of enemies, for the gift of rain, for the bestowal of eloquence, or for abundance of food. Even in battle the Fathers are invoked as warriors.&amp;quot; But the energy of the Fathers has one special end, the production of offspring, in which they have the special interest that the rites for the dead can only be kept up by the device of continuing the family. At the offering for the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2 The Offerings to the Dead in the Domestic Ritual</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/4_THE_SPIRITS_OF_THE_DEAD/25_THE_CULT_OF_THE_DEAD/2_The_Offerings_to_the_Dead_in_the_Domestic_Ritual/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/4_THE_SPIRITS_OF_THE_DEAD/25_THE_CULT_OF_THE_DEAD/2_The_Offerings_to_the_Dead_in_the_Domestic_Ritual/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Beside the regular offerings which are prescribed for the Fathers, there are others which are to be performed on special occasions, such as the birth of a son, a marriage, and the giving of the name to the child. In this case the offering or &amp;lsquo;Śrāddha&amp;rsquo;, which bears its name of that which is connected with Śraddha, faith&amp;rsquo;, from the fact that the presents to the Brahmans which accompany the offerings to the dead reveal the faith of the offerer in the Brahmans, is to be performed on the waxing half of the month, and before midday the number of Brahmans chosen is even, not as usual odd: the performances are from left to right, not vice versa; barley replaces sesame; the milk meal lumps are mixed with sour milk and roasted grains, and the Fathers are addressed as Nandimukha, &amp;lsquo;joyful in countenance&amp;rsquo;, 5 in place of with tearful countenance&amp;rsquo;, which is elsewhere not rarely used. These rank as the Vṛddhi Śrāddhas, and similar to them are Purta Śraddhas, at the dedication of wells, pools, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 The Offerings to the Dead in the Grauta Ritual</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/4_THE_SPIRITS_OF_THE_DEAD/25_THE_CULT_OF_THE_DEAD/3_The_Offerings_to_the_Dead_in_the_Grauta_Ritual/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/4_THE_SPIRITS_OF_THE_DEAD/25_THE_CULT_OF_THE_DEAD/3_The_Offerings_to_the_Dead_in_the_Grauta_Ritual/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the Śrauta ritual a leading place in the cult of the dead is taken by the Pinḍapitṛyajña, which should be offered after midday of the day of new moon. The sacrifice must take place in the southern fire, which is that appropriate to the Fathers, and the regular procedure of such offerings is followed: the sacred cord is to be worn over the right shoulder, not the left; all movements are from right to left, and recitations and acts take place once, not thrice; while in the normal offering movements are from south and west to north and east, in this offering they are in the reverse order, in so far that they must&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
