<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Articles on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Articles on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Recitational permutations</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/recitational-permutations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/recitational-permutations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;TODO: footnote and other formatting&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;RECITATIONAL PERMUTATIONS OF&#xA;THE ŚAUNAKĪYA ATHARVAVEDA&#xA;Critically edited with an Introduction&#xA;by&#xA;Madhav M. Deshpande&#xA;2001&#xA;Dedicated&#xA;with&#xA;Respect and Affection to my&#xA;Veda-Vidyā-Guru&#xA;Late Professor R.N. Dandekar&#xA;Preface&#xA;While I was working on my edition of the Śaunakīyā Caturādhyāyikā, later published in 1997 as HOS, vol. 52, I felt the accute need to consult Atharvavedic reciters on the formation of Kramapāṭha, which is elaborately described in the rules of the Śaunakīyā Caturādhyāyikā. At first glance, one may feel that such recitational varieties are fairly mechanical, and hence there would be no difference between the rules of the Śaunakīyā Caturādhyāyikā and the actually recited Kramapāṭha. However, there is sufficient evidence available to let us recognize that there were differences of opinion on all such matters going back to ancient times, and hence I felt it necessary to get hold of an actual performance of the Kramapāṭha. Vedic reciters who could recite the Kramapāṭha were known to S.P. Pandit when he published his magnificent edition of the Atharvaveda Saṃhitā in 1895-98. However, no such living reciters are to be found today. I was fortunate to find three manuscripts at the Bhandarkar Oriental Research Institute and two at the Vaidika Samshodhana Mandala in Pune that contained the Jaṭāpāṭha for the 15th and the 17th Kāṇḍa and the Kramapāṭha for the 20th Kāṇḍa. Here I wish to thank Professor M.G. Dhadphale and Professor A.M. Ghatage of the BORI and Dr. Bhagyalata Pataskar of the VSM to have allowed me to photocopy these manuscripts and use them for the present edition. During my several visits to Pune, especially in 1995 and 1999, I worked on these manuscripts at the BORI. I particularly want to thank the library staff at the BORI, who facilitated my work at the Institute. This book represents the first critical edition of such texts, and I hope that it will allow us to move beyond the merely schematic understanding of these recitational permutations, and place them within their own evolving history. I would like to dedicate this book to my Veda-Vidyā-Guru, Late Professor R.N. Dandekar, who introduced me to the mysteries of the Śaunakīya Atharvaveda when I was his student at the University of Pune. He was not only my teacher, he taught Shakespeare to my father when he was a student at the New English School in Pune. This volume is a result of the love for Vedic studies he inspired in me. I was hoping to personally present a copy of this volume to him. However, he passed away on December 11, 2001 at the age of 93. May his Ātman rest in peace!&#xA;December 12, 2001 Madhav M. Deshpande, Ann Arbor&#xA;Contents&#xA;Preface&#xA;Introduction i-lxv&#xA;Jaṭāpāṭha for the 15th Kāṇḍa of the ŚAV 1-101&#xA;Jaṭāpāṭha for the 17th Kāṇḍa of the ŚAV 102-127&#xA;Kramapāṭha for the 20th Kāṇḍa of the ŚAV 128-456&#xA;Two Fragments of AV Jaṭāpāṭha 457-460&#xA;INTRODUCTION&#xA;Introduction&#xA;From the very beginning of the Vedic period (1500 - 500 BC), language used in religious texts appeared to possess a mysterious aura. Common folks (manuṣyāḥ) were said to have access only to a quarter of the true&#xA;extent of this divine language, while only the wise and thoughtful priests&#xA;(brāhmaṇā́ yé manīṣíṇaḥ) were said to have access to its entire mystery&#xA;(RV.1.164.45). It was the responsibility of these wise Brahmans to&#xA;comprehend the mystery of language and explain it in appropriate ways to&#xA;those who had no access to it. The linguistic sciences in ancient India originated in this religious obligation felt by the Brahman priests. There were also&#xA;a number of practical considerations. Vedic literature was produced in&#xA;different geographical areas and was orally transmitted both from one generation to the next, as well as from one region to another. There were also the&#xA;shifting mother tongues of the transmitters and interpreters. The priests believed that a ritual is truly perfect in form (rūpasamr̥ddha) if the recited&#xA;sacred texts matched the action being carried out. Thus one had to know&#xA;what these texts meant. On account of the factors described earlier, neither&#xA;the understanding nor a perfect pronunciation of the sacred texts could be&#xA;taken for granted as the inherited oral texts became more and more archaic.&#xA;This anxiety gave rise to the early efforts by the priestly scholars to find ways&#xA;to overcome these difficulties.&#xA;Different Recitational Versions of Vedic Texts1&#xA;The orally preserved Vedic texts underwent a great deal of consolidation during the Brāhmaṇa period, and scholars like Māṇḍūkeya and Śākalya&#xA;prepared the Saṃhitās and their Padapāṭhas. The Aitareya-Āraṇyaka explicitly refers to the activity of the redactors, but it is not clear how far before the&#xA;Aitareya Āraṇyaka the activity of dividing the Saṃhitā into Padas ‘words’&#xA;and Pādas ‘metrical feet’ actually began. The words pada, pāda and the&#xA;related stems pad- and pād- appear in Vedic texts. During the R̥gvedic&#xA;1 I would like to thank Professor George Cardona, Professor Michael Witzel and Dr. Arlo&#xA;Griffiths for their constructive suggestions. I have adopted many of their suggestions in the&#xA;following narrative, though I alone remain responsible for my final presentation in this&#xA;volume. Many topics that are briefly introduced and discussed in this Introduction are&#xA;worthy of longer treatment. I hope to return to these topics in the future.&#xA;ii RECITATIONAL PERMUTATIONS&#xA;period, the word pada was occasionally used to refer to ‘word.’ Louis Renou&#xA;(1958: 21-22) points to a few passages in the RV where, according to him,&#xA;the word pada does not mean a step or place, but is more like an equivalent&#xA;of the term nāman ‘name,’ or perhaps ‘word’ in a non-technical sense [RV&#xA;7.87.4: tríḥ saptá nā́mā́ghnyā bibharti; RV 1.72.6: tríḥ saptá yád gúhyāni&#xA;tvé ít padā́vidan níhitā yajñíyāsaḥ; and RV 10.53.10: padā́ gúhyāni kartana&#xA;yéna devā́so amr̥tatvám ānaśúḥ]. Whether such early usages of pada&#xA;metaphorically suggest the meaning ‘word’ or whether one can actually assert&#xA;that they refer to ‘word’ may be debatable2, and yet it seems clear to me that&#xA;a sense of ‘word’ for the term pada is beginning to emerge. According Roth&#xA;and Böhtlingk (PW), the word pada in the Śatapatha-Brāhmaṇa (10.2.2.13:&#xA;r̥gbhir yajurbhiḥ padair akṣaraiḥ) refers to ‘word,’ where it occurs in the&#xA;context of reciting a hundred R̥ks, Yajus, Padas, or Akṣaras. A clearer&#xA;instance is perhaps found in the Śatapatha-Brāhmaṇa (11.3.8.9, devapadam)&#xA;where the word pada seems to have been used in the sense of a ‘word.’ The&#xA;Aitareya-Brāhmaṇa (6.33, Ānandāśrama edn., Vol. II, p. 788), referring to a&#xA;passage called Aitaśa-Pralāpa says that this passage is to be recited&#xA;padāvagraham. Sāyaṇa renders this archaic gerund by pade pade avagr̥hya&#xA;‘separating each pada’ or pausing after each pada. If we are to believe&#xA;Sāyaṇa (ibid., p. 785), the word pada here refers to a metrical foot.3 While&#xA;the term avagraha is used in later grammatical treatises to refer to a pause&#xA;between the constituents of a word, such as the members of a compound, and&#xA;is not used to refer to the pause between the separated metrical feet, this&#xA;passage makes it likely that the procedure of breaking down a continuous text&#xA;into its constituent units, and reciting these units with separating pauses had&#xA;begun before the formation of the Padapāṭhas or ‘word-by-word’ versions of&#xA;the Vedic Saṃhitās. Thus, one can conceive of a stage of development when&#xA;the textual wholes were broken down into their constituent units such as&#xA;metrical feet, but that these units were not yet further analysed into their own&#xA;constituents. This next stage is found in the available Padapāṭhas for the&#xA;various Vedic Saṃhitās. It seems likely that the terms avagraha and pada&#xA;were inherited by the later tradition, which used them in a somewhat different&#xA;meaning of ‘a short pause between the constituents of a word’ (avagraha)&#xA;and a word (pada). The words pad- and pād- referring to a foot, including a&#xA;2 Professor Cardona has drawn my attention to the difference of opinion between Geldner&#xA;and Renou on this question. While Geldner thinks of ‘word’ as a metaphorical meaning of&#xA;pada, Renou is more assertive in claiming that the term refers to ‘word’ in several RV&#xA;passages. For a recent exhaustive treatment of pada in Vedic, see: G. Thompson (1995).&#xA;3 Falk (2001:196): “We know from several Gr̥hyasūtras that the Sāvitrī at least was taught&#xA;first quarter by quarter, then in half-stanzas and finally in total, e.g. Āpastambagr̥hyasūtra&#xA;4.11, 8-10.”&#xA;OF THE ŚAUNAKĪYA ATHARVAVEDA iii&#xA;metrical foot, also appear in early Vedic texts (eg. RV 1.114.1c, 1.164.24,&#xA;and 8.27.12cd) and are related to the term pāda for the foot, appearing&#xA;already in RV 10.90.3cd. Gradually a stable terminological distinction&#xA;emerges between pada ‘word’ versus pāda ‘metrical foot.’ Such a&#xA;distinction, which is maintained in all the later technical literature including&#xA;the Nirukta and the Prātiśākhyas, is already evident in the ŚāṅkhāyanaBrāhmaṇa (26.5). This passage is particularly significant in our&#xA;understanding of how the need for various kinds of segmentation may have&#xA;arisen and how it may have formed a part of the recitational and ritual&#xA;practice:&#xA;daivodāsiḥ pratardano naimiṣīyāṇāṃ satram upagamyopāsyadya vicikitsāṃ papraccha yady atikrāntam ulbaṇaṃ&#xA;sadasyo bodhayetartvijāṃ vānyatamo budhyeta kathaṃ vo&#xA;’nulbaṇaṃ syād iti ta u ha tūṣṇīm āsus teṣām alīkayur&#xA;vācaspatyo brahmā sa hovāca nāham etad veda hanta&#xA;pūrveṣām ācāryaṃ sthaviraṃ jātūkarṇyaṃ pr̥cchānīti taṃ ha&#xA;papraccha yady atikrāntam ulbaṇaṃ kartā vā svayaṃ&#xA;budhyetānyo vā bodhayeta kathaṃ tad ulbaṇam anulbaṇaṃ&#xA;bhavet punarvacanena vā mantrasya homena veti punar vācyo&#xA;mantra iti ha smāha jātūkarṇyas tam alīkayuḥ punaḥ&#xA;papraccha śastraṃ vā anuvacanaṃ vā nigadaṃ vā yājyāṃ vā&#xA;yad vānyat sarvaṃ tat punar brūyād iti yāvanmātram&#xA;ulbaṇaṃ tāvad brūyād r̥caṃ vārdharcaṃ vā pādaṃ vā padaṃ&#xA;vā varṇaṃ veti ha smāha jātūkarṇyaḥ |&#xA;“Daivodāsi Pratardana having gone to a sacrificial season of&#xA;the Naimiṣīyas and having glided up asked a question on this&#xA;point of doubt, ‘If the priest in the Sadas should call attention&#xA;to a flaw passed over or any one of the priests should note it,&#xA;how would you remove the flaw?’ They were silent; Alīkayu&#xA;Vācaspatya was their Brahman priest; he said ‘I know that not;&#xA;but will ask Jātūkarṇya, the aged teacher of those formerly.’&#xA;Him he asked, ‘If the performer himself should note a flaw&#xA;passed over or another should call attention to it, how is that&#xA;flaw to be made flawless? By repetition of the Mantra or by&#xA;an oblation?’ ‘The Mantra should be recited again,’ Jātū-&#xA;karṇya said. Him Alīkayu again asked, ‘Should one recite in&#xA;full the Śastra or recitation or Nigada or offering verse or&#xA;iv RECITATIONAL PERMUTATIONS&#xA;whatever else it be?’ ‘So much as is erroneous only need be&#xA;repeated, a verse (r̥cam), or half verse (ardharcam), or quarter&#xA;verse (pādam), or word (p a d a m), or letter (v a r ṇ a m),’&#xA;Jātūkarṇya replied.” (A.B. Keith, 1920: 498).&#xA;This is an extremely important passage which provides a valid pretheoretical practical rationale for recognizing the constituents of speech units.&#xA;Not only do we find here a clear distinction between a pāda ‘metrical foot’&#xA;and pada ‘word,’ we also find one of the early uses of the term varṇa to refer&#xA;to ‘sound,’ in contrast with the older term akṣara ‘syllable.’ Thus, there is&#xA;clear conceptual and terminological range from metrical feet to words, and&#xA;from syllables to individual sounds. Perhaps, the ritual necessity of making&#xA;minimum corrections in the recited Mantras may have led to the early efforts&#xA;in recognizing the constituents in the metrical or non-metrical Vedic compositions. Such efforts on large scale may have eventually led to the formation&#xA;of what we know as the Padapāṭhas or ‘word-by-word’ versions of the Vedic&#xA;texts. Such texts have already come into existence by the time of the&#xA;Āraṇyakas, where one finds some explicit discussion about their formation.&#xA;Another interesting feature of the above passage is the order in which&#xA;the successively smaller segmentations are listed: a verse (r̥cam), half verse&#xA;(ardharcam), quarter verse (pādam), word (padam), letter (varṇam). This&#xA;would seem to imply the sequence of segmentation into successively smaller&#xA;units, as well as a recognition that first there were the unsegmented texts and&#xA;then came the various segmentations. Such an implication, if we can accept&#xA;it, would lead us to some very ancient ideas concerning the relationship&#xA;between what came to be later called the Saṃhitās and their Padapāṭhas.&#xA;The debate regarding the relationship between the Saṃhitās and their&#xA;Padapāṭhas as seen in the various texts is indeed confusing at first sight. The&#xA;oldest complex debate regarding these two sets of texts is found in the Aitareya-Āraṇyaka. In this debate, we find the use of two sets of terms. The&#xA;first set of terms includes nirbhuja and pratr̥ṇṇa.4 The second set is represented primarily by the term saṃhitā. Of these two sets of terms, the first set&#xA;is not only seen here for the first time, it is, strangely enough, a set of terms&#xA;which appear to be on their way out, and which are explained not intrinsically, but in terms of the emerging term, i.e. saṃhitā. It is this term, saṃhitā,&#xA;and its later comrade, pada, which appear to be the current paradigm for the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
