<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;14 Sūtra: Vedic Sciences on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/14_sUtra_Vedic_Sciences/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;14 Sūtra: Vedic Sciences on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/14_sUtra_Vedic_Sciences/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 The Concept of Science and its Ancient History</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/14_sUtra_Vedic_Sciences/01_The_Concept_of_Science_and_its_Ancient_History/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/14_sUtra_Vedic_Sciences/01_The_Concept_of_Science_and_its_Ancient_History/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Science is universal, but the concept of science varies in different cultures. English &lt;em&gt;science&lt;/em&gt; is different from French &lt;em&gt;science&lt;/em&gt;, German &lt;em&gt;Wissenschaft,&lt;/em&gt; Japanese &lt;em&gt;gaku,&lt;/em&gt; Russian &lt;em&gt;nauka&lt;/em&gt;, etc. English &lt;em&gt;science&lt;/em&gt; refers to what it regards as the ‘exact’ sciences, viz., mathematics, physics and other so-called ‘natural sciences’. The French and the other quoted terms include human, life, social and other sciences. They are all exact in that they strive for explicitness and avoid contradictions. The definition I adopt is the widest I could find within these constraints: science is the search for systematic, exact and highly confirmed knowledge of the universe which includes, of course, ourselves. Thus defined, science is similar to &lt;em&gt;veda&lt;/em&gt;. However, it recognizes more clearly and explicitly the duality of facts and logic.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 The Traditional List and the Concept of Sūtra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/14_sUtra_Vedic_Sciences/02_The_Traditional_List_and_the_Concept_of_sUtra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/14_sUtra_Vedic_Sciences/02_The_Traditional_List_and_the_Concept_of_sUtra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Vedic sciences are not objects that moderns are at liberty to make up. Much is known about them and what we know is in accordance with a traditional classification of sciences that belong to the late Vedic period. This was anticipated by a more adventurous or generous list in the early Chāndogya Upaniṣad (7.1.1–4). It uses the term &lt;em&gt;vidyā&lt;/em&gt; which is closely related to &lt;em&gt;veda&lt;/em&gt;, both meaning ‘knowledge’. The Chāndogya passage starts with sage Nārada asking Sanatkumāra, ‘Eternal Youth,’ to teach him what he knows. Sanatkumāra returns the question: ‘Tell me first what you know. Then I’ll tell you what more there is to know.’ Nārada gives a long reply in which he refers to the four Vedas, the corpus of histories and ancient tales, ancestral rites, mathematics, soothsaying, the art of locating treasures, and the sciences of ritual, spirits, government, heavenly bodies and serpent beings. ‘All that, sir, I have studied.’ Eternal Youth responds wisely: ‘All that is nothing but names.’&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 The Science of Ritual</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/14_sUtra_Vedic_Sciences/03_The_Science_of_Ritual/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/14_sUtra_Vedic_Sciences/03_The_Science_of_Ritual/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Following the order of the ‘limbs of the Veda,’ we begin with the science of ritual. It deals with many more scientific concepts than the notion of ritual evokes in a modern mind. There is nothing in modern science that corresponds to such a discipline unless it is directly inspired by it, like Hubert and Mauss. It is a science because it provides systematic and highly confirmed knowledge of ritual structures such as self-embedding and other forms of recursiveness mentioned or alluded to in Chapters 11 and 12. Other civilizations have been interested in the study of ritual—the Confucian and Taoist in China and the Orthodox and Catholic during the European middle ages—but it is unlikely that they attained the high level of technical and theoretical sophistication that we find in the Śrauta Sūtras because they lacked the close interaction between ritual and grammar that characterizes Vedic science. Some technical concepts of the Vedic science of ritual anticipate linguistics, modern logic and computer science.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Geometry</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/14_sUtra_Vedic_Sciences/04_Geometry/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/14_sUtra_Vedic_Sciences/04_Geometry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Vedic geometry is attached to ritual because it is concerned with the measurement and construction of ritual enclosures (such as the ritual arena of Figure 15) and of altars (Figures 21–22). Our knowledge is based to a small extent upon the living tradition, but more complete information survives in the Śulba Sūtras. The most important are Baudhāyana, Āpastamba and Mānava, which are attached to Śrauta Sūtras of the Black Yajurveda, and Kātyāyana which is attached to the White. The term &lt;em&gt;śulba&lt;/em&gt; means rope. Ropes and pegs are used for measurements, to mark a straight line or circle and construct a square, rectangle, trapezium or straight line parallel or orthogonal to another.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Numbers and Infinity</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/14_sUtra_Vedic_Sciences/05_Numbers_and_Infinity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/14_sUtra_Vedic_Sciences/05_Numbers_and_Infinity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We have so far looked at ‘Vedic geometry’, but is there no other mathematics in the Vedas? Though the term is used in several senses, there certainly is no trace of algebra. What about those very large numbers that we have come across (in Chapter 7) and what about the concept of infinity which is almost omnipresent in some form or other? I offer two observations, one speculative which takes us to a distant past, another factual which takes us to more recent times.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 ‘Vedic Mathematics’</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/14_sUtra_Vedic_Sciences/06_Vedic_Mathematics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/14_sUtra_Vedic_Sciences/06_Vedic_Mathematics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A few paragraphs should be added about the book &lt;em&gt;Vedic Mathematics&lt;/em&gt; by Bharati Krishna Tirtha Maharaja (1884–1960), former Śaṇkarācārya of the Govardhana Maṭha at Puri and published long after his death. (A Śaṇkarācārya is pontiff of one of the four or five traditional schools of the Advaita Vedānta, founded by the original Śaṇkara according to tradition.) A Hindi edition of &lt;em&gt;Vedic Mathematics&lt;/em&gt;, called &lt;em&gt;Vaidika Gaṇitā,&lt;/em&gt; and a revised English edition, published in Delhi in 1992, were reprinted many times in the following years. There are also active web-sites and a &lt;em&gt;Vedic Mathematics Newsletter&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 The Prātiśākhyas and the Padapāṭha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/14_sUtra_Vedic_Sciences/07_The_prAtishAkhyas_and_the_padapATha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/14_sUtra_Vedic_Sciences/07_The_prAtishAkhyas_and_the_padapATha/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The classification of sciences as ‘limbs of the Veda’ with which we began includes four sciences of language. I shall try to simplify, reconstruct their salient features differently and treat them in three sections. The first examines the Prātiśākhyas and the Padapāṭha with which we are already familiar from Chapter 4.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Prātiśākhyas are attached to each of the Vedic schools (&lt;em&gt;śākhā&lt;/em&gt;) as their name indicates. It will be helpful, therefore, to caste another glance at Table 1 on &lt;em&gt;Four: The Four Vedas&lt;/em&gt;. The most important is the Rik-Prātiśākhya. The Yajurveda, has one for the Taittirīya and another for the White Yajurveda. The Atharvaveda has two and the Sāmaveda possesses a number of compositions that deal with the many features of its ritual chants. Scholars have long discussed whether the early Prātiśākhyas pre-date the famous grammarian Pāṇini and if so, which of them. The fact is that their linguistic content is basically pre-Pāṇinian though the present form in which we know them has been influenced by Pāṇini’s grammar which in due course eclipsed them all because it went beyond the śākhās and described the spoken language of his time and place. This remark is relevant to the development of linguistic systems and to the chronological sequence of scientists and their works. There were Bloomfieldians left, chronologically speaking, after Chomsky’s first revolution, which does not contradict the fact that Chomskian linguistics was, among other things, a reaction against Bloomfield and, therefore, best understood and described as a new chapter in the history of linguistics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 The Sound Pattern of Language</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/14_sUtra_Vedic_Sciences/08_The_Sound_Pattern_of_Language/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/14_sUtra_Vedic_Sciences/08_The_Sound_Pattern_of_Language/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The second Vedic science of language as I have reconstructed it led to a major empirical discovery with profound implications for the methodology of linguistics. It was made by Vedic reciters who were engaged in composing Prātiśākhyas and constructing Padapāṭhas or were already familiar with them; and arrived at in stages during roughly the same period. Because the reciters did not think of changes in the Vedic language—what we interpret as such, for example, in the distinction between early, middle and late Vedic (Chapter 4)—they would interpret them as characteristics of different regions (which was often the case). They emphasized, therefore, what we would call synchronic linguistics, not diachronic philology. All the time they used purely empirical methods: they did not prescribe but describe. They went further than most modern linguists. They did not imagine that language starts from the larynx. They knew that its deeper source lies in the intention, that is, the mind or heart of the speaker. In so doing, they anticipated by more than two millennia the spirit of synchronic linguistics, initiated in Europe by de Saussure; and of psycholinguistics which began to develop in the twentieth century.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 Notations and Artificial Languages</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/14_sUtra_Vedic_Sciences/09_Notations_and_Artificial_Languages/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/14_sUtra_Vedic_Sciences/09_Notations_and_Artificial_Languages/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The third Vedic science of language as I have reconstructed it may be looked upon as a methodology but its significance is wider. The Prātiśākhyas introduced, along with rules and metarules, the beginnings of the metalinguistic study of language. To see what that means we should start with some simple facts about rules. Many rules of language are of the form ‘A &amp;gt; B’. This may be read as ‘A becomes B’ or ‘B is substituted for A.’ ‘A &amp;gt; B’ is a modern artificial notation. The Prātiśākhyas did not use variables such as ‘A’ and ‘B’ or expressions such as ‘+’ and ‘&amp;gt;’, but other artificial notations. Their rules made metalinguistic use of the case endings of the object language, that is, Vedic. Thus two expressions, distinguished in English as ‘becoming’ and ‘substitution,’ correspond to a single artificial expression:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 Astronomy and Astrology</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/14_sUtra_Vedic_Sciences/10_Astronomy_and_Astrology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/4_WHAT_CAN_WE_LEARN_FROM_THE_VEDAS/14_sUtra_Vedic_Sciences/10_Astronomy_and_Astrology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The reader need not raise eyebrows about the combination of astrology with astronomy during the Vedic period. It is and has been common all over the world for a long time. The combination occurs in pre-modern and even in early-modern science. Kepler, Tycho Brahe and Newton were all interested in astrology though Newton’s real passion was alchemy. I shall be brief on the entire subject and rely on Michio Yano and the late David Pingree who died on 11 November 2005, when I was struggling with a first version of the present section.1&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
