<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;07 Yajurveda on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/07_Yajurveda/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;07 Yajurveda on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/07_Yajurveda/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 The Role of the Yajurveda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/07_Yajurveda/01_The_Role_of_the_Yajurveda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/07_Yajurveda/01_The_Role_of_the_Yajurveda/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Yajurveda is not simply the next Veda. Sāyaṇa, a scholar with a deep and wide-ranging knowledge of the Vedas, described the Rig- and Sāmavedas as the pictures (&lt;em&gt;citra&lt;/em&gt;) and the Yajurveda as the wall (&lt;em&gt;bhitti&lt;/em&gt;). If he is right, the reader has been reading about beautiful things—Rigveda poetry and Sāmaveda chants—and should now get ready for the study of what supports and holds them together. These supporting structures must refer to ritual, the domain of the Yajurveda, which is concerned with complex activities. How to understand these structures? Must we wade through masses of ritual descriptions?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 The Ritual Arena</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/07_Yajurveda/02_The_Ritual_Arena/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/07_Yajurveda/02_The_Ritual_Arena/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is more to it as we shall see in Chapter 13, but I am afraid we must return from Sāyaṇa to the Yajurveda and the Yajurvedins. The Adhvaryu priest of the Yajurveda was a typical product of Kuru &lt;em&gt;orthopraxy&lt;/em&gt;, that is: he was concerned with ‘right action’ rather than ‘right opinion’ or ‘right belief’, the meanings of the term &lt;em&gt;orthodoxy&lt;/em&gt;. His home was the ritual arena, especially as it is constructed for the performance of Soma ceremonies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Yajurveda Mantras and Brāhmaṇas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/07_Yajurveda/03_Yajurveda_Mantras_and_brAhmaNas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/07_Yajurveda/03_Yajurveda_Mantras_and_brAhmaNas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Adhvaryu and his three assistants do not only recite Mantras and Brāhmaṇas of their Yajurvedic school. They mutter brief formulas referred to as &lt;em&gt;yaju&lt;/em&gt;s. These accompany ritual acts and the Yajurveda is named after them. Many are muttered in a low voice: &lt;em&gt;upāṃśu&lt;/em&gt;, ‘articulated (within the mouth) but inaudible’. Uttering them in a low voice strengthens them so that they will strengthen the mutterer as the Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa puts it in its sacerdotal fashion. The meaning of the word is more interesting: it comes from &lt;em&gt;aṃśu,&lt;/em&gt; the stalk of the Soma plant and &lt;em&gt;upa&lt;/em&gt; which means ‘close’ (as in &lt;em&gt;upa-niṣad&lt;/em&gt;, ‘sitting close’). The Soma drink is obtained from pressing these stalks which are, therefore, the essential part of the plant. In Soma rituals, prior to the main pressing, there is an &lt;em&gt;upāṃśu-graha&lt;/em&gt; or small pressing before sunrise. It takes place without recitation; the Adhvaryu keeps silent (‘restrains his voice’) as on many other occasions. But the Śrauta Sūtras display variations: breath may be taken or not, different deities are involved, etc. It is a somewhat mystifying and flexible word: it may occur as a noun, adjective or adverb.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
