<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Indology exercises on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Indology exercises on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>ANCIENT INDIAN POLITY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/ANCIENT_INDIAN_POLITY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/ANCIENT_INDIAN_POLITY/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A proper integration of the interests of the individual and the society may be said to constitutc the central problem of all social philosophy So far as the ancient Indian thinkers were concerned, they had developed in this field two distinct disciplines, namely Dharmaśāstra and Arthaśāstra. As a matter of fact, the ancient Indian concept of Dharma is very comprehensive and touches all aspects of man&amp;rsquo;s relation with the society. One such aspect is political in character and often manifests itself in the form of the relation between the subject and the state. In view of the fact that the state in ancient India was mostly monarchical, this aspect of Dharma was known as Rajadharma ( duties of kings ). Naturally enough, the Rājadharma which, by and large, corres ponded with political theory and practice, formed but one of the many topics dealt with in the larger scheme of Dharmaśāstra. Dharmaśāstra was normally divided into three main sections, namely, ācāra or rules of conduct, vj&amp;rsquo;avahāra or civil and criminal law, and prayascitta or expiation and punishment, and the Rājadharma was included in the section embodying the rules of conduct.&#xA;In course of time, however, polity came to be regarded as being important enough to be recognised as an independent branch of knowledge, under the same of Arthaśāstra. As against Dharmaśāstra, Arthaśāstra may be said to have given quite a new orientation to political theory and practice. It may be presumed that this new orientation was, at least to a certain extent, the result of the movement of popular Hinduism which, incidentally, arose, on the one hand, to counteract the essentially&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>dAsharAjJNa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/dAsharAjJNa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/dAsharAjJNa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;TIC DĀśARAJÑA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(Some time ago a friend and colleague wrote to me asking me a few general questions regarding the Dāśarājña in reply, I sent him a brief note embodying in broad outline my views on the subject. In the forward n, letter ( dated August 4 1972), I wrote - There are many theories about the Dāśarājña. Besides the historical interpretation, naturalist, astronomical and symbolical interpretations of the event have also been attempted. I have set forth my own view in the enclosed note. I have derived my guidance mainly from the the Rgveda . &amp;ndash;RND)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>East and west</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/East_and_west/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/East_and_west/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THE EAST AND THE WEST 1&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Characteristics of Eastern Culture&#xA;It would be convenient if I begap by defining, to a certain extent, the implications of the terms, “Eastern,&amp;quot; &amp;quot; Culture,&amp;quot; and “Characteristics,&amp;quot; so far as the present paper was concerned. It has now become almost trite to say that the categorisation of thought and culture as Eastern&amp;rsquo; and Western&amp;rsquo; is not at all scientific. There are, as we all know, great and fundamental differences between the various ideologies that have originated apd grown in the geographical East. The cultural matrix of China, Japan, Indonesia, India, and Asiatic Russia can by no means be regarded as a single entity which may be analysed and studied as such. Similarly the differences between the Latin and the Germanic cultures as also between the cultures of the European continent on the one hand and those of the Americas on the other cappot be certainly overlooked. Further it has been osten pointed out that there is hardly anything in the so-called Oriental thought which cannot be found in the wide range of Occidental thought, and, conversely, there is nothing in the traditional Western thought which has not found expression in the Orient. Notwithstanding all this, in view of the fact that the ways of life and thought of peoples are invariably conditioned by their anthropo-geographical situations and the course of their history, and mainly as a convenient point of departure for a comparative study of their thought and culture, it may not be ahogether unwarranted to speak in terms of the Eastern tradition and the Western tradition. It would, however, be advisable to remind ourselves, jo this connection, of what has been so very well said, namely, that we might divide in order to distinguish if we did not distinguish in order to divide.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;This served as a working paper for a UNESCO symposium beld under the auspices of the Ninth laternational Congress for the History of Religions, at Tokyo, Japan, in August September 1958,&#xA;314&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;Even a casual student of the history of Indian culture will be struck by what TOYNBER calls the religious penchant of that culture. With a view to bringing this penchant into relief, one may as well contrast it with the mechanical and technological penchant of the modern Western civilisation or the aesthetic penchant of the Hellenic civilisation. This religious penchant or the spiritual attitude of the Indian finds a very striking expression in the motivation of Indian philosophy. Indian philosophy, as has been often rightly emphasised, springs from the unrest of the soul rather than from any metaphysical curiosity. In the West, philosophy is a kind of scholastic Occupation or academic game; it is often isolated from life and consists of purely theoretical speculations. As against this, the Indians have sought to give a practical orientation to their philosophical thought. They aim at spiritually realising what is intellectually known. After the three stages in one&amp;rsquo;s progress on the path of philosophy, namely, śrayana (knowledge derived through study), manana (cogita tion), and nididhyāsa (constant and repeated meditation), säksātkāra (direct realisation) is invariably mentioned as the final goal. Koowledge is barren unless it is transformed into vision ( darśana) or experience. This pragmatic view of philo sopby has resulted in the so-called systems of Indian philosophy subordinatiog their theoretical differences to the ultimate spiritual&#xA;s goal. Philosophy is after all a means to not an end in itself.&#xA;And this leads us to another significant attitude of the Indians, pamely, tolerance. Philosophy and religion not being regarded as ends in themselves, there is in India do scope for philosophical or religious dogma. There may be various roads which can take one to the ultimate goal of spiritual realisation, and any talk of exclusiveness in this regard is generally repulsive to the ladian mind In the course of her long history, India has,&#xA;(Continued from the last page) while reading this paper. It may also be pointed out that the assertion of the exclusiveness of the various characteristics vis-a vis India is intended primarily for bringwg iato sbarp relicf the Indian tradition and the Western tradition,&#xA;THE CAST AND THE West&#xA;315&#xA;accordingly, welcomed different races and religious cults without having ever entertained the idca of aggressively converting them to any specific way of life and thought Thus hospitality, this elementary good manners 10 matters of spirit, to use RADHA KRISHNAN&amp;rsquo;s felicitous phrase, has characterised the Indian tradi. tion through the centuries&#xA;But the non individualistic attitude must perhaps be regarded as the most basic attitude of the Indian The genesis of this attitude has of course to be traced back to his cosmic Weltans. chauung The Western thought is essentially anthropo centric &amp;ldquo;Man is the measure of all things&amp;rsquo;. this dictum of Protagoras has oriented the entire outlook of the West As agajost this, in India, man is regarded as just a part of the cosmic whole in the same way as an animal or a tree Man is just one of the many forms in which the Supreme Bcing becomes manifest in this Universe An Upanısadıc seer has put this 10 a ycry telling manner He proclaims that the essential self or the vital essence in man is the same as that in ant, the same as that in gnat, the same as that in elephant, the same as that in these three worlds, indeed, the same as that in the whole universe Co ordination (or setting side by side ) of the various aspects of creation, 10 cluding man, and not subordination to man of other things is the guiding principle of the Indian thought No unique position is ascribed to man in the cosmic scheme of things The Indian man, therefore, acver assumes any domincering attitude in life On the contrary, he is ever eager to siok bis individuality in the ocean of cosmic totality. Humility or surrender before reality comes naturally to the Indian He realises that what is called&#xA;3 It may be contended that, from the cosmic, metaphysical point of view, co ordination may be the guiding principle but in the social organıza tion of the Indians at 13 certainly not so There is thus a kind of dichotomy betweea the spiritual ideology and the social actuality of the Indians A conuderation of this point docs not fall within the scope of thu paper, but it may be pointed out that, in the ultimate analysus, the underlyiog principle of the Indian system of social orders (vargas) also is co-ordination (10 the form of ethical interdependence ) and not subordination [For details, see the discussion of the topic in scveral contexts to DANDEKAR, Insights into Hinduism)&#xA;316&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;life is after all a state of temporary and, from the ultimate point of view, apparent disintegration or standing aparthe, therefore, seeks to achieve te integration through Yoga and mysticism&#xA;It is on account of this son individualistic attitude that India has failed to produce any real work of history as we understand at today That is also why in Jodia one speaks not in terms of individual philosophers but of schools of philosophy All interest is concentrated on ideas and not on individuals on principles and not on personalities In India individuality has, indeed, been never regarded as a problem worthy of senous consideration As against this, the West has consistently opposed the rejection of individuality However, in recent times, Western individualism has been stoutly challenged by the new ideals of collectivism and socialization And therein we see one aspect of the present crisis in the West&#xA;A natural consequence of the Indian non individualism is Indian non activism Individualistic West is aggressively activistic The Western man has been trying to understand nature with a view to ultimately being able to control and direct her forces And the success that he has so far achieved in this his endeavour has prompted him to further activism While detachment&amp;rsquo; 15 the watchword of the Indian s behaviour the Westerner takes deep interest in this life and seeks to make it more and more happy and useful The Indian transcends all this worldly values, be regards them as being merely subservient to the values of another better existence He sees no salvation in the exclusively humanistic ideal of the West &amp;ndash; in its anxiety to remould human society or to reform the state While the West believes that if anything is to be perfected it is this life and this world with all its complexities, the Indian is convinced that there is nothing per manent - either physical or psychical - In this temporal world, nothing enduring, and that, therefore, instead of striving to change this world one would do well to aspire for another better existence&#xA;4&#xA;For details, sec&#xA;Man 1 H ndu thought&#xA;in Ins ghis inlo Hinduism&#xA;TITE FAST AND THE WEST&#xA;317&#xA;The non-activistic and essentially contemplative Indian has consequently lagged far behind the West in the matter of scientific knowledge and matcrial progress. But, thereby, India and the East may be said to have escaped, to a large cxtcnt, another aspect of thc crisis which the West is now facing. On the onc hand, the West is feeling frustrated at the thought that, with all its knowledge and equipment, it has not succeeded in bringing peace and contentment to this world, where, on the contrary, tension is growing day by day in every splicrc of lifc; and, on the other, instead of remaining the master of its activistic impulse, the West has become almost its sfasc. The means of production and the products have, for instance, tended to dominate the producer. The economics of the non-activistic India Hould preach the desir ability of reducing the needs rather than of increasing the pro duction.&#xA;At this stage I may incidentally refer to an apparent locon gruity. I have spoken above of detachment and religiosity as the distinctive features of the Indian way of life and thought. Para doxical as it may sccm, the Indian tradition is by no means devoid of litcrature and art characterised by carcirce sensuous abandon and of religions glorifying orgiastic cults. Indeed, this polarity itself must be mentioned as a characteristic ladian attitude. Or course, this polar attitude is not to be vicucd, as it is sometimes donc, as being the result of the Indian ideology being primitive at the base and highly cultured in devclopment. Rather the two poles - attachment&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;aloofness&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;abandon&amp;rsquo; and asceti cism&amp;rsquo;-are to be understood as being indicative of the essential Dature of one single integrated wholc. In the cosmic-magic ideology, the two extremes of asceticism and sexuality, of capas and kāma, arc regarded as being by no means exclusivc; in an ideal situation, they may co-exist and thereby engender a lind of superb spiritual balance. In the Hindu mythology, Siva, who is celc brated as the most prc.cminent among the Yogins and the ascetics, is also represented as being ever united with his spouse Sakti who is the centre of rcligious orgies.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;See Insights into Hinduism, 309-10.&#xA;318&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;Turning now to the way of approach to the problems of life and reality, it may, at the very outset, be broadly pointed out that the Western approach is intellectualistic, analytic, and regulative, while the Indian approach is intuitive, synoptic, and conformistic. The Western man believes that there can be no knowledge which cannot be expressed by means of verbal and logical symbols. Knowledge, according to him, is a body of strict concepts, and the categories of reason necessarily coincide with those of reality. He revels in setting forth all knowledge in a systematic frame work. To him reason is the only test of reality; formal logic is his very god. On the other hand, in conformity with his general attitude, the Indian regards nyāja (logic) as subservient to reli gion. The aim of logic is not so much epistemological as religious. The Indian has also fully realised the limitations of logic. He, no doubt, accepts the validity of reason, but he positively believes that the ultimate reality is beyond the reach of discursive and demonstrative logic. He is naturally unwilling to accept the absoluteness of any system of thought; for, according to him, truth manifests itself in many ways, and dogma is but the re flection of intellectual vanity. Further, the Indian believes that, in the ultimate analysis, all logical systems are based on the&#xA;relativity&amp;rsquo; and uncertainty of human experience.&#xA;Like the individualism and the activism of the West, its uncompromising intellectualism also has caused a major crisis in Western life. Logical positivism has collapsed before relativity, and the undeniable evidence of the irrational, produced by modern psychology, has brought about the fall of reason from its high pedestal, India has sought to overcome this inevitable intellectual indeterminateness by postulating sabda (scriptural authority) as a valid source of loowledge. The Indian has deep faith in the scriptures, which, according to him, embody the results of the supra-rational perception and intuitive ex perience of the ancient sages. Sensual perception (pratyahṣa) and logical inference (anumāna ) are necessarily limited in scope. for, the capacity of the human senses and of the human intellect is obviously limited. But, at this stage, the Indian exhibits a&#xA;THE EAST AND THE WEST&#xA;319&#xA;remarkable epistemological optimism. He firmly believes that where pure intellectualism fails, faith often functions effectively.&amp;rdquo; In this connection, it may also be pointed out that, for his progress on the path to the direct realisation of reality, the Indian takes the aid of such non-intellectualistic disciplines as Yoga. As against this, the Westerner is critical of everytbing; he hesitates to put faith in anything; for him gothing is sacred by virtue of itself. Therefore, he suffers from a terrible intellectual frustration,&#xA;The attitudes of the Indian and his way of approach to the problems of life and reality have inevitably influenced his thought and practices. Indian cosmology, for instance, accepts the essential oneness of all aspects of being. There is no qualitative difference between one entity and another. According to one phase of the early Vedic thought, the same magical potence, asu, permeates through everyone and everything - god, man, animal,, trees, etc. &amp;ndash; and the apparent manifoldness of form and type is due to quantitative differences. The later doctrine of advaita is but a metaphysical expression of this original cosmic-magic view. It is further believed that the universe, vast and complex as it is, is by no means chaotic; it is governed and regulated by an all pervasive universal law, Rra. Nothing is higher than this cosmic law. Even gods are subservient to it and capaot outgrow it.&#xA;Indian metaphysics cannot be defined in the usual terms of idealism, materialism, realism, etc. The manifold phenomenal manifestations are apparent, transitory, and contingent; they are&#xA;T&#xA;!&#xA;6. Jacidentally, attention may be drawn in this context to a peculiar feature of India&amp;rsquo;s religio-philosophical ideology. Though the Indian has accepted fabda or scripture as the ultimately valid source of knowledge, the religious thought and practice in lodia have by no mocans ternained static on that account, through the various periods of her long history. Unlike many other religions, Hinduism was never bound down by the “ Loub &amp;rsquo; and the &amp;ldquo;Prophct.&amp;rdquo; It would seem that fabda-frutanga had but louted application - it was accepted only as an epistemological device - and that frequcat changes were wrought to religious concepts and precepts so as to make them conform to the changing times. See fo 3a on pp. 72–73 of this Volume.&#xA;7. Scc DAXDEKAR, Vedic Alythological Tracts, 53-56&#xA;8 For R&amp;rsquo;s, see the relevant portions in the book mentioned in the preceding fn.&#xA;322&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;deeper fundamental plane it has proved to be remarkably dynamic. As for the second vicw, it is necessarily partial and tendentious. Many European historians, and others who had come under their influence, believed that Europe was the scene of the origin and growth of real culture and could, therefore, alone be a proper subject of history They, therefore, deliberately refused to study the history of the Eastern civilisations. The erstwhile popular assumption of the Hellenistic origin of Indian drama, art, medi cine, etc, for instance, was but an ego-centric illusion of the Western mind The correct view would be that, in the course of history, the Indian culture and the Western culture had influenced each other in several ways,&#xA;How can the fact and the nature and extent of the influence of one culture upon another be determined ? Direct, specific, and unequivocal evidence in this regard is obviously not always possible. We have often to depend on the evidence which is circumstantial and inferential. It is also not possible to state in very precise terms the various aspects of such infuence, One point needs to be specially emphasised in this connection. Similarities or resemblances between two cultures, however striking, are not always a sure criterion of the influence of one culture upon the other. Similarities may be accidental. Side shoots sprouting out from two different stems are, pot unoften, seen to approximate one another as a matter of course. Similar ideologies and practices may also evolve independently in two different areas. Similar problems faced by the human intellect on similar backgrounds may be tackled independentlly but in similar ways Such similar-looking cultural growths are really&#xA;parallel,&amp;rsquo; It is further not unlikely that the influence of a common third source, and not mutual contact, is the cause of some resemblances. Some resemblances may, again, be only apparent and superficial. The apparently similar concepts may have actually originated from entirely different contexts and on entirely different planes The cosmic non-individualism of India, for instance, cannot by any means be regarded as being similar to the collectivistic or socialistic non-individualism of the modern&#xA;THE &amp;lsquo;EAST AND THE WEST&#xA;323&#xA;West. Similarly, the claim that the sages of ancient India had anticipated in their speculations some of the results of modern science (e. g. coormous number of years from the beginning of creation to the present yuga; infinite number of worlds existing outside our own; presence of worlds even in the space of an aton; etc.) must be regarded as untenable. Lastly, it must be pointed out that partial resemblances are always deceptive.&#xA;We may, however, set forth some workable criteria for our present purpose. The Indian way of life and thought is essentially traditional in character. It is seen that even original thinkers have been chary of afirming the originality of their contributions; they have always tried to fit in their contributions into the traditional pattern. Whatever, therefore, seems not to belong to the traditional pattern may be regarded as the result of foreign jofluence. So too, whatever is peculiar to a particular author or school - that is to say, whatever was generally not knows or accepted before that author or school and is generally not known or accepted after that author or school - may be the result of foreign influence. It might be further assumed that borrowing would normally occur in those spheres of life and thought in which India had not made sufficient advance. Generally speak ing, no foreign borrowing or influence might be expected in the fields of philosophy, religion, literature, etc. It has also to be remembered that the influence of one culture upon another may either be general and of a more or less permanent character, or it may be limited to a particular sphere of life and to a particular historical period. In many cases, Western ideas and ideals, being exotic, have failed to strike root in traditional India. What is, however, perhaps most important in this context is that it should be possible to account for the phenomenon of influence Tationally and in conformity with the history and cultural develop ment of Iodia.&#xA;The first principal landmark in the history of the intercourse between lodia and the West must be said to be represented by the obvious relationship between the Indus valley civilisation and the contemporary civilisations of Western Asia. A more or less324&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;uniform culture-complex may be presumed to have extended from the Mediterranean to the Indus in the fourth and the third millennia B.C. A little later the Indo-European-speaking tribes from the West and the North migrated into the North-Western region of India. These people, popularly known as the Vedic Aryans, brought with them their own language, religion, and culture, which, in course of time, proved to be some of the most fundamental factors in the evolution of the Tadian culture. Words of Babylo nian and Chaldean origin occurring in the Veda, rare as they are have also to be understood as implying some contact between India on the one hand and Babylon and Chaldea on the other. Similarly, the early Dravidian language and culture show unmistakable affinities with the prehistoric cultures of Anatolia, Armenia, and Iran The Lycians of Asia Minor, in their inscriptions, called themselves Trimmlai, which word is presumably related to dramila or Tamil A large number of ancient place-names in that region are shown to conform to Dravidian forms. The Hurrian and the Kassite languages also show great alioity with the Dravidian. These linguistic affinities between Western Asia and South India are clearly confirmed by cultural affinities.12 A more direct evidence is available of vigorous trade gojog on between the Phoenicians of the Levant and the merchants of Southern and Western India found about 975 B, C.&#xA;More siguifcapt, however, from our present point of view is the period of the contacts between India and Greece. It must be pointed out that, in this context, Greece has to be understood in a wider sense as comprising Greece and Greek colonies in Asia Minor, Egypt, Italy, and Sicily, while India has to be understood io a far too restricted seose as being coextensive only with the region of the lodus. The connecting link between India apd Greece in this carly period was the Persian empire. It is histori cally attested that the Persian emperor Darius sent a Greek mercenary, called Scylax, to sail down the river Indus to its mouth, in about 510 B. C. It is not unlikely that Herodotus&#xA;12. See : K. A. NILAKANTA SAJTRI, A Ilustory of South India, 57-58.&#xA;THE EAST AND THE WEST&#xA;325&#xA;(born 484 B. C.), who gives several significant details about India, has utilized the accounts of Scylax&amp;rsquo;s adventures. Ctesias (401 B, C.), another Greek who had travelled in India, wrote quite a lot about this country, but his descriptions are rather fanciful. But, even before the times of Darius, India seems to have heard and known of the Greeks, la this connection, it is significant that the great grammarian of Sanskrit, Pānioi, refers to the script of the Yavanas (lonians) in a familiar way. A mention may also be made here of the interesting tradition, which Eusebius attributes to Aristoxenus (330 B. C.), namely, that an Indian Pandit actually visited Athens and conversed with Socrates. The Indian Pandit, it is said, asked Socrates what he was occupied with. On being told by Socrates that his work consisted in inquiriog into the life of man, the Indian Pandit smilingly retorted that none could hope to understand things human who had not understood things divide. It is generally believed that Alexander&amp;rsquo;s raid on the Indus region (4th cent. B. C.) facilitated deeper and more extensive contacts between India and the West. But the raid itself did not make any discernible impact on the history of Indian culture. The Hellenistic intrusion into India must be said to have really begon with Demetrius, the Greek king of Bactria, who crossed the Hindu Kush in 190 B.C. And, even after the Greek principalities in that region had come to an end, the Hellenistic influence on India continued through the “Philhellenic” sakas, Parthians, and Kuṣānas (2nd cent. B. C. to 1st cent. A. C.).&#xA;During the first centuries A. C., Alexandria had developed into a great cosmopolitan cultural centre. According to a tradition, the Alexandrians honoured a Buddhist monk from Bhțgukaccha and listened to him with as much attention as to Saint Paul. There is also evidence of brisk trade and other contacts between South India and the Roman Empire.194 Similarly some Indian rulers are known to have appointed&#xA;12a. One may recall in this connection the arcbacological excavations carried out in recent years at Arikmedu and other places in South India.&#xA;326&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;ambassadors at the Roman Court, and Roman colonies are said to have been established at Cannanore, Madura, etc Christianity also made its way into India duriog this period, though it does not seem to have the influenced the Indian way of life and thought in any significant way Marco Polo&amp;rsquo;s accounts of his Indian travels12b are historically important, but, on the whole, there was, in the medieval period, a compara tive lull in the cultural intercourse between India and the West 13&#xA;On May 20 1498, the Portuguese adventurer, Vasco de Gama, sailed into Calicut, and thus began what may be called the modern period in the history of the intercourse between Igdia and the West Of course, in this period we are more particularly concerned with the Indo British contacts&#xA;Out of the above mentioned four periods in the history of the intercourse between India and the West, for the purpose of this paper, I have taken into account only the last three&#xA;So far as the Hellenistic contacts with India are concerned, broadly speaking, before Alexander&amp;rsquo;s campaign, thought seems to have travelled - mainly, and quite understandably - from the East towards the West Though positive evidence in this connection is mostly lacking there is a strong probability of the Indian thought having rafluenced the Greek philosophers Chronology and historically demonstrable contacts would seem to support the assumption of such influence Thales, the father of Greek philosophy postulated water as the basic element It is not unlikely that in this postulation he was influenced by the Vedic concept of primeval waters Similarly the Upanisadıc theory of one single Reality underlyiog the phenomenal manifoldness may be presumed to have been the source of the speculations of the Eleatic school The entire body of the religio philosophical and mathematical teaching of Pythagoras had been known in India&#xA;126 Round about 1275 A C&#xA;13 Tor furt) er details regardiog ti cse three periods in the history of the intercourse between India and ibc Hest see Indo-Afcditerranean contacts Published elsewhere in this Volume&#xA;THB EAST AND THE WEST&#xA;327&#xA;already in the 6th century B. C., and the biographer of Pythagoras tells us that the latter bad travelled exteosively and had thereby become familiar with the thought of the Brāhmaṇas among others. The afinities between the Orphic school and India&amp;rsquo;s transcendental philosophy are self-evident, and, if any influence is to be presumed, India must be regarded as the source of that influence. The same thing may be said in connection with Neoplatonism on the one hand and Vedānta, Yoga, and Buddhism on the other. In this context, one may usefully refer to the verdict of Clement of Alexandria who proclaimed that the Greeks bad stolen their philosophy from the barbarians. According to Lucianus (2nd cent, A. C.) also, philosophy had beea first cultivated in India before it came to Greece. Further, it is well known that gnosticism is often characterised as &amp;ldquo;Orientalism in Hellenic Mask.&amp;rdquo;&#xA;As suggested above, the flow of culture definitely changed its course from the time of Alexander onwards. It was the Western thought and culture which now began to influence the East. Some aspects of this jofluence, so far as it operated on lodia&amp;rsquo;s cultural development, may be noted here.&#xA;The polity of the Mauryan age (4th century B. C.), as reflected in the Arthasāstra of Kautilya, exhibits certain features which are alien to the traditional political thought of Jodia. 180 According to the traditional view, the highest sanction in social and political matters vested in Dharma. In the Indian theory of government, both Brahman, the spiritual authority (normally symbolised by the Brāhmana Purohita ), and Kṣatra, the temporal power ( normally symbolised by the Ksatriya ruler), were, in the ultimate analysis, always subordioated to Dharma. Indeed, sacerdotium and regnum were both regarded as but instruments of Dharma. As against this, according to the Arthaśāstra of Kautilya, from among the four sources of authority, namely, Dharma, civil and criminal law, custom, and royal edict, each&#xA;13a. K. A. NILAKANTA SASTRI, &amp;ldquo;The place of the Arthalastra in the Iterature of Indian polity,&amp;rdquo; ABORI 28, 84–95.&#xA;328&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;succeeding one was superior in validity to each preceding one.14 This kind of absolute exaltation of the king&amp;rsquo;s authority was unknown to ancient Indian tradition. Nor can it be said to have been generally accepted in the post-Mauryan periods. It clearly marks a deviation from the cosmic non-individualistic ideology of India. It may, therefore, be presumed that Kautilya derived this concept of monarchic absolutism from the political ideas and ideals of the Persians and the Greeks. The intercourse between India and the West had become closer and the interchange of ideas more active and vigorous in the period immediately following Alexander&amp;rsquo;s Indian campaign. And it is, indeed, not unlikely that, when Kautilya says that he has formulated his political theories on the basis of traditional sciences (sästra) and actual practices (prayoga),15 the practices intended by him are the political practices obtaining in the Persian and the Greek empires. Incidentally, a reference may be made in this connec tion to the view of STEIN that the chapter in Kautilya&amp;rsquo;s Artha śāstra, which deals with the Sāsanādlukāra (II. 10), bears á composite appearance and shows signs of having been remodelled in the light of Roman Imperial letters of a later time, 15a&#xA;Another teaching of Kautilya, which does not seem to fit in well into the pattern of India&amp;rsquo;s traditional polity, relates to the vast bureaucratic governmental machinery with centralised control.16 The Maurya rulers are known to have actually tried to translate this teaching into practice. The Mauryan state, which sought to plan, control, and direct the entire social and economic life of the nation, departed fundamentally from the traditional practice of not interfering actively in the daily avoca. tions of the people. In this matter, Kautilya must have obviously received inspiration from the Hellenistic concept of the State. As ROSTOVZEFF says, through such radical centralisation of government, Candragupta and Kautilya did more to &amp;ldquo;hellenise&amp;rdquo; India than Demetrius and Menander.17&#xA;+54 11. 10.&#xA;14, KA III.1. 15. KA II, 10.&#xA;15a, 211 6, 45-71. 16. See particularly KA II: Adhyaksapracıira. 17. Social and Economic History of the Hellenistic World.&#xA;THB EAST AND THE WEST&#xA;329.&#xA;Another field in which the Hellenistic influence becomes perfectly evident is art. In the Gāndhāra art, which is also significantly called Graeco-Buddhist art, the subject is Buddhistic while the style of execution is undeniably Hellenistic. This art was actually sponsored only after the direct Greek domination in the North-Western region had ended, and was patronised mainly by the Sakas and the Kuṣānas who continued the tradition of their Hellenistic predecessors. The traditional cosmic non individualistic outlook of the Indians did not encourage the sculptures of individual isolated figures. It must have been the contact with the anthropocentric West which had inspired the sculpture of the figures of the Buddha. Indeed, the religious penchant of the Indian culture united with the aesthetic penchant of the Hellenistic culture produced this one of the most sublime and creative schools of art. It must, however, be pointed out that the later specimens of the Gāndhāra art were characterised by a lack of sympathy, sincerity, and spontaneity. The artists tended to indulge in a kind of mechanical mass-production of sculptural figures. Such mechanical approach and attitude were unknown in India, and their origin also has to be traced to the Western influence.&#xA;The Western influence on the ancient Indian coinage is equally conspicuous. A type of coins previously unknown to India came to be introduced by the Bactrian Greeks. These coins had the names and portraits of the rulers inscribed upon them. This may be presumed to have been the result of the influence of the anthropocentric West. The earlier Indian coins had been mostly punch-marked. The Hellenistic character of this gew coinage becomes evident from two facts: first, instead of the figures of the rulers, these coios sometimes show the figures of the divinities belonging to the Greek pantheon; and second, the pames Dinara and Dramma, given to some of these coins, are obviously Indian forms of Greek Dinarius and Drachma. The standardisation of the new coinage in respect of form, character, and weight was also something which had been unknown in India in the earlier periods, and must, therefore, be presumed to have been due to foreiga influence.&#xA;830&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;Astronomy may be mentioned as still another sphere in which the lodian thought was influenced by the Greek and the Roman theories In this connection, the view expressed by Varaha mıhıra is highly significant This distinguished Indian writer on astronomy of the 6th century A C says &amp;ldquo;The science of astronomy is well established among the Yavanas Therefore, though they are barbarians, they must be respected like our own ancient sages 18 Alberuni refers to another writer, earlier than Varahamihira who records high praise of Greek scholars As a matter of fact after the 3rd century A C, the influence of Greek and Roman knowledge in various sciences began to be effectively felt among the learned circles in India It is, therefore, not surprising that two of the five principal schools of astronomy came to be named Romaka (after Rome) and Paulisa ( after Paul of Alexandria, 378 A C)&#xA;The contacts between India and the West, which, in the earlier periods of history, had been more or less occasional and brief, have tended to become steady and permanent in recent years Consequently, the influence of the West on the Indian way of life and thought in modern times, has proved to be compa ratively deeper and more extensive It is but natural that, in this context, one has to think primarily of the lado British intercourse during the last two hundred years or so A few characteristics of this Indo British impact may be stated here To begin with, it would be seen that the British influence began to operate 10 India from above downwards The large masses of the Indians semained almost unaffected by that influence, at least in the initial stages of the intercourse between the British and the Indians Whatever influence there had been was, accordingly, only superficial Attention may also be drawn to the attitude of the Early Europeans who came to India They were all inspired by a purely mercenary and adventurist spirit They looked upon India as colonie d exploration and not as colonie de peuplement In this respect, they differed fundamentally from the ancient&#xA;18&#xA;Brholsam hita 2&#xA;14&#xA;THE EAST AND THE west&#xA;331&#xA;Indians who had colonised in the different regions of South-East Asia. By way of contrast, two features of this ancient Indian colonisation may be particularly emphasised. Firstly, these colonies had little or no political connection with the metropolitan India; and secondly, these colonies never entertained the idea of economically exploiting those various regions for the sake of the mother-country. On the other hand, those regions themselves became independent Indias in miniature.&#xA;The dealings with the Indians of the early British officers were actuated by a sense of racial superiority and scorn for everything Indian. Their ignorance of the heritage of India and of the East was colossal. MACAULAY was perhaps the most shining example of this kind of racial and cultural arrogance. When such an attitude is in evidence, the process of cultural give-and take is necessarily retarded. A tribute must, however, be paid, at this stage, to the great service rendered by the European Orienta lists in India and in the West to the cause of the wider and fuller appreciation of India&amp;rsquo;s art, philosophy, and literature. But, in actual practice, the influence of the Orientalists was quite limited in extent. On the whole, therefore, the early intercourse between the English and the Indians may be said to have proved sterile. As a matter of fact, neither then por later did the English make any attempt - though they were in a position to do so - to develop a new form of civilisation, a sort of Indo-British civilisa tion, in India. Whatever influence India has received from the West, during this period, is mostly due to the initiative of the Indians themselves.&#xA;While considering the impact of the English on India, one must also not forget that the Indian civilisation and the Western civilisation are essentially different in ethos. As indicated else where, the attitude of the Indians and their approach to the various problems of life were quite distinct from those of the West. Many features of the Western civilisation failed to be appreciated by the Indian mind; they were exotic and did not strike root in the Indian soil.&#xA;332&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;The reaction of the Indians to the impact of the Western culture in modern times may be said to have been fourfold. There were some Indians who had been completely swayed by the Western way of life and thought. Their entire outlook was Westernised-so much so that they were dominated by a sense of revolt against the Indian tradition. Indeed, as converts to the new ideology they exhibited greater fanaticism than the Westergers themselves. The other extreme was represented by the people who wanted to repudiate everything that was foreign These people believed that there could be nothing richer and nobler than the traditional Indian culture and that those who were even slightly inclined towards the Western way of life and thought were paving the way to perdition for India Their reaction to the impact of the West often bordered on obscurantism. Even at the remotest hint of anything foreign they withdrew themselves into the closed shell of ancient traditions. The third kind of reaction was resignation to the new situation There was a class of people - and the majority of people belonged to this class &amp;ndash; who passively accepted the things as they came. They did not bother themselves about either the mending or the ending of the new dispensation. The thought-leaders from among the newly educated middle class, however, saw the possibility of a fruitful blending of the Eastern and the Western cultures. They might have differed from one another in respect of the emphasis in the new synthesis on one culture or the other. But they generally aimed at evolving a new culture which would be essentially Indian in spirt though Western in form and expression. They also hoped that, as the result of this dynamic synthesis, they would be able to fight away their Western rulers by means of the very weapons which the latter had made available to them,&#xA;Some of the actual results of the influence of the British on Indian life may now be briefly stated here. With the foundation in 1857. under the auspices of the British government, of the three Universities - at Calcutta, Bombay, and Madras - the doors of knowledge may be said to have been, for the first time, opened to all lodiaps irrespective of sex, class, or creed. For instance, the&#xA;THB EAST AND THE WEST&#xA;333&#xA;study of the real language of the Indian culture, namely, Sanskrit, which had till then been restricted to a specific class, could now be pursued by anybody in the Universities and the secondary schools. This was, indeed, a tremendous experiment to universalise education - at least in theory. The content and the methodology of the new education were also mostly derived from the English pattera. Education, it was realised, must inculcate among the students an attitude of inquiry as against the traditional attitude of acceptance. Mere line-by-lipe study of ancient texts, intensive as it had been, was found to be static and non-productive. An attempt was, therefore, made under Western inspiration, to make the study of any subject dynamic and broad-based by adopting critical, comparative, and historical methods. As a result, the new scientific literature was not restricted to being merely interpretative; it also tended to become creative. The aim of education, it came to be reiterated, was not, as formerly under stood, only the conservation of ancient knowledge; it was also the acquisition - and more particularly the creation - of new kaowledge. The scope of study in schools and Universities was, accordingly, considerably enlarged by the addition of new subjects.&#xA;In the field of public administration, several centuries after the Mauryas, the British again sponsored a vast bureaucracy with centralised control. However, their two most remarkable contributions in this sphere must be said to be the setting up of all-India services and the insistence on the absolute authority and universality of law. These two went a long way in integra ting India iolo a politically homogeneous unit.&#xA;India has had and still continues to have mostly an agrarian economy. But the industrial revolution, which the country has witoessed during recent years, is, without doubt, wholly due to the impact of the West. The impact of the West and the general world-situation have rudely shocked India out of her traditional non-activism. The Indians have now realised that they will not survive the new global struggle for existence unless they industria lise their country, and that they cannot industrialise their country334&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;unless they learn the sciences and technology of the West. Contrary to her traditional spirit, India is now aiming at raising the material standard of living of her people.&#xA;As for the influence of the West in the sphere of religion, I do not want to refer, in this paper, to the proselytizing activities of the Christian missionaries in India. Nor do I want to say anything about the ineffective attempts of the Portuguese to evolve a sort of an Indian-Christian civilisation, I want to mention quite another kind of influence. Though the traditional religious life of India seems to have been generally unaffected by the impact of the West, the Western thought has influenced the religious ideology of modern India - at least at certain levels - in various subtle ways. This influence has worked in four main directions, namely, rationalisation, liberalisation, universalisation, and activisation, Modern Indian thinkers have sought to reinterpret India&amp;rsquo;s religio-philosophical ideas and ideals in terms of modern knowledge and aspirations, and thereby to render them appealing to the rationalistic disposition of the Western and the Western-educated Indian intellectuals. They have tried to dispel the general misunderstanding that Indian religions are crude conglomerations of superstitious beliefs and primitive practices. Tadia&amp;rsquo;s religio-philosophical ideology, they assert, would effectively meet the claims of the metaphysical curiosity as well as of the spiritual quest of even the modern world. This was, indeed, what Swami VIVEKANANDA did - obviously under the Western influence; and this is what RADHAKRISHNAN is doing now.&#xA;Attempts were also made, again under the influence of the Western thought, through movements like the Brahmo Samaj, to rid the Hindu religion of its exclusive character. Caste distinc tions and worship of specific gods, which had been the hall-marks of this exclusiveness, were discarded, and all persons, irrespective of sex, caste, and creed, were brought together within the larger brotherhood of bhakti for a universal godhead. In some cases, the Indian theology was sought to be actually brought close to the Western theology. The Indians have been traditionally&#xA;THE EAST AND THE WEST&#xA;335&#xA;actuated by a spirit of tolerance in the field of both thought and practice. They were gencrally always willing to sacrifice the petty superficial differences in creed and cult at the altar of the ultimate spiritual goal. It was, therefore, by no means difficult to emphasise the liberal outlook and the universal aspect of Hinduism so as to make it conform to the new situation. But perhaps the most significant change which the Western impact brought about in the religious sphere was the social value with which religion came to be so emphatically reinvested. Religion, it was asserted, must not aim merely at individual salvation. Service to society was as much a religious duty as service to god. Religion and social reforms must not be regarded as antithetical. Indeed, the humanistic aspect of religion must be allowed to dominate over its denominational aspect. Such views definitely re-activised and re-vitalised lodian religion, and a new missionary zeal became evident in the sphere of religion, as exemplified by the Ramakrishna Mission and the Arya-Samaj.&#xA;It would not be an exaggeration to say that, even in their recent struggle for dependence, the Indians received their main inspiration from the West. For one thing, the contact with the West helped India to regaip her lost individuality. A new sense of nationalism and social solidarity was engendered among the Indians and spurred them on in their freedom struggle. Whether that struggle took the form of constitutional agitation or of secret revolutionary insurrection or of moral non-violent resistance, the leaders of the struggle invariably derived the impetus from the writings and doings of Westerners like ROUSSEAU, MILL, MAZZINI, TOLSTOY, THOREAU, and RUSKIN. Of course, in order to be able effectively to appeal to the patriotic instinct of their followers the lodian leaders had to fall back, from time to time, on the teachings of the Bhagavadgitā and the Buddha and on the heroic examples from the Epics and the historical annals of India.&#xA;What is the prospect of the influence of the West which has been operating in India in recent years? As indicated above, a new form of social compromise seems to be evolviog out of this Western impact. The Indians are avidly experimenting with the&#xA;336&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;various economic, political, and social systems and thought patterns of the West, but they are also becoming keenly aware of the serious crises which the individualistic, intellectualistic, and activistic West is facing today. They realise that, if they do not become divorced from the essential spirit of what may be called Indianism, they will still be able to avoid those crises. A new society with Western equipment seems inevitable, but in order that this new society should be enabled to survive the crises of the modern age it must have an Indian soul GANDHIJI, indeed, sounded a timely note of warning to his compatriots when he told them that they might allow winds from many quarters to blow over them but that they must not allow themselves to be swept off their feet by those winds&#xA;[ First published JUPHS, No 17, 1963, 67–83 Also published Proceedings of the Ninth International Congress for the History of Religions, Tokyo, 1960, 667– 674, 693-704 ]&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>hRd in vedas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/hRd_in_vedas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/hRd_in_vedas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Another current of thought also is associated with the notion of hrd. A study of certain words in Gk, Lat, etc., possessing psychological significance, such as phren, phrénes, kérdos, vecors, recordari, proves that the human faculties of feeling, willing, etc, were connected by the people speaking those languages more parti cularly with the heart. The same feature is to be noticed in the Veda also, It is obviously on account of certain distinctive features of hrd, such as its being the innermost as well as the most vital and the most sensitive organ in the human body, that certain primary psychological functions have come to be connected with it. Primi tive thinking does not seem to have countenanced any abstract conceptions. Whatever is real must be, according to the primitive thought, concrete and substantial. So the psychological experi ences also were associated by the primitive man with concrete physical organs And the bodily organ, which was particularly .affected by such experiences as fear, anger, hatred, longing, love, etc.,,was evidently the heart in this manner the heart became the starting point of early psychological speculations. In what may be called the pre-analytical stage of Vedic psychology, side by side with hrd, manas also played a similar role and that too in a more or less material form 3 Several psychological ex. -periences and functions had come to be related to manas. 1 would, however, seem that, when manas was later conceived as the human faculty connected with certain specific psychological (functions, such as sankalpa, the Vedic poet began to lay greater stress upon the original association of hrd and the primary psy ichological experiences. In such cases hrd may be said to have been regarded rather as a psychological faculty than as a mere physical organ. The association of hrd and hurdaya with manas (RV, VII, 98. 2; VIII, 100.5), dhi and manisi (RV. I. 61.21 would confirm this assumption It is from this point of view that a few characteristics of hrd as constituting an element of the human personality will be described in this paper. For, the role of hrd in human life as represented in the Veda is, as is perhaps&#xA;3 See &amp;ldquo;Somatism of Vedic psychology&amp;rdquo; published elsewhere in this Volume.&#xA;&amp;ldquo;ARD IN THE VEDA&#xA;255&#xA;quite natural, essentially psychological. But,&amp;rsquo; for the sake of a clear understanding of this entire conception, the significant deve lopment in the notion of hrd, broadly outlined above, should not be lost sight of&#xA;In the so-called analytical stage of Vedic psychology híd seems to have been distinguished from manas in that it then camc to be regarded as the basis of all spontaneous psychological ex periences. All such psychological phenomena as do not require any sort of positive effort for their manifestation are normally connected with hrd. &amp;lsquo;Fear&amp;rsquo;, for instance, is said to enter into the heart (RV I. 32. 14); elsewhere it is spoken of as being placed in the heart (RV X. 84.7; AV IV. 31.7). Similarly one finds that desire is spoken of as having its roots in the heart (RV X. 40. 12). A Vedic poet says that Agni knows their hearts : asmaddhirdo blūrijanmā yi casļe (RIX. 5.1). Siyana, in his commentary, explains lidah as hrdayāni, that is to say, abhilaṣitāni : asmakam hrdayāni abhilasilani jānālt. Incidentally, we clearly observe here a peculiarity of the Veda, pamely that a human faculty itself is made to represent its own function. The &amp;ldquo;longing&amp;rsquo; on the part of a person is manifested in his heart (RV X. 123. 6). The feelings of pleasure&amp;rsquo; and satisfaction spring from the heart (RV I.43.1; VIII.43.31; AV XX, 87.2). Soka, in the same manger, burns the heart (RV X. 103. 12; AV VI. 18. 1; XIX 28.2), or the heart is said to be free from, torment&amp;rsquo; (AV XVI. 3. 6) The Vedic poet refers to himself, in another sepse, as invoking Indra with a burning heart : yar tvà hrda focatā johanim (AV 11. 12. 3). The words, Liriñã hrdā (RV V.4 10), suggest, according to GRASSMANN, the feeling of grati tude. It will be thus seen that, in all these cases, the sponta neity of the psychological phenomena is suggested through their association with hrd.&#xA;Besides spontaneity&amp;rsquo;, the association of the psychological phenomena with hrd also signifies their sincere,&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo; spiritual,&amp;rsquo; and inspired character ( AV I. 60.3; 116. 17). It should be noted&#xA;4. GRASSMANN, Rig Veda, erster Theil, $ 358, p. 165.&#xA;256&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;in this connection that, in the Veda, lird is often considered to be the proper fountain of song. The Vedic mantra springs directly from the heart of the poet (RV 1. 60.3). In one Vedic passage, Indra is implored to accept such a song, which goes up to bim, in all exuberance of sincere and spontaneous feelings and emotions, like a beloved to her lover (RV III. 39, 1). In another passage, the streams of poetry are described as flowing out of the ocean of the heart : etā arsanti hrdyāt samudrät (RV IV. 58, 5). The heart is the ocean from out of which the genuine feelings of a Soma-inspired poet flow forth. According to the Vedic poet, the seat of genuine poetical inspiration is the heart. Indeed, in RV III. 26. 8 a Vedic poet seems to have succinctly set forth the whole process of the origin of a truly inspired song. First of all there flashes a light (jyotih: inspiration ). It touches the poet&amp;rsquo;s heart. The seed of the song thus sown begins to sprout with all the spontaneity, sincerity, and spirituality associated with hrd (hrdā anu prajānan). The words in which that song (arka) is to be formulated are then made to pass through the threefold sieve of inner thought (tribhih pavitraih apupot) so that they may ultimately spring forth as a properly refined, well thought out, and well wrought prayer (mati).? It is directly from hrd that the poet addresses the divinity: hrdā hūyanta ukthinah ( RV VIII, 76,8).&#xA;Not only does the Vedic song originate from hrd but its appeal too is directed towards hrd. It is in this sense that the Vedic song is often said to be hrdısprś (RV I. 16.7; X. 47. 7). It ought to go directly to the heart of the divinity (RV VII. 101,5). It must also lie within the heart : hrdi stoma upaśrilas cid astu (RV VIII. 86,8). The Vedic song, indeed, forms the&#xA;5. In this connection one may recall the Wordsworthian conception of poetry as the spontancous overflow of powerful feelings. Such poetry may ba distinguished from the vaco mali (RV I. 143 1) type of poetry, in which a cons cious effort is made, as by a laksa&amp;rsquo; a carpenter&amp;rsquo;, to put the best words in the best order and thus to make the prayer a sunku, a well wrought song.&#xA;6. Cf. RV X 71.2 : saklum 100 Itauna punanlah. 7. Cf. RVI, 143. 1 ; t4co matt,HRD IN THE VEDA 1&#xA;257&#xA;bridge between the heart of the poet and the heart of the divinity and thus brings about the true communion between the two. It should be noted that an interesting commingling of ideas on the part of the Vedic poet occurs in this connection. Like stoma, Soma also is called hrdisprś (RV X, 25, 2),for, it is said to enter into the depths of hrd ( RV III, 42. 8, IX. 60. 3; 108. 16). It is not only in this respect that Soma is similar to stoma, the Vedic song. Just as the Soma-juice is pressed out and purified three times ( RV IX. 73. 8), so too is the Vedic song purified and perfected through the functioning of hrd and manas : samyak sravanti sarito na dhenā antar hrda manasā pūyamānah (RV IV. 58.6: also cf. III. 26 8) Soma is often referred to as pouring into and reposiog in the heart (RV I. 91. 13; 168, 3; 179.5; VIII. 2. 12; 48. 12) From out of the heart spring forth the in spired songs of the Vedic poet. These two notions seem to have merged into one another. The Vedic poet, therefore, represents the origin of the song in terms of the stream of Soma (ghrta. dhārāk) flowing out of the ocean of the heart (RV IV. 58. 5; also cf. IV. 58 11; X 5.1; 89.4). This conception of Vedic poetry originating from the heart of the poet and having a direct appeal to the heart of the divinity would clear up a common mis understanding about its nature, namely, that Vedic poetry is often purely conventional in form and content.&#xA;According to the early Indian thinkers, true comprehension lies not in indirectly knowing&amp;rsquo; a thing, but in directly feeling&amp;rsquo; it. The Vedic poet seems to express this idea when he suggests that true comprehension appears in hrd Through the light&amp;rsquo; of hrd, there dawned upon Sunahấepa the true knowledge of the nature and function of Varuṇa : 1ad ayam keto hrda ā vi coste (RY 1.24.12). In another passage (RV V. 31.9), darkness is said to have been driven away from the heart. Another striking passage (RV VII.&#xA;8 hrdısprfah, in this context, 13 understood by Sayapa and GELDNER as Nom. Pl. referring to the priests.&#xA;9. Here there seems to be an obvious commingling of the two DOLIODS regarding hid-rd as a physical organ, perhaps belly &amp;lsquo;, and hyd as a psychologi. cal faculty.&#xA;33—&#xA;258&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;33 9) tells us that through the lights of the heart&amp;rsquo; (hrdayasya praketaih), Vasistha was enabled to comprehend the great secret of the phenomenal world 10 Elsewhere (RVX 129 4) we are told that the secret of how, in the beginning of the universe, the non existent was related to the existent and of how indeed the existent arose was first revealed to the seers in their heart sato bandhum asatı niravindan hrdı pratisya kayayo manisa The role of hrd in the Vedic religion is, again by no means unimportant When the Vedic seers intuitively discover the divinity, dhirasah padam kajajo nayantı, they seek, by means of every effort, each to hold that divinity in the heart nana hrda raksamānā ajuryam (RVI 146 4 ) This alone would facilitate an eternal direct com munion with the divinity An AV-poet expresses the same idea when he says yo no agnih pitaro hrtsv antar aviveśa amrto mar tyesu mayy aham tam parigrhnāmı devam (XII 2 33) &amp;lsquo;what Agni hath entered into our hearts, an immortal among the mortals, that god do I inclose within me&amp;rsquo;&#xA;It will be seen from the foregoing brief statement regarding the salient features of hrd and its functions that the original notion about hrd was greatly influenced in the Veda by other psychologi cal concepts, particularly by the manas concept It would, there fore, be interesting to note in this connection the main features which characterise the relation between hrd and manas in the Veda To begin with, it appears that the word hrd is connected with manas, in certain passages, more or less as an adjective Thus the word hrd seems to qualify, to a certain extent, the functions of manas The phrase hrda manasa occurs more than once in RV in one context, RV X 177 1, Sayana rightly explains hrda manasā as antarmukhena manasa The ideas of spontaneity, sincerity, spirituality, introspection, true knowledge, etc, which are usually associated with hrd are thus brought into contact with the function of manas A specific type of think ing&amp;rsquo; is here indicated by the addition of the word hird In another context (RV VI 28 5), Sayana again suggestively ex&#xA;10&#xA;See&amp;rdquo; The two births of Vas tha&#xA;publ shed elsewhere in this Volume&#xA;HRD IN THE VEDA&#xA;259&#xA;plains the phrase hrdā manasā as Sraddhāyuklena manasā. The distinction between the two concepts of hird and manas implied here is that manas represents the faculty of thinking-of reason, while hrd represents the faculty of feeling-of faith&amp;rsquo;. The real intellectual approach towards anything should be, according to the Vedic poet, one characterised both by reason and faith. A linguistic study of the words meaning &amp;lsquo;heart&amp;rsquo; in the cognate IE languages would show that, properly speaking, the Vedic equi valent of the original IE word *kered, *kred, should have been Śrd. In its place, lird, which is merely a Iliyme-word, has actually been preserved. It seems, however, that śrd also has been re tained in Vedic in another form, viz , śrad. The Vcdic verb śrad v dha, which corresponds with IE kred dhē, literally means &amp;rsquo;to put one&amp;rsquo;s heart&amp;rsquo;, that is, to believe, have faith&amp;rsquo;. The man Der, in which that verb is used in śrad asınai dhatta (RV II, 12,5) makes it clear that srad must have been used as an independent word, obviously in the same sense asi hrd 12&#xA;be 11&#xA;· The Vedic poet tries to express the distinction between the human faculties of hrd and manas and their respective functions in several ways. One passage (RV VIII, 100, 5) is particularly illuminating in this connection. Indra explains the reason for his sudden appearance on the earth. When he sat alone, upon the back of the much sought after (sky)&amp;rsquo;, there entered in him a feeling of urgent anxiety. He wondered why such a feeling should bave originated Thereupon an inner voice told him that his devoted singers were invoking him, and so he came down to the earth. This entire psychological process on the part of Indra has been very picturesquely described by the Vedic poet. The heart is, as we have seen so far, the human faculty which is usu ally the seat of “ feelings&amp;rsquo;. Manas, on the other hand, is the human faculty which is responsible for positive thinking&amp;rsquo;. In this particular psychological experience of Indra, his lid could&#xA;11. The Avestan zrazd (Skt {raddha ) is connected with zerd heart&amp;rsquo;. The connection between heart&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;faith&amp;rsquo; will be made clear by the study of the relevant words 10 other IE languages, such as Lat. credo, cor, etc&#xA;260&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;&amp;lsquo;feel&amp;rsquo; something, but it was unable to find out the real cause of that feeling. As a matter of fact, the function of hrd ended with the feeling. Indra, therefore, brought into action his other psy chological faculty, pamely, manas. His manas investigated into the nature of the feeling which arose in his hrd and supplied, so to say, the answer to the query of hrd: manas cin me hrda a pratyavocad acıkradan chi sumantah sakhayah. It is manas which, on account of its main function of positive thinking, completes the whole psychological process by supplementing the psychologi cal experience of hrd. Thereafter follows the &amp;lsquo;doing&amp;rsquo;, namely, Indra&amp;rsquo;s appearance before his devotees. This passage is remark able also from another point of view. It throws considerable light on the Vedic thinker&amp;rsquo;s conception of the three most primary phases of human action, namely, feeling, knowing, and doing.&#xA;A similar functional distinction between the two human faculties, hrd and manas, seems to be suggested in a passage from AV (VI. 73. 2), where the poet refers to hrdaya as the seat of&#xA;vehement feelings in contrast to manas which is supposed to be the seat of conscious designs&amp;rsquo;:30 vah fusnio hrdayesy anlar akūtir jā jo manasi pravistā. The twofold conception of Vedic poetry, firstly as an outburst of the exuberance of feelings directly springing from hrd, and secondly as a conscious artistic effort, in the manner of a taksā, an artisan, to put the best words in the best order, often connected with manas, also make the distinc tion between the nature and functions of hard and manas quite clear. Such primary analysis of psychological functions is not an uncommon phenomenon in the Veda (cf. RV I. 61. 2; X. 10. 13; 123. 6).&#xA;Finally, we fiad in the Veda the beginnings of the later view regarding the relation between hird and manas. In AV XIX. 9.5, hrd is clearly referred to as the abode of manas and other indriyas. The reference is important from two points of vicw. Firstly, it appears from this reference that in later Veda manas came to be regarded as one of the indriyas, though still the most essential, that is to say, mcrcly as one of the several constituents of the&#xA;HRD İN THB VEDA&#xA;261&#xA;human personality;12 and, secondly, hrd gradually came to lose its essentially psychological import.&#xA;[First published : Siddheshwar Varma Presentation Vol, 1950, 137–142.)&#xA;12. At one stage in the desclopment of the Vedic conception regarding the human personality, manas seemed to indicate almost the entire human personality. Scc DANDERAR, Der vedische Mensch, pp. 44 ff.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>INDEX</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/word-INDEX/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/word-INDEX/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;arrya 5&#xA;Aalto, Pentti 49n.&#xA;ahamkāra 138, 138n. abhıcārila 83, 158n,&#xA;Ahavaniya (fire) 70, 203 Abhidhamma 251,&#xA;Ahura Mazdah 39, 77, 173, 187, Abbiras 287, 298&#xA;187n, 207, 2070, 224 Abhyavartın 190 Abıyard 190&#xA;Artareya Aranyaka 75n abstract divinities 208&#xA;Antareya-Brāhmaṇa 104, 1430, acara 348&#xA;1440, 146, 149, 1500, 169, 177n, accent 12, 69&#xA;351, activisation 334&#xA;Aitihasikas 235 activistic 336&#xA;aja 136 Adbhuta-Brāhmaṇa 176n&#xA;Ajamidha 1910 Adbhuadhyaya 176n&#xA;Ajas 234, adevism 184n&#xA;aj: 199, 243n Adhvaryu 109, 110, 110, 158, ajya 199&#xA;159.&#xA;akasa 138n. Aditi 173, 181, 182, 184, 187, akhyanas (akhyana theory ) 155,&#xA;1876, 202, 205n, 218n, 222, 229, 155n, 156, 217 229n, 2 0, 233, 240&#xA;Akkadian( 9 ) 15-17, 207, 208 Aditya[ ) 129, 134, 173, 195, alamkaras 242&#xA;207, 213, 222, 229n,&#xA;Alberuni 330 administration of justice 356. Alekseyev, V P450, advarta 319, 343&#xA;Alexander (the Great) 59-62, Aegis 216&#xA;325-328, 353 aesthetic penchant 67, 314, 329 Alexandria 60, 62, 63 Agastya 99, 105, 1050, 107-109, alig vrliga 50&#xA;109, 110, 111, 159, 190, 217 ell Iudia services 333 Agni 120, 120n, 144n, 145, 1587, aloofpess 317.&#xA;170, 178, 182, 183, 1940, 1950, Alpine (race) 7. 198, 200, 203, 203n, 213, 216, Alsdorf, L 1560. 222, 223, 223, 2240, 241n, Altaic (coltare, people ) 16, 17a 244, 255, 258.&#xA;Altekar, A S 3, 58n Agnicayana 1330, 210&#xA;Amaracandra Suri 307. agrarian economy 333,&#xA;Amenophus III 51&#xA;INDEX&#xA;361,&#xA;Atharraveda Parisista 159, atharyu 158n, atheism 184, Athena Tritonis 216 Athens 60. atmañana 284-286.&#xA;Ātman 216 atomism 339. Atrı 83n attachinent 317. attitude of blind acceptance 3. attitude of critical inquiry 344 Audhomla 139n. Aufrecht, T, 177, 177, 178, 188. Apgustus 63. austerities 338. Austin 150 Austric 243. Austro Asiatic 227, 228, 230, 232,&#xA;233.&#xA;aga 77. asal 342 asceticism 317, 338 Asharagata 190. Asian home theory 21n. Asiatic Mediterranean ( race) 7. Asoka 62, 271, 354, 355. asrama( 8 ) 347, 348n, 350, asramadharma 345, 347, äsranı 251. ase 185, Assyrian 15, 32 āstila 73 Astronomical evidence 8n, 9 astronomy 330 asu 246, 319.&#xA;Asura (asura ) 146, 162, 182, 228,&#xA;229n, 232, 248. Asura Varuṇa 213, 340, Aśraliyana 274. Astalāyana Grhyasūtra 274 asramedha 355, Asvins ( Asvinan) 146, 174, 176,&#xA;177, 181, 185, 187, 1870, 209, 209n, 214, 214n, 215, 220, 222, 227, 229, 230, 233, 235, 238,&#xA;2410, 2730. athar 158D. Atharvan(8) 119, 1440, 157,&#xA;3577, 158, 158, 160, 160n, 161,&#xA;162, 161-168, 225n Atharta reda 50, 53, 82, 83, 1130.&#xA;119, 133, 133n, 134, 134, 135. 136, 140, 143, 1440, 151, 156_ 158, 158n, 159, 159, 160, 160n, 1610, 163, 173n, 180. 1910, 204, 213, 218, 229, 241, 248, 250, 253, 255, 238, 260, 34?, 349, 350&#xA;46&#xA;23&#xA;avabhrtha 204 avataras 241n, 289,&#xA;Avesta 37, 38, 76, 78n, 201, 210n,&#xA;231 Avestan (Aryans, mythology )&#xA;207n, 211, 2590 babhru 52.&#xA;Babylon 191n, 324. Babylonians 49, 207. Bactrian 62 Bactrian Greeks 329 Bactrian language 190n bahulrihi 70,&#xA;Balabharata 306, 307. balı 146, 338 Balkh (region) 25, 26, 36-3v, 24&#xA;43, 55, 56, 76, 78, 78n, 79, 80,&#xA;94, 340 ballad 99, 101, 156,&#xA;362&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;Baltic plain 23, 41 Baltic Sea 19n Bapa 219 bandhu 167 bandhuta 343 Banerjea, A, C 128n Banerjee, N R 610 barasman 236, 243D Barnett L D 224n, 235n Barofsanes 65 Barth, A 196, 197, 197, 199,&#xA;267, 267n, 294 baru ( bharu ) 228 battle-axe 11, 13, 22 Battle of ten kings see Daśarafia Baukis 191 Becker 312 beech ( beech-argument) 14n, 19,&#xA;191 beeg 18, 182, 19 Begram 63 Bender 19n Benfey 170, 171, 181, 1820 Bengal 304_307 Benvenuste, E 52n, 2410 Bergaigne, A 178, 191, 192, 1920,&#xA;193, 1931, 194, 1949, 195, 195n, 196, 196, 197, 200, 205,&#xA;212, 241 Berliner comparative mythology&#xA;222 Bhaga 182 Bhagavadgita 119n, 267, 268, 287&#xA;289, 291, 299, 335 Bhagavan Krsna 289 Bhagavatas 267, 268, bhavsaja 83, 158n, bhakta 114, 115, 119, 120 Bhaktı 114, 116, 120-122, 160,&#xA;161, 167, 216, 237, 286, 334&#xA;Bhal, nases 96 Bhandarkar Oriental Research&#xA;Institute 302, 303 Bhandarkar, R, G 302 Bhāl a radvajals) 57, 83n, 95 Bharata 273n, 274, 276, 282, 283,&#xA;286-289, 297-300 Bharatabharadvipa 307&#xA;Bharatam (Javanese ) 306 Bharalamafijart 306. Bharatartapı adipika 307 Bharatarthaprakaska 307 Bharatas (Bharata) 11a, 84,&#xA;85, 94-96, 100, 113, 275, 279,&#xA;280, 281o, 282, 295, 297 Bharata varsa 85, 96. Bharata var 281, 290, 295, 296, Bhargavarama 290, 291 Bhargavas 290, 291 Bhat, G K 1560, Bhattabhaskara 133n, 134n. bhaujya 143n Bhawe, S S 155 Bheda 96 bheda 281, 296, Bhima 240 Bhisma 117n, 240n, 269, 273n&#xA;349 Bhrgu 83, 238, 291. Bhiguisation 291, Burgukaccha 325, Bhrgusamhita 291, Bhujya 176 bhusalı 242 Biardeau, M 276n Bibby, G 480 Brble 73, 185 Bindugera 62 birch 19, 190, Black Sea 18&#xA;INDEX&#xA;363&#xA;blondes 7, 12&#xA;Brahmo Samaj 334 Bloomfield, M, 143n, 214, 2140, Brandenstein 15n, 200, 21n.&#xA;215, 216, 231&#xA;brh 174 Bogdanov 22&#xA;Brhadaranyaha Upanisad 149 Boghaz Kör (Boghazhoi ) 34-36, Brhaddezala 99, 104n, 1050, 175n,&#xA;50, 51, 55, 221, 222&#xA;Brhaspati 202, 203, 203n, 208, Bogu 182&#xA;2080, 213, 224, 341 Bohlen (von ) 170, 178n.&#xA;Brough, J, 238n Bollensen, F 189&#xA;Brunbild 176 &amp;ldquo;Book&amp;rdquo; 319n&#xA;Brandhofer, H, 189, 190, 190n, Bopp, F 4, 170, 171&#xA;191, 191n Bosch-Gimpera, P 24n&#xA;Buchanan, B 49 brachycephalic 6, 7, 12,29, 46. Buddha 62, 65, 66, 67n, 91, 329, Bradke, P. von 187a, 2010&#xA;339, 355 Brahmā 271, 273, 291.&#xA;Buddha Religion 173 Brahmacarıd(s) 2360, 339. Buddhism 67n, 91, 270, 271, 273, Brahman (brahman) 107, 110, 327, 339, 344, 352, 354, 355&#xA;111, 113n, 135-137, 142n, 149, Buddhist paychology 251 150, 157, 1581, 159, 159n, 174, bureaucracy 333, 354 182, 188, 202, 210, 223, 233, bureaucratic machinery 328. 236, 238, 239, 239n, 243, 284, Burnham, R E 160. 289, 327&#xA;Burnouf, Eugène 171, 174, 178, Brahmadas 202, 239, 272, 327 178n. Brāhmaṇa( 8 ) 86–89, 1137, 141, Burnouf, Émile 178, 193&#xA;172, 184, 210n, 216, 219, 241, Burrow, T 37n 262, 279, 282, 283, 286, 292, Cacus 171 340, 343, 344, 351.&#xA;calsuh 1380 Brāhmaṇaspati 202, 208n, 341. Caland, W. 221 brahman-bricht 243n&#xA;Candragupta (Maurya ) 62, 328, Brahmanic (hierarchy, society, 353, 354&#xA;way of life and thought) 337. Candramas 207. 345, 352&#xA;capitalism 67n Brahmanism 197. 199. 263. 270_ Cappier, N 45,&#xA;272, 283, 288, 289, 292, 299. Carnoy, A 180 300, 337, 344, 345, 352, 354,&#xA;Carvakas 251. 355&#xA;Caspian Sea 190 Brahma-Religion 173&#xA;castes 347 Brahmaveda 158, 158n&#xA;caste system 7, 345, 346 Brahmodya 165,&#xA;Centauros 175, 191&#xA;361&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;Central Ann lione 281, central sob recension 305. centum 19n Cerberus 171, 177, 215. Chalder 324 Chanclogya-Ujunt acl 118n, 135n,&#xA;250 characterization 55 chariots 11 Charpentier, J 28n, 155, 235,&#xA;235n, 236, 236n, 243n Charsada 61 Chatterji, 8 K, 31n Chattı empire (archives ) 29. checks (on autocracy, monarchy)&#xA;141, 149&#xA;cornio religion 77, 79, 81, 82,&#xA;310 cosmology 341 wow fetish 203n, 218n, Cox, G. 184, 184n. cremation 6, 13. Critical Edition (of the Jaha&#xA;bharata ) 2650, 301, 302, 302a,&#xA;306, 308-310 Croll In Crossland, R A. 270 Ctesias 59, 320. Cumari 190 Cyarana 175, 177. Dadlukra (van ) 227, 2272, Dadhyan 227&#xA;INDEX&#xA;365&#xA;dasa-varqa 346 Das Gupta, KK, 630, 67n. Dasgupta, S N 138n Delitzsch, F. 33, 33n, 51, deluge 177 Demephon 2240 Denester 2240 Demetrius 325, 398 deminrge 139, Democritus 59, demoniacness 227 Derbiks 190. detachment 316 Deus Aricus 189 Deussen 2160 Deya Asura war 10n Devabodha 307 Devanagarı 303, 3030, 30-4_306, Deva religion 224. deratas 83 dharana 251 Dharma (dharma) 142n, 149,&#xA;240n 265, 289, 291, 300, 390, 327, 345, 347, 348, 3480, 355,&#xA;216 Dickinson 312 Dictionary ( Vedio) 170 diksa 210 Dilmun 49, 50, 50n Dipära 66, 329 Dinarius 329 Dionysog 171, 181 Dioscuri 176 Dipika 134 dividity of the king) 142 Diyodass 57, 191 Dixon 6, 60 dolicocephalic 5-7, 12 Donn, V 80 do ut des 194 Drachma 329 Dragon 341 diamila 324 Dramma 66, 329 Draupad: 272, 273, Dravidian 243, 324 Drbhika 190 Drona 269, 272, 273n, 290, 349 Druhyus 35, 84, 94, 96 Drupada 272 dualism (light and darkness ) 221 dualistic mythology) 195 Dumézıl, G 1040, 2310, 237, 238,&#xA;2389, 239, 239, 240, 24On,&#xA;243n, 375n, 2760 Duryodhana 1170 drapara 290 Drivedagar 1767 dwarfs 175 Dyauh 77, 130, 177, 182, 185,&#xA;1877, 188, 199, 218, 227, 2100 Draus pita 177 Dyavaprtluri 123, 124, 340&#xA;357&#xA;Dharma (god) 273n Dharmaraja 269 Dharmasastra 273, 345, 347-349,&#xA;352, 356, 358 Dharmasulral 8 ) 92, 199, 345, 352,&#xA;353, 355 dharmayuddha 269, 349 Dharnikota 64 dhatus 251 dhena 224 dhe 254 Dhrtaråstra 275, 280 dhyana 251 dialogue-lymo(s) 99, 155, 156,368&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;Helios 177, 182 hell 211n Hellenic civilization) 60, 314 Helleputac 60, 322, 325, 326, 328,&#xA;329, 354 Hencken, H 220 henotheism 183, 183n 209, 210,&#xA;215, 237, Heracltus 59&#xA;Herakleitos 224n hermaphrodite 186n, 226, 342 Hermeias (Hermes) 175, 181,&#xA;216, Hero 341 Herodotus 59, 324 Hero-religion 79, 81, 341 Heros Eremon 240 Herrenvolk 11 12 Hertel, J 155, 217n, 223, 224,&#xA;54, 55, 228n, 2297, 232. Hittite-Mitanni kingdong 59 Holtzmann, A. 269, 269n, 270&#xA;273, 294 homa 338 Home (Cradle, Urheimat) of the&#xA;Indo Europeang (Aryans ) 4, 5, 8, 8n, 13, 140, 15, 17, 18, 180, 19, 190, 20, 200, 22, 25,&#xA;26, 27n Homer 293 honey 18 Hopkins, E. W 199, 2050, 2097,&#xA;234, 276, 276n horse( 9 ) 13, 17 horse sacrifice 17 Hospitality (God) 2390 Hotr 109, 1100, 158, 159 hrd 253, 253n, 254-257, 2570,&#xA;INDEX&#xA;369&#xA;Indian culture 262. Indian ethics 320. Indianisin 336. Indian metaphysics 319, 320, * Indianness&amp;quot; 265. Indian tradition 312, 314n, 315,&#xA;332, iodigenous Indian communities&#xA;346, individualistic 336. individuality (individualism) 316. Indo-Anatolian (period) 45, Indo-Aryan(s, language, elements&#xA;53, 56, 57, Indo-British (contacts, impact,&#xA;intercourse ) 326, 330-332. Indo-European (language, langua&#xA;ges, mythology, period; Indo Germanic) 1, 3-5, 7-9, 11, 11n, 12, 13, 13, 14, 140, 169, 17, 17n, 18, 18n, 190, 200, 21, 23, 25, 33, 36, 39-41, 52, 58, 68, 69, 76, 77, 78n, 174, 175, 181, 205, 206, 208, 209, 214, 215, 217, 219, 221, 223, 224. 227. 230, 231, 235, 241, 246, 247.&#xA;253, 259, 2590, 324. Indo-Hellenistic (period) 45, 66, Indo-Iranian (also see Aryan)&#xA;208, 222n, 240. Indo-Mediterranean (contacts)&#xA;154, 170, 181-184, 186, 186n, 187n, 189, 190, 194, 195, 1950, 200, 202, 208, 2080, 212, 215, 217, 223, 224, 229n, 233, 235, 236, 238, 240, 2400, 241, 2410, 243, 248, 256, 259, 260, 263,&#xA;2730, 292, 338, 341. Indra- (cult, religion ) lin, 391,&#xA;113, 121, 123, 130, 132, 160. indrafalra: 70. Indra-Varuṇa (Indrāvarunau )&#xA;113, 122, 122, 123n. indriyanām prāpyakārtā 249. indriyas 249, 260. Indus (people, region) 47, 50,&#xA;64, 190, 191, industrial revolution 333. Indus valley civilization (also see&#xA;Harappa) 10, 46, 241, 323,&#xA;338. intellectualısın (intellectualistic)&#xA;318, 319, 336. intercourse (India and the West)&#xA;321, 326, 3261, 328. interpretation 308. interregnum 91, 92. interstatal relations 353. inversion 270. Ipsen 16n, 20. Iran (Iraniang, Iranian Aryang )&#xA;5, 10n, 35, 36, 38, 77, 187n,&#xA;189, 340. iron 61. Islam (Islamic tradition) 312,&#xA;321n. isolated migration 26, 40, 54. ista-deuren 115, 2270, 237. kvara 139, ilihusa-gruerana 3, 73, 278.&#xA;Indo-Mesopotamian (period) 45. Indo-Roman (period, commerce,&#xA;trade) 45, 63, 67n, Indra 11n. 31, 42, 51, 56, 69, 70,&#xA;79, 80, 96, 98, 99, 99n, 114, 120n, 123-127, 129, 130n. 131. 134n, 141, 143, 1440, 147, 148,&#xA;46&#xA;370&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;Jackson 2340 Jacobi, H 35, 350 Jagat 136 Jazmini 300 Jarmıniya Brāhmaṇa 97 Jainism 339, 344 Janamejaya 309 Jaritz, K 60n Jalaka: 269 Jåtayeda 159n, 163 Jatavedas 163, 164 JĀtavidyā 159n, 163 jati( 8 ) 109n, 346 jati vyavastha 346&#xA;harmayoga 285, 286 larmendi iya, 138 Karm 269, 373n 290, 349. Károti 190 Kashmiri 303n, 305 309 Kassites 33, 34, 318, 35-38, 43, 51 hathaka Sarıhıta 97, 1090 Katyayana 98 halya jana-Srautasulra 1761 Kauravas 267, 268, 270 272, 2730,&#xA;280, 281, 294 296, 319 hauska Sutra 133, 1440, 1510,&#xA;157, 176 hausitaki Upanisad 97, 109&#xA;INDEX&#xA;22&#xA;Korybantıs 2171 Kosala.Videha 177. Kossina, G. 11, 120. krama patha 75, 750. Kramer, S. N. 49, 50n, Krause, W. 6n, Kretschmer, P. 228, 228n, 229n,&#xA;232. Kronos 238, Krsna 119n, 240, 240n, 268, 269,&#xA;271-273, 273n, 281-288, 2880,&#xA;289, 298, 299, 319. Krspá 275. Krspasm 271, 2730, 286-289,&#xA;298–300. Krsna lajurveda 88 Krama 10n. Kṣatra 149, 150, 327. Ksatriya code of conduct 267. Ksatriyals) 216, 267, 268, 258,&#xA;290, 327.&#xA;lākså 14n, 15n.&#xA;Lakálamkāra 307. Laksmana 185. Laksmi 65, Lal, B. B, 640. land of seven rivers see Sapta&#xA;sindhu. Lanká 186. Lassen, C. 176, 274 274n. La Vallée Poussin, L. de 217,&#xA;218, 2181, 232. law 142, 333. lectro difficilior 308. lectio facilior 308. Leemans, W. F. 481, 49a, leptorrhynian 5, 12, Lév, S. 155, 2170, 267, 2670,&#xA;294, liberalisation 331. Lithuanian 19n. logical development 310.&#xA;572&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;madhukasa 220, 2291,&#xA;manasaspatt 248, Madhyadeśa 272.&#xA;manasyu 248. Mādhyamdina 176n.&#xA;manasvan 248, Madri 273n.&#xA;mandala( 8 ) 83, 83n, 97, 98, 98n. Magadban thought-complex. 339. Manlūka-Sūkta 242. magic 81, 82, 84, 210n.&#xA;Mandũkeya. 234n. magical bondage and release 222, manīsā 254 magico-religious 242.&#xA;Mann, S. E 23, 23n, 27n, Mahabharata 3, 141, 141n, 1420, Mannhardt 204n, 209.&#xA;170, 263-270, 272 275, 275n, mantra( 8 ) 35, 37, 38, 41, 69, 71, 276, 281n, 289-291, 293, 294, 75, 77 83, 87, 243n, 256, 340, 300 302, 302n, 303 310, 349, 341. 355.&#xA;Mantra (=Samhita ) 241.&#xA;INDEX&#xA;373&#xA;Max Muller, F. 13n, 87, 87n, 171, Mitanni-Hittite treaty 53.&#xA;1710, 1777, 178, 178n, 179, mixed castes 347. 179n, 180, 180n, 181, 18lo, 182, mleccha 49p. 182n, 183, 183n, 181, 184n, Mohenjodaro 45, 46, 48, 50.&#xA;186-188, 192, 209, 213n, 225n. mokī 191. māyā 139, 188, 222, 243&#xA;inolṣa 266, 285, 286, 347. Mayrhofer, M. 15n, 52a.&#xA;monarchic absolatism 328. Mazda yasnians 225,&#xA;monarchy 150. Mazzini 335,&#xA;monkeys 186. Mecaulay 331,&#xA;monotheism 183n, 164. Mechanical (technological) pen- Moon 202, 203, 207-209, 213, 216,&#xA;chant 314,&#xA;235. mechanical sacerdotalism 313. moon.mythology (&amp;ldquo;mythologist) Mediterranean race (stock, 222, 223.&#xA;world) 29, 45-47, 61,&#xA;morality 195. Megasthenes 62.&#xA;morning star 209, 214n. Meillet 2390,&#xA;Diother-Goddess 14, 50. Melahha 49.&#xA;mounds 22. Menander 328,&#xA;movement of manas ) 249. mendicancy 338.&#xA;Muir, J. 1610, 186, 186n, 187, Mesopotamia 15, 16, 48.&#xA;1870, 188, 2110, Mesopotamian(s) 46, 47, 49,50. Mūjavat 38, 780, meteorological phenomena 192. Mukherjee, B. N. 63n. Meyer, E. 280, 233n,&#xA;Munis 339. milakkha 49n.&#xA;Muni.Yati-tradition 338. Jilindamastha 63&#xA;Mursitis I 31. Mill 335.&#xA;Myriantheus 187n, mind 247, 248, 248n.&#xA;mysticism 316. Minoan Crete 50.&#xA;mythologisation ( of history ) 341, missionaries (to Greek kings )&#xA;Nadi-Siikta 10n, 11n. Mithra 207, 225.&#xA;Nabus 190. Mitra 34, 51, 126, 127. 129. 129n. naksatraśaras 225.&#xA;146, 189, 207, 222, 232, 235 Naktā 182,&#xA;237, 239, 239, 2100. 341 Nana 229n. Nitra-Varuṇa MGtråvarnau Nanai 229n.&#xA;103, 104, 104, 105.107. 109, Nandaya 306,&#xA;naga 190. Mitandi( , Mitannian) 32. 34 38. mārāśamsīs 279, 295.&#xA;42, 43, 51-56,&#xA;Nārāyana 134, 142n,&#xA;168.&#xA;376&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;prakrtı 136, 136n, 137, 138, 138n, prakritismy 69. pramana 72 Pramantha 182 prasada 251 prasar 2430 Pratrealhya (Rgveda ) 172. pralistha 243 Pratrds 109, 111, 159 pratyalsa 72, 318 pravritı 251 Prayadiya isti 1440 prayascitta 348.&#xA;prśno 121, 136, 136n, 137, 139,&#xA;139n, 162 pretha 199 prthrv: 138n, 199 Prthoparśavah 190 Przylaski, J 227 229, 2290, 230,&#xA;230, 232, 233 Ptolemaic ( empire) 62, public administration 333 prua 338 punarmagha 162, 166. Puranas 3 Purandara 39, 42&#xA;INDEX&#xA;377&#xA;1610, 163 165, 167, 169 174, 174n, 176, 177, 1770, 178, 180, 182 185, 188 191, 191n, 192, 192n, 195, 196, 196n, 197, 198, 198n, 199, 201 203, 2041, 205, 205n, 208, 203n, 209, 210, 211n, 212-216, 217, 218, 218n, 219, 219n, 220, 221, 223 225, 227, 231 234, 237, 239n, 240, 241 243, 243n, 248 250, 253, 253n, 254,&#xA;259, 341, 342, 345, 346, 351 Ridgeway 155, 155n. Ripley, W F 6 ritual drama 155, 217 ritualism (brahmanıc) 90, 285,&#xA;286&#xA;rajyavināśa 281, 296 Rama 185, 186 Rama Bliergava see Bhargava&#xA;rama Ramakrishna M 18910n 335 Ramachandran, KS 280n Ramayana 3, 186 Rao, S. R 48n rasa 1380 rasana 1380 rastra 144 Rathakaras 236 rationalisation 334 Råvı 96 Rawlinson, H. G 58, 59n Rbhas 174, 174n, 175, 182, 235,&#xA;236 Red god 338 Red Sea 64 Regnaud, P 197, 198, 198n, 199 Regnier, A 171, 174 regnum 150, 327 re integration 316 religion (the term ) 81, 82 religion (Western influence on&#xA;Indian ) 334 religio philosophical culture 313,&#xA;313n. religious penchant 67, 314, 329. Renou, L 240, 241, 2411, 243n, renunciation 338 revivalist movement 345, 352 rex 239n Rgreda (-Samhita) 2, 110, 22,&#xA;38, 39, 41, 53, 57, 58, 75, 82, 83, 85, 95 98, 99n, 108, 109, 111. 113, 114, 1170, 119, 122, 131, 1340, 142, 152, 153, 156, 158, 1580, 159, 159 160, 1600,&#xA;rna 350 Romaka 66, 330 Roman colonies ( in South India)&#xA;64 Roman empire 325 Rome 63 Rosen, F 171, 1720 177n Rostovzeff 328 Rousseau 335 Roth R 134n, 160n, 162, 171,&#xA;172, 172n, 173, 173n, 174 176, 1771, 178n, 186n, 187, 1870, 188, 189, 192, 196, 197, 211n,&#xA;213n, 219, 219n Rsihood 161 1 R819 71 Rsi tradition 338 Rta 38, 77, 129 131, 182, 188,&#xA;196 218 222, 236, 237, 319,&#xA;319n, 320, 340 Rtagmara 34 Rudra 101, Rudra 181, 185, 20 209, 210,&#xA;214, 218, 226, 227, 3410, 338,&#xA;$80&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;Sol 177&#xA;stateless society 142 solarization 341&#xA;state of nature 141, 142 solar phenomena 192&#xA;states (types of ) 351 Solomon 68&#xA;Stein 328 Soma (cult, sacrifice, plant, pri slemma codicum 305&#xA;ests ) 38, 70, 78, 780, 79, 81, Stevenson 1720 830, 1430, 158, 194n, 195, sloma 257 1950, 198, 200, 203, 203n, 209, Strabo 62 210, 213, 215, 224, 230, 241n, struggle for independence 335 253, 257, 340&#xA;Sturtevant 29 somatism (somatic) 248, 251, 252 Subandhu 34. Sommer, F 280, 29, 30n&#xA;aubeastes 347 Sonne, w 176&#xA;subordination 315, 3150 Sorensen, S 267, 2670, 294 Sudas 84, 85, 94 96, 113, 186 Sorley 4 T 42&#xA;Sudra(s) , 149 tound-shift 12.&#xA;Saka 300 South East Asia 331&#xA;Sukra 291 Southera recension 304-309 Sukranını 1410, 356, 357, 3577 South European (race 7 Sumantu 300 South India 64, 324, 350 Sumerian( 9 ) 16, 17, 46, 50,2940 South Russian home 240&#xA;Sun god, worship) 170, 1942&#xA;i&#xA;ÍNDEN&#xA;381&#xA;198&#xA;Sūtra-Vedanga (period) 92, 283,&#xA;288, 299, 345. svara 69 svastika 36. Svetāśvalara-Upant:ad 136, 136n. symbolic magic 194 Syris-Crete 50 Szemereny, 0 52n&#xA;mälz 50 Taittirīya Aranyaka 133. Taillirīya-Brāhmana 141n, 1590,&#xA;351, Taittirīya samhrtā 70n, 1020,&#xA;11la, 1200, 159n, 160, 176n, Taittiriya Upanisad 135n laksā 256, 260&#xA;Tanais 229n tamas 136 Tāndyal -elahā)-Brähmana 97,&#xA;351. fanmälrāni 138, 138n. Tantra 241, lapas 317. Taraporewala, I J, S Sn.&#xA;theological&amp;rsquo; mind 141, theopanism 237 thickening (of manas ) 250. Thieme, P. 75, 140, 53n, 2380,&#xA;239n, 243n. Thomas, H, 27n. Thoreau 335. Thracophrygian area 222n. three classes of gods 199. Tiglat-Pileser IV of Assyria 7. Tilak 80, 9n. Tilmpo see Dilman, Tirthamkaras 339. Tiruvalluvar 357. Tistrya 225. Tocharian dialect 27. tolerance 314, 335. Tolstoy 335 Tomyrie 191. totemism 205, 2110, 215, 234 Tovar 220 Toynbee 314. trade-routes 61. training of the king) 150.382&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;Trtsus 84, 85, 95, 96, 100, 108,&#xA;109, 109n, 110, 159 Trubetzkoy 27, tryañjala 62. Tura Kåvaseya 190 Turan 189, 190, Turvaśa 84, 94, 96 tvak 138n Traṣtr 69, 70, 208, 236 tveganrmre 162 Tveṣaratha (tresaratha) 34, 63n, twaddle (theological) 87. twilight (morning) 214. Tylor 2041 Ubaidians 46, Udgatr 109, 110n, 158, 159, Ugraśrayas 290 Ugro-Finnio 16, 16n. Uktbs( 8 ) 109, 110, 159. * unchanging East&amp;rdquo; 321, unitarian (conception of mytho&#xA;logy) 195. unity of logical development) 74 universalisation 334 universe 81. universities 332 Upanisad( 8 ) 89.92, 135, 140, 184,&#xA;214, 216, 241, 262, 282-284, 286,&#xA;292, 340, 344, 349-352, 354 Upanisad-period 89 upastha 138n&#xA;purustlo 133n. Ur 48, 50 Ural Altaic region 18, 18n, 22n, urbanisation (first) 61n, urbanisation (second) 61. Urheimat 40, 54. Ur-Indo-European (Proto-IE, lan&#xA;guage, people ) 140, 15, 150,&#xA;160, 10, 21n, 30, 31, 39, Ur Vahabhārala 305, 309. ar-monotheism 237, 237n, orns (pyxig) 47. tirugula 50. Urraś: 103, 104, 106, 107, 103,&#xA;175, 177. Ur-Veda 240. Usag 174, 175, 181, 182, 186, 191,&#xA;193, 204, 2040, 2960, 240. utsar 243, 243n, Vācaspati 138. trico matt 266 Vādırája 307, virajya 143n. Vaiśampayana 300, 309. - Vaiśeṣika 339. Vaisnavism 197, 270. Faitāna-Sülra 133n, 1447, 148,&#xA;157, Vājasaneyi samhita 153, 176n,&#xA;248 zajra 243 Vala 176, trīk 121, 138n, 161, 182, Vamadeva 830, 177. Varahamıhıra 65, 330. ! Varcin 190 varna(8) 315n, 346, 3480, varna-dharma 345 tarna-asrama-dharma 345, 356, Denne ogu otsuit 12, 345, 346, vartani 51, Varupa 34, 38. 51, 77, 114 116,&#xA;116n, 117, 117n, 118, 119, 1191, 120, 1201, 121.129, 130n, 131, 1310, 132, 144, 146, 147, 157, 158, 160 168, 170, 173, 177, 181-183, 187, 1877, 188, 189,&#xA;INDEX&#xA;383&#xA;191, 191n, 195, 197, 200, 202, 207, 208, 208n, 212, 215, 217, 218, 220, 220n, 2310, 222, 223, 220, 226, 228, 228n, 2290, 232, 233, 233n, 235 230, 239n, 248, 257, 262, 202 Varuṇa(-calt, -religion ) 11n, 39,&#xA;390, 113, 123, 123, 127, 130,&#xA;132, 160. validari 1050 Vasco de Gama 326.&#xA;agrethe (Vasıthas, Vagsthas ) 830, 84, 85 95, 96, 98, 98, 99,&#xA;99n, 100, 100, 101, 102. 101. , 105, 105, 106, 107, 107n. 103.&#xA;109, 109n, 110, 110n, 111, 113, 113, 114 116, 116, 117, 1170, 118, 1189, 119, 120, 1200, 121 125, 127, 130, 132. 158 160, 1600, 161, 163 168, 173, 186,&#xA;219, 258, 279 2444 221, Vasudeva 376 Vasudeva Krona 289, Vata 182. Vatsas 234n taty 1910&#xA;Vảyu ( câu ) 1380, 238, 240,&#xA;243, 262, 278, 283, 207, 333, 337&#xA;313, 346 l&amp;rsquo;edic Billiography 40 Vedic drama 155 Vedic exegesis 218, 219 Vedic gods 63. Vedic mythology 200, 202, 205,&#xA;206, 205, 211, 212, 215, 218&#xA;221, 2+1 Vedic period 1, 3, 41, 43 Vedic poetry 257 Vedic priests 320 Vedic psychology 250, 254 Vedic ritual (cult, sacrifice) 86,&#xA;178, 193, 195, 196, 199, 200, 201, 205, 210, 212, 221, 222, 231,&#xA;337, 241 Vedic Sanskrit (language, literar&#xA;ture, religion ) 33, 35, 36, 63,&#xA;2736.&#xA;Veda 37, 68, 71, 339 vedana 251 Vedanta 327, teda pramanya 72, 73 Vedic Aryans (Vedic Aryan,&#xA;Vedic Indians, Vedic people ) 13, 9, 10, 10, 11n, 39, 42, 57. 76, 77, 78n, 79, 80, 82. 128 130. 177, 181, 192, 196, 106, 197, 202, 2070, 208, 210, 228, 234,&#xA;Vedism 207, vegetation ritual 217, 235 Velanlar, I D 102n, 128n Veon 133, 134, 134n, 135, 136,&#xA;1390 Vendulace 8n terbum 182 Verethragna 2410 Vesta 78 Vethiadina 230 vibhulis 291 andatha 152 Vıdeglia Mláthava 177 midki 279&#xA;24 Vijnana Bhiksu 138 vihrts (of Vedic recitation) 70n Vimalabodha 307 Vinayaka 148&#xA;384&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;uiniyoga 157 Vira) 201 Virajas 1420 Vis 149 Visamastokr 307 Vysanın 96 Visby 142n, 177, 186, 194 194n,&#xA;208, 242, 226, 226n, 230, 233, 235, 240, 240n, 241, 24+ 262,&#xA;289 Vispimitra 831, 84, 85, 95, 96,&#xA;113n, 173, 186, 219 Viśparupa 69, 70 Visve Devah 103 106, 146, 181,&#xA;209 Vith 230 Vathal Vathoba 230n Vivagyat 181 Vivekananda 334 Voz 182 Vratyas 2, 233, 339 ursabha 184 Vpsakapı 217&#xA;Weidner, E F 30n Wells, H G9n Westergaard 187 Western 311. western approach 318 Yestern Asia 323, 324 western culture 332, Western sub recension 305 western tradition 314n. Wheeler, REM 42n, 610, 63,&#xA;657. whip-cord (-decorated cups,&#xA;pottery) 12, 22n Whitney, W D 44, 133, 1337,&#xA;1390, 1430, 154, 1611, 1870,&#xA;209n Wikander, S 276n Wilkın 204 Winckler, H 28, 29, 34, 51 Windisch 155 Windischmann 1870, 2130 Winn, M M 37. Winternitz, M 35, 35n, 2160,&#xA;INDEX&#xA;385&#xA;Yami 17. Yaska 171. Tasts 224, Yatis 338 YarkTag 9, 0, 65, 325, 30. Yoga 251,316, 319,323、327,&#xA;| 338, 339. Yogåcåra 251,&#xA;yoking (of manas) 249 gard 243 Zaotar 10 Zanber-Ritual 221. Zeus (Pater) 177, 182 Zimmer, H. 178n, 188, 196n Zoroastrianism 224&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>INDIAN PATTERN OF LIFE AND THOUGHT</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/INDIAN_PATTERN_OF_LIFE_AND_THOUGHT/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/INDIAN_PATTERN_OF_LIFE_AND_THOUGHT/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-glimpse-of-its-early-phases&#34;&gt;A GLIMPSE OF ITS EARLY PHASES&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is customary to regard the Veda as the starting point of the entire ancient Indian way of life and thought. A critical consideration of the question regardiog the genesis of several significant concepts and practices which had prevailed in ancient India would, however, show that they could by no means be traced back to the Veda, either ideologically or from the point of view of literary documentation. It would appear that, long before the Vedic Aryans migrated into the land of the seven rivers on their avowed mission of conquest and colonisation, a distinct socio-religious pattern had evolved in the Indian sub continent. Unfortunately do direct literary sources are now available to enlighten us on this pre-Vedic non-Aryan pattern of life and thought. But the cumulative evidence of archaeology, anthropology, ethnology, and linguistics yields a more or less vivid picture in this respect. Moreover, this pre-Vedic pattern of life and thought had extended so far and wide and had become so firmly established on the Indian soil tbat it did not fail – indeed, it could not have failed – to influence the Vedic Aryan ideology itself in an uomistakable manner. In spite of the obviously deliberate attempts on the part of the Vedic (Brahma Dic) hierarchy to suppress these intuences, it was compelled, presumably on account of sheer popular pressure, to accommo date into its own pattern of life and thought some aspects of what was to it an alien way of life and thought, albeit in a modified - in some cases vitally and substantially modified - form. It is, indeed, only on such an assumption that the Occurrence in Brahmanism of certain concepts and practices, which are obviously non-Vedic in character, can be accounted for.&#xA;By way of illustration, attention may be drawn to the Siva religion and the practices and cults associated with it. The fact&#xA;338&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;that the existence of this religion is clearly evidenced in the Indus valley civilisation is sufficient to prove its pre Vedic non Aryan provenance Indeed, it can be shown that the worship of Siva, the red” god, had spread in several parts of India long before the penetration of the Vedic Aryans in those parts - different features of the character and the cult of that god having been emphasized in different regions The Sıva religion was essentially non Vedic in character It was obviously an iconic religion, while idol worship was entirely unknown to the Veda The formal worship of this pre Vedic god consisted, among other things, in besmearing his icon with some substance (püja) and offering raw oblations (balı directly before it As against this the typical Vedic form of worship was honia, that is, offering of ablations to gads through fire – the gods themselves not beiog actually present in the form of idols and it being believed that those oblations were conveyed to them by fire who was therefore called havja vahana carrier of oblations&amp;rsquo; Further there were usually associated with the Sıva religion cults which glorified a life of repunciation, asceticism, wandering mendicancy, and severe austerities Some kind of yoga practices also seem to have figured prominently in these cults The Vedic Aryan ideal, on the other hand, was one of a materially secure and prosperous family life Similarly, the early Veda does not show any traces of joga In this connection we may indeed speak, 10 very broad terms, of two traditions – the pre Vedic non Aryan Muni Yatı tradition and the Vedic Aryan Rsi tradition The non Vedic character of the cults sponsored by the Siva religion is clearly sodicated by the antagonistic attitude, towards Yaris, of lodra, the chief god of the hieratic Vedic religion But it may be presumed that the Siva religion had been so very deeply rooted among large sections of the people that the protagonists of the hieratic Vedic religion found the pressure of that popular religion almost irresistible They were, therefore, obliged to accept, how soever reluctantly the Sıva religion and the cults associated with it The Vedic god Rudra for instance, is but an aryanised version of the proto Indian Siva It is significant that the various references to Rudra in the Vedic mythology and ritual isolat&#xA;INDIAN PATTERN OF LIFE AND THOUGHT&#xA;339&#xA;that god from the other gods of the Vedic pantheon in a very conspicuous magner, One also gets the unmistakable impression that the cults of the Vrātyas, the Munis, and the Brahmacārins, which were closely allied to the Rudra-Siva-worship, followed a way of life which was fundamentally different from that of the Vedic Aryans.&#xA;All this would indicate how very inadequate it was to seek in the Veda the only or even the main fountain-head of Indian thought as a whole, It is, indeed, possible to point to some other concepts in Indian thought, such as atomism, for which it is not possible to posit any Vedic origin. Further, a critical study of some later systems of Indian philosophy like Samkhya, Yoga, Vaiśesika, Buddhism, and Jainism would show that there existed in these systems a substratum of common concepts which were definitely not derived from the Veda but which might be traced back to a pre-Vedic Magadhan thought-complex. The traditions regarding the various lives of Gautama Buddha and the twenty three Jaina Tirthamkaras who preceded Mahavira are certainly quite significant in this connection. It would seem that the pre-Vedic current of thought with its many ramifications continued through centuries to serve as a significant source for the later Todjan thought to draw upon. The Vedic Aryan current of thought, which was, in a sense, foreign to the Indian soil, never succeeded - indeed it could not have succeeded - in superseding it completely. As a matter of fact, a large number of elements in the classical Hindu way of life and thought clearly betray a pre-Vedic non-Aryan origin. From this point of view, the Aryan Vedism may be regarded as a graod interlude in the continuity of ancient Indian thought.&#xA;The earliest literary manifestations of Indian thought are, however, to be found in the Veda. It should be remembered that the Veda, in respect of whose creation tradition denies the operation of any human agency, is not one single book. It has been very aptiy described as a whole library and literature. Its extent in point of the authorship, of the geography and chronology of composition, and of the form and contents is, indeed, vast. But&#xA;340&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;a critical student would notice that, in spite of its vastness and variety, there runs through the Veda a thread of logical develop ment which invests it with some kind of unity. From the point of view of literary form and contents, this literature, which is usually called the Veda, is broadly divided into three classes, the Samhitā, the Brāhmaṇa, and the Upanisad. These three classes also correspond to the three successive periods in the history of the Vedic literature and culture - each succeeding literary period being logically and historically the natural - indeed, the inc vitable - outcome of the preceding period. Long before they entered India, the Vedic Aryans, who had been living in the region round about Balkh together with their Iranian and Anatolian brethren, must have started producing prayers (mantras ) relating to their religion. The character of this religion was determined by the kind of life they had been living. At that early stage of their cultural history, the Vedic Aryans lived close to nature - as a part of it rather than apart from it. It was, therefore, the vastness and brilliance of oature, its blessings and maledictions, and, above all, the inexorable and subtly operating law which regulated all its manifestations, that dominated their religious ideology. The earliest mantras of the Vedic Aryans accordingly pertained to this cosmic religion, to which they gave expression through such mythological concepts as those of the divine parents, Dyāvā-Prthivi, the cosmic law, Ria, and the sustainer of that law, Asura Varuṇa Side by side with this cosmic religion, the Vedic Aryans had also developed a kind of simple fire-worship and elementary Soma-cult. The cosmic religion of the Vedic Aryans tended towards anthropo morphism but it was not idolatrous. Fire was, therefore, regarded as the liaison between gods and men.&#xA;la coursc of time, there occurred a distinct change in the condition of life of the Vedic Aryans and consequently in their religious ideology. They set out towards India on campaigns of conquest and colonisation, fought, on their way, a series of batiles with several antagonistic tribes whom they collectively called Disas and Výtras, and anally emerged as victorious&#xA;INDIAN PATTERN OF LIFE AND THOUGHT&#xA;341&#xA;colonisers of that part of India which was known as the land of the seven rivers. In this epoch-making warlike enterprise the Vedic Aryans were led by their heroic leader, Indra, whom they soon made into a god. The individual was gradually institutiona lised, and history came to be transformed into mythology. In this process of the mythologisation of history, several elements derived from the ancient primitive myth of the Hero and the Dragon were made use of. And later, as was but to be expected, the Vedic Aryan war-god also came to be invested with a cosmic character. Naturally enough, this hero-religion superseded the earlier cosmic religion almost completely, and consequently dominated the first regular collection of mantras, made by the Vedic poets and priests on the Indian soil, namely, the Rgveda,&#xA;Perbaps with a view to counteracting the growing influence of this essentially warlıke religion, which glorified military prowess, the Vedic poets and priests deified, in the form of Bphaspati-Brabmanaspati, who is in many respects modelled after Indra, the magical potency of their prayers and priestcraft.&#xA;Sun-worship, which also figures prominently in the Veda, is, in a sense, just an aspect of fire-worship. But a critical study of the Vedic mythology would also show that it had greatly influenced many a mythological concept sa the Veda with the result that dividities, which had originally nothing to do with the solar phenomena, came to be regarded as sun-gods at some stage in the evolution of their personality and character. For instance, Viṣou, who had originally belonged to a popular religious cult but who was later elevated to the hieratic Vedic pantheon through the process of the hierarchisation of popular divinities, belongs to this category. Savitr, Mitra, and Püsan are other gods who have been subjected to the process of the solarisation of the originally non-solar divinities.&#xA;The religious speculations of the early Vedic Aryans manifest ed themselves mainly in two forms-mythology and cosmology, Like many other primitive communities, the Vedic Aryans believed that the creation of the universe and the procreation&#xA;342&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;of the human race were the result of a primeval sacrifice which was of the nature of the self immolation of a cosmic being This cosmic being is represented in the Rgieda as the hermaphrodite god man, Yama, or as the Virāt Purusa Apart from this concept of the primevat cosmic sacrifice as the starting point of creation, there are represepted jo the Rgveda two other significant currents of cosmological thought According to one of them, the source of all powers and existences, divide as well as earthly, was conceived as the &amp;lsquo;golden germ&amp;rsquo; - a form assumed by an unnamed ur god This golden germ is obviously the precursor of the golden egg of the later cosmogony The other cosmogonic theory is far more profound It seeks to controvert the generally prevalent view that the world has evolved out of &amp;lsquo;gon betog&amp;rsquo; or asat At the same time, this theory asserts that the source of this world cannot be, strictly speaking, characterised as being&amp;rsquo; or sat in the beginning there was a certain unapparent condition which, on account of the absence of distinctness, was not an *entity, and which, on account of its being the instrument of the creation of the world, could not also be regarded as a * D01 entity&amp;rsquo; Besides these cosmogonic theories, one comes across, even in the early Veda, other theosophic speculations regarding the problem of reality.&#xA;Side by side with the mythology, the cosmogony, the theo sophy, and the ritual of the classes&amp;rsquo; among the Vedic Aryans, which were embodied mainly in the Rgveda, there had also existed what may be called the religion of the masses&amp;rsquo; This religion, mainly represented in the Atharvayeda, comprised a variety of charms, imprecations, and exorcistic practices which were primarily intended to appease, to bless, and to curse. The motif recurring throughout this religion was, of course, magic&#xA;It would be seen that, in the first period of the cultural history of the Vedic Aryans as reflected in the Samhitās of the Rgseda and the Atharsaneda, the religious practices of the Vedic Aryans, in contrast with the manifold character of their religious thought, had been few and quite simple This was, indeed, in full conformity with their nomadic way of life When, how&amp;rsquo;&#xA;INDIAN PATTERN OF LIFE AND THOUGHT&#xA;343&#xA;ever, they settled down and began to experience a sense of security and prosperity, their religion, naturally enough, tended to become increasingly complex, Out of a primitive form of ritual, which the Vedic Indians, like any other ancient commu nity, had already known, they now developed a very elaborate system of sacrifice. As a consequence of this, there arose, of necessity, a new class of priests who alone could master the many and highly complicated details of the sacrificial procedure and who indulged with great avidity in discussing those details, often in a hair-splitting maqner, in the Brāhmaṇa texts which they produced for that purpose. And, perhaps with a view to maintaining their hold over the contemporary religious thought and practices, these priests continued to load the ritual with still more details. They insisted on a scrupulous observance of all those details, so much so that such observance, iostead of being a means to an end, came to be looked upon as the end in itself. It must, however, be pointed out that the Brabmanic system of sacrifice did make a certain distinct contribution to the specula tive wisdom of India - though in an incidental manner. For instance, it sought to discover all kinds of symbolic tres or mystic bonds, bandhutā, between the various details of the sacrifice on the one hand and the different aspects of the cosmos on the other, and thereby tried to establish a kind of magico. ritualistic advaita. It also helped the growth of many sciences, such as phonetics, grammar, etymology, astronomy, etc., though the Brahmapic lucubrations in these fields can at best be described as pre-scientific science.&amp;rsquo;&#xA;The mechanical sacerdotalism evolved by the Brahmanic priests and represented in the Brāhmanas had its expected reaction. Some sections of the non-priestly classes, which had been reduced to the position of mere passive instruments in the hands of the priests, and the free-thinkers among the priests themselves, now began to question the efficacy of sacrifice as a means for attaining the true spiritual goal, as also to doubt the absolute authority of the scriptures which were pressed into service, often by circumvention, in order to establish that efficacy,344&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;The new shift, which was clearly reflected in the Upapisads, was from an attitude of blind acceptance to that of critical inquiry, from externalism to essentialism, from priestly exclusive ness to equality and freedom in the religio philosophical quest The Upanisadıc thinkers looked outwards&amp;rsquo; and inwards&amp;rsquo;, and, through an analysis of the macrocosm and the microcosm, tried to discover the ultimate reality underlying them. They finally arrived at the grand concept that the ultimate reality underlying the apparent manifoldness in the world was one and permanent, whule the phenomenal world itself was merely a bundle of fleeting names and forms Through ignorance, man forgets his real nature, gets involved in the phenomenal world, and, as the result of the inexorable law of karman, continues to live through the transmigratory existences until he realises the identity of his true self with the ultimate reality and thereby becomes spiritually emancipated,&#xA;Though the teachings of the Upanisads have dominated Indian philosophical thought as a whole most profoundly, their immediate iniluence cannot be said to have been commensurate with their essentially radical character For one thing. on account of its peculiar mysticism, the philosophy of the Upa niṣads could not be easily comprehended by people at large It, therefore, necessarily represented a way of life and thought intended only for the select few Again, the Upanisadıc thinkers succeeded to a certain extent in dislodging the earlier religions of the Samhitas and the Brābmanas, but they, as it were, left the people in the lurch by their failure to substitute any new religion of their own They apparently did not realise that people could live without a philosophy but that they could never live without a religion The gap thus created by the Upanisads in the religious life of the people was filled in, more than adequately, by such religious movements as Buddhism and Jainism This naturally mcant a serious set back to the old Brahmanism In order, there fore, to counteract this onslaught of the non-Brahmadic religions, the rear guards of the old Brahmanism started a comprehensive movement to consolidate, reorganise, and revitalise the BrahmiDIC&#xA;INDIAN PATTERN OF LIFE AND THOUGHT&#xA;345&#xA;way of life and thought This revivalist movement in what might be called the Sutra Vedanga period touched all spheres of human life - religious, academic, domestic and social Indeed, it was then that, for the first time, conscious efforts were made to evolve a definite pattern of Brahmanic society This social aspect of Brahmanism is best represented in the Grhya Sutras and the Dharma Sutras and the later Smçtıs and other texts relating to the Dharma-sastra&#xA;One of the concepts which was elaborated and emphasised at this stage, in a special mapper, was that of dharma The word dharina has been used in most of the Brahmadic texts from the Rgveda downwards, and in different contexts, it has denoted different ideas, such as Vedic ritual, ethical conduct, caste rules, and civil and criminal law Actually, however, the concept of dharma is all comprehensive and may be, broadly speaking said to comprise precepts which aim at securing the material and the spiritual sustenance and growth of the individual and the society. Another significant characteristic of dharma, which deserves to be specially noted, is that it has always been regarded as sot being static The content of dharma has often changed in the changiog contexts of time, space, and environments&#xA;In spite of the essentially comprehensive character of dharma, in its most common connotation, it was limited to two principal ideals, namely, the organisation of social life through well defined and well regulated social orders (popularly known as varna dharma) and the organisation of an individuals life, within those social orders, through well coordinated stages ( = aśrama dharma) Thus, in popular parlance, dharma almost came to mean just varna-aśrama dharma&#xA;The varna vyavastha has, indeed, come to be regarded as the most essential feature of the Brahmanic society Even later Hinduism, which differs from Brahmanism in many significant respects, has scrupulously preserved this peculiar social organisa tion Though the word varpa vyavastha is generally translated as caste system, it should be remembered that, strictly speaking,&#xA;346&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;varna does not denote caste as we understand it today. Caste system is jāti-yyai asthā which no doubt represents a ramification of the original varna-vyavasthä or the system of social orders. From the early Brahmanic texts we can derive but little historical information regarding the origin and development of varnas and jātis. The aim of those texts was avowedly to glorify and defend the social organisation governed by the concepts of varnas and jātis. They, therefore, either speak of the divine origin of those social phenomena or give some mythical accounts in respect of them,&#xA;A complex social phenomenon such as the caste-system must, indeed, be presumed to be the result of the interaction of a variety of factors. The word varna (= colour, complexion) itself would indicate that one of these basic factors was racial distinction. In the Rgveda we actually come across references to the ārya-varna (= the Vedic Aryans) and the dāsa-varna (which is the name collectively given to all the racial groups other than and antagonistic to the Vedic Aryans). Another important factor was magico-ritualistic in character. The four main social orders were distinguished from one another on account of the specific roles which they were expected to play in connection with the communal sacrifice. These roles were determined by certain definite concepts of taboo, pollution, and purification, Corresponding to their roles in the ritual, these orders were assigned distinct colours, which fact also seems to have confirmed the use of the word varna with reference to them. This magico ritualistic origin of the four social orders is indirectly indicated by their mention in the Puruṣa-sūkta (RV 8.90) as the limbs of the cosmic sacrificial Purusa. Then there was the impact on the social organisation of the Vedic Aryans of the pattern of social life which had been already evolved by the indigenous Indian communities; and this impact must have been responsible for the consolidation of yarna in the form of the social phenomenon which, in course of time, came to be designated as jäti or caste. In the initial stages, the varņas of social orders were more or less Quid and elastic. But, 10 course of time, they hardened into a&#xA;INDIAN PATTERN OF LIFE AND THOUGHT&#xA;347&#xA;rigid social system characterised by a large number of castes, sub castes, and mixed castes Elaborate discussions occur in the Dharma sastra texts regarding their respective duties and religious, social, and legal privileges and disabilities&#xA;Within these social orders (or castes ), an individual&amp;rsquo;s life was organised into four distinct stages, called asramas, in such a manner that the individual should be enabled to realise, through a properly graded scheme, the four ends of life, namely, kama or aesthetic expression of natural instincts, artha or material prosperity, dharma or ethical conduct, and moksa or spiritual emancipation. These four stages of life are life of a student. life of a householder, life of a hermit or recluse, and life of an ascetic It will be seen that the aśrama dharma seeks to resolve the conflict between the two ideals, namely, the consolidation and the progress of the society on the one hand and the spiritual emancipation of the individual on the other In connection with the scheme of the aśramas, the Dharma sustra texts have stated clearly and at some length the Brahmanic ideals regarding such topics as education, position of woman, and family life Attempts have also been made to render the broad scheme of the aśramas more viable and effective by prescribing various samskaras or sacraments wbich are, as it were, the lamp posts on the road leading to the full fledged growth of man&amp;rsquo;s personality These samskaras cover man s whole life - actually beginning from its prenatal and ending with its post-morteo phase&#xA;It will be thus seen that the Brabmanists had developed quite a remarkable social philosophy This philosophy continues to constitute - though in a more or less modified form - the basis of the Hindu society even up to this day The fact of its emergence would also serve as a corrective against the popular misconception that the ancient Indians always thought in terms of fatalism, pessimism, and otherworldliness&#xA;[ First published&#xA;IAC 8, 1939 47-59 ]&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Indo Mediterranean contacts</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/Indo_Mediterranean_contacts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/Indo_Mediterranean_contacts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SOME ASPECTS OF THE INDO-MEDITERRANEAN CONTACTS&#xA;The subject of my lecturel is : Some Aspects of the Contacts between India and the Mediterranean World. Let me begin by defining my subject geographically and chronologically. For the purpose of this paper, by &amp;quot; Mediterranean World &amp;quot; I have under stood, on the one hand, the Levant which included Asia Minor and the Fertile Crescent with Egypt at its western terminus, Syria Palestine forming its western band, and Assyria-Babylonia con stituting its eastern bow, and, on the other, Greece and Rome. By India I mean the Indian subcontinent, I shall deal with my subject roughly in four chronological periods, which, for the sake of convenience, I shall designate as Indo-Mesopotamian period, Indo-Anatolian period, Indo-Hellinistic period, and Indo-Roman period.&#xA;An important aspect of the proto-historic India is represented by the Indus valley civilization (now more popularly known as the Harappan civilization) which has been brought to light, in its various ramifications, during the course of the last forty years or So. On the basis of an examination of the craniological series of Mohenjodaro, a majority of anthropologists and ethnologists are now inclined to reject the theory that the Mohenjodaro people contained a mixture of such types as the Negroid, the proto. Australoid, the Veddoid, etc., and to suggest that the Indus valley people belonged to the mediterranean branch of the europeoid race. Mario CAPPIERI, for instance, says that in the fourth millennium B. C. and probably before, North-West India seems to have been inhabited by a long-head race, which had a high&#xA;1, R.G Bhandarkar Anniversary Address delivered at the Bhandarkar O. R. Institute, Poona, on Rupañcami, 16th September, 1969.&#xA;2. Cr. V. P. ALEKSEYEy in Indiya v Drernos-Soomık Slatej, Moscow, 1964,&#xA;46&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;vault, long face, and thin and prominent nose,&amp;lsquo;3 Indeed, in different parts of the region which included Anatolia, Palestine, Mesopotamia, Iran, and North-West India, one has to assume the existence of a very archaic racial type of extensive diffusion, relatively homogeneous and living in well defined, small, indepen dent groups This type belongs to tbe great group of mankind, which G SERGI has called the Mediterranean race. Most of the anthropologists, who have examined the human remains found in the excavations of the regions from the Aegean Sea to the Indus and who have minutely studied the prehistoric skulls and skele tons, admit that the long-head forms belong to the Mediterranean stock. The Mediterranean type of people is believed to have been the carliest contributor of agriculture and urban civilization in almost the whole extensive area stretching along the Mediterra nean basis towards the east up to North-West India. It is sug gested that the rise of the Indus cities was due to a kind of cul tural explosion or revolution occasioned by the penetration into India of a new ethnic group, namely, one of the Mesopotamian peoples - presumably the Ubaidians - which was subjugated and forced out by the Sumerians.&#xA;However, in view of the fact that the skeletal remains exca vated from the various sites of the indus.civilization are extre mely meagre, it would perhaps be hazardous to assert that the authors of that civilization belonged to the eastern type of the Asiatic proto-Mediterraneans. There is, indeed, no evidence to suggest any wholesale migration of peoples from Mesopotamia to the Indus region. There is also reason to believe that the socio political patterns of the Mesopotamian and the Indus civilizations were quite distinct from each other. It is further to be noted that, besides the Mediterranean type, the Indus skeletal remains were found to include stray brachycephalic Alpine or Armenoid types as well. Therefore, on the basis of the available evidence, it would be safer to assume that the Harappans originated in the local soil, that their civilization was essentially an indigenous develop ment, but that they had very busy and active contacts with, among&#xA;3. Proceedings of the flørld Population Conference, Vol. II, 761-762.&#xA;INDO-MEDITERRANEAN CONTACTS&#xA;47&#xA;others, the Mesopotamians belonging to the Mediterranean stock from whom they borrowed some techniques of urban life.&#xA;The contacts between the sodus and the Mesopotamian re gions can be traced back to the Sargonide period of the Sumerian history (circa 2500 B, C) and seem to have actively continued up to at least 1900 B. C. A mention may be made in this connec tion of actual finds of objects which were typical of one civiliza tion in the archaeological sites representing the other civilization. Such are, for instance, the distinctive but uras (pyxis) in the proto-historic cities of Mesopotamia and Elam, the bone inlays of the characteristic Iodus kidney-shape, segmented, etched and gold disc beads, bronze amulets of couchant bulls, Early Dynastic scarlet ware with the figure of humped bull, and pottery bearing kaobs. The stylistic and typical details of these objects are such as would render improbable the assumption of coincidental similarities The evidence of the discovery in the Royal Tombs of Sumer of the figure of squatting monkey, carpelian beads, and a peculiar type of hair-dressing as also of the discovery in Harappa of a distinctive type of terracotta figurines, fashioned in the round, depicting nude male body, perhaps ithyphallic, with ex tremely obese stomach, prominent buttocks, shoulder-holes for the attachment of movable arms and stubby tail, hundreds of specimens of which have also been excavated from the Meso potamian sites, is certainly quite illuminating. A terracotta die of Indian origin discovered by Professor SPEISER in his Tepe Gawra excavations again suggests a basic synchronism between the Mesopotamian Old Akkadian period and the &amp;ldquo;mature&amp;rdquo; Harappan period 4 A reference may be made here also to the figurines of the so-called Eye-Goddesses, which have been discovered in the Indus as well as the West Asian archaeological sites. It is rightly pointed out that functional architecture is common to the Indus valley and Sumer. The similarity between the Indus region and Mesopotamia in the matter of corbelled arch (as attested in Tell Asmar and Mohenjodaro), circular wells&#xA;4. George T. DALES, &amp;quot; Or dice and men&amp;quot;, J405 82, 14-23.&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;of segmental bricks, and stone or baked clay lattice screens for windows cannot be regarded as being fortuitous It may be in cidentally added that the Indus civilization shows some improve ment in certain respects over the technique of Mesopotamia as is testified by the irregular streets of Ur and the planned ones of Mohenjodaro&#xA;The evidence of seals is perhaps more convincing As many as thirty ladus seals are said to have been actually excavated from Sumer They can be understood as being indicative of trade contacts between the two regions Such trade link between India and West Asia is confirmed by the discovery of Indus like seals in the island of Bahrain in the Persian Gulf. It has now been shown that the Indus civilization was a marıtıme civilization and not merely a land locked one Lothal which represented a sou thera extension of the Harappan civilization was undoubtedly a port with an impressive dochyard and served as an important centre of sea faring activity between the Harappan and the Meso potamian regions &amp;amp; It is even suggested that the presence of mature Harappan civilization can be attested along the coast as far west as the Dasht valley and that Sutkagen dor in the Dasht valley and Sotka koh in the Shadı kaur valley north of Pasoi played a key role as Harappan ports? It is further suggested that the enterprissog merchants of Kull civilization may have served as middlemen between Mesopotamian and Indus regions A spe cimen of the so called Persian Gulf seal, which, as indicated above, is a variant of the Indus pattern, is discovered at Lothal,&#xA;5 G BUDY, &amp;ldquo;The Ancient Indian Style scals from Bahrain , Anli qu ty 32, 243-46 Also scc W F LEENANS Forrign trade in the Old Babylonian Parod Leiden 1960&#xA;6 CES R RAO Shipp ng and maritime trade of the Indus people&amp;rsquo;, Exped I on 7, 30–37, Hartmut SciTxoKEL Zw schen Ur und Lothal DC Scchandelsroute von Allmncsopotamien zur Induski ltur, Forschungen unl Fort schnite 40 (5) 143 117 Incidentally it is suggested that when the Indo Aryans alrcady inl al ied a great part of India thc peninsula of Gujarat was perhaps a last bulwark of the Ind is civil zat on (I EEMANS, JCSHO 11, 223)&#xA;7 Gr Dale Harappan outposts on the Makran coast, Ant quly 36, 86-97&#xA;8 SR RAO A Pers ap Gulr cal from Lochal , Antiguity 37, 96-99&#xA;INDO-MEDITERRANEAN CONTACTS&#xA;49&#xA;while Briggs BUCHANAN speaks of&amp;rsquo; a dated seal impression con necting Babylonia and ancient India. * Mesopotamian records mention specific goods and materials which used to be imported from foreign lands, and at least some of these must have been imported from the Harappan regions. It is, however, interest ing to note that there are no traces of wares imported by the Harappans Presumably they were &amp;lsquo;soft&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;consumable&amp;rsquo;, such as garments, wool, leather products, and perfumed oil. In deed, the viability of the Mesopotamian and ladus civilizations depended largely on mutual active trade, and it is not without significance that the end of the international trade of the Larsa period in Mesopotamia coincided with the end of the &amp;lsquo;mature&amp;rsquo; Harappan period.&#xA;A reference has already been made to the skeletal remains in the Indus valley which are suggestive of Mesopotamian Mediterranean stock. The Mesopotamian records mention several distant places, some of which may be identified with Indus localities. For instance, the inscriptions of the kings of Akkad and certain lexical texts originating in that region mention Magan or Makkan, which scholars identify with Makran in Baluchistan, and Melubha, from which place carnelian and special kinds of wood were imported by sea by the Babylonians and which is identified with Lothal and its environs.10 Dilmun is frequently mentioned in Sumerian texts and glorified in Sumcrian mythology. It is described as a place where the sun rises (that is, which is towards the east) and as a prosperous land dotted with great dwellings. Samuel KRAMER is inclined to identify&#xA;9 Archaeology 70, 104-107 Also scc : C J. GADD, “Seals of ancient Indian style found at Ur&amp;rdquo;, Proceedings of the British Academy, 1932, 191-210.&#xA;10 CF &amp;ldquo;The identification of Meluhha with India is well established and $ corroborated by its etymological derivative in Sanskrit mleccha, a word which occurs first in the Salapathabrahmana to denote barbarians (&amp;ldquo;lemons &amp;ldquo;) of unintelligible speech&amp;rdquo; (Asko PARPOLA and others, Deapherment of the Proto Dravidian Inscriptions of the Indus Gtoilization, A first announcement, Copen hagen, 1969, p.4) Penttı AALTO first suggested the connection of Meluhba with Palı milakkha. Sanskrit mleccha (bid, p 50) Also see : W.F. LEEMANS, &amp;quot; Additional cvidence for the Persian Gulf trade and Meluhha&amp;rdquo;, JESHO 11 (2), 215–226.&#xA;50&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;Dilmun with the Indus region. He further points to the signifi. cance of the facts that the great Sumerian water-god Enki was most intimately connected with Dilmun and that the Todus civili zation was characterized by the cult of a water deity and sea faring ships 11 A reference may be made in this context also to words like taimáta, urugulā, and algi viligi occurring in the Atharvai eda (V 13 ), which are obviously non Aryan and which are supposed to have been derived from Mesopotamian Tiamut (the dragon ), urugala (the underworld), and Bilgi (an ancient Assyrian god) Thus, though it is not possible to ascertain at this stage the exact nature and extent of the interdependence between Indus India on the one hand and Mesopotamia which was a part of the Mediterranean world on the other, the fact that active coptacts had developed between the two regions early in the third millennium B. C and had continued for nearly 800 years can be proved beyond doubt&#xA;As a matter of fact it does not seem unlikely that the Indus people had established trade links even with the Minoan Crete In this connection, a reference may be made to the correspondence between the Mother Goddess cults of Harappa and Syria Crete Syrio-Cretan type of doves, snakes, and tree worship was prevalent also in Mohenjodaro and Harappa Further, the segmentai variety of faience beads from Harappa resemble not those of Ur but those discovered in Crete&#xA;If the evidence for the Indo Mesopotamian contacts is mainly archaeological, that for the Indo Anatolian contacts is essentially linguistic It also needs to be pointed out that the relationship between India and Anatolia was not of the nature of direct and continuing contacts As a matter of fact, neither of the two regions seems to have been at all conscious of this relationship. A clay tablet discovered at Bogazkoi (about 80 miles to the&#xA;11 Samuel Noah KRAMER, The Induṣ cıvılızation and Dumun, the Sumerian Paradise lost , Expeditzort 6, 44 52 PARPOLA and others identify Tilmun (Dilmun) with thc Bahre n land (op cut P4) Also see h JARITZ, &amp;ldquo;Talmud Makan Meluhba , Journal of Near Lastern Studies 27 (3), 209-213&#xA;INDO-MEDITERRANEAN CONTACTS&#xA;51&#xA;south-west of Ankara ) - presumably, the ancient name of the place was Hattuśa - by Hugo WINCKLER in 1906 represented a treaty concluded between the Mitannian ruler Mattiwaza (son of Tuśratta) and the Hittite king Suppiluliuma, in the fourteenth century B.C. As witnesses to the treaty are involed, among many other gods, four gods whose names are clearly akin to those of the Vedic gods, Mitra, Varuṇa, Indra, and Nasatya. About twenty years before this discovery, that is, in 1887, there was discovered at El-Amarna in central Egypt a large number of tablets with writings in cuneiform characters. This collection constituted a part of an ancient archive containing the correspon. dence of Pharaoh Amenophis IV (circa 1364-1347 B, C.) and his father Pharaoh Amenophis III (circa 1402–1364 B, C.) with the castern states – particularly with the city-states in Syria Palestine and with Mitanni in castern Anatolia whose rulers were matrimonially related to the Pharaohs. The names of the Mitanni rulers mentioned in this correspondence, such as Arta tama and Artassumara, also show linguistic affinitics with Aryan names. Three years earlier, that is, in 1884, Friedrich DELIT ZSCH had drawn the attention of scholars to the Aryan influence on the language of the Kassites who seem to have had their principality to the south-east of the Mitannian realm, just to the north of the Persian Gulf. For instance, the word for the sun god in that language was śuniaś, and, both in form and meaning, it corresponded with the Vedic word sürya. Further, in the course of the archaeological expedition of 1906-12 itself, there was brought to light at Bogazkoi a text dealing with the breeding and training of horses, which belonged to the 14th century B. C. and wbose apiborship was attributed to one Xikkuly described as aśśuśćani ( which word is obviously related to asia - horse&amp;rsquo; and sam-&amp;rsquo;to tame) from the land of Mitanni. This text contains some numerals like aika, lira, panza, śalia, etc, which are unmistakably reminiscent of Sanskrit eka, tri, pañca, sapta, etc. These numerals occur as the first members of the compounds formed with - uartanna, which form is clearly connected with Vedic vartani - its i ending having been changed to a-ending as is to be seen in such Vedic compounds with numerals as dasãigula&#xA;52&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;(from daśa + anguli) and tryañjala (from tri ef anjal). Finally, between 1925 and 1931, there were unearthed important documents from the city of Nuzi which was situated at the south-eastern end of the Mitannian realm. These documents again contained words like babru-nnu (babhru ), parita-nnu (palta), and pinkara-nnu (pingala) to denote the colours of horses.&#xA;This Aryan linguistic material gleaned from different sources, which, however, were directly or indirectly connected with the Mitanni state in ancient Anatolia and wbich generally belonged to the second millennium B, C., is classified under three main heads, namely, (a) Dames of four Vedic gods, (b) thirteen appellatives - among them four substantives, three adjectives, five Dumerals, and one verb - seves of which are derived from Kikkuli&amp;rsquo;s work, three from Nuzi, and three from Hurrian records, and (c) a oumber of personal names.13 About the Aryan character of the first two of these classes there can hardly be any doubt, while the third class contains words which seem to be local variations of the original Aryan forms. In the context of this last class, it may be incidentally pointed out that the mutual influence of the Near Eastern speech and the Aryan speech may be discovered in such phenomena as the peculiar development of the Indo-European vocalısm in Aryan, the participles in- ma-of Luwian with a middle or passive meaning corresponding to the formations like Sanskrit ksāma, stima, bhima, dasma, migma, uma, etc,15 and the Aryan words with Hurrian suffix like mutunni and aśśuśśanı,16 As regards a more precise linguistic characterization&#xA;12. M MAYRHOFER, &amp;quot; Zablwortkomposita des Kikkuli Textes&amp;rdquo;, IF 70, 11-13.&#xA;13. For a fuller discu$:09, see : R. HAUSCHED, Uber due fthesten Asset im alten Orient, Berlin, 1962, M. MAYRITOFER, Die Indo-Aruer im alten Vordera sien, mil cine analytischen Bibliographie, Wiesbaden, 1966, A KAMMENHUBER, Die Aner im Vorderen Orient, Heidelberg, 1968&#xA;14 CE O SZEXERCNYI, “Structuralis, and substsatun : Indo-Euro pcans and Semites in the Ancient Near Last&amp;rdquo;, Lingua 13, 1-29.&#xA;15. E BENVENISTE, &amp;ldquo;La forme du participe en Luw.&amp;rdquo;, Festschrij? Johan. rus Friedrich, 1959, 53-59&#xA;16 M MAYRHOFER, &amp;ldquo;Uber einige arische Worter mit hurtschen Suffix&amp;rdquo;. Annah Ist Uni, Or, Napoli, Sez. Ling 1,1-11.&#xA;INDO-MEDITERRANEAN CONTACTS&#xA;53&#xA;of these Aryan linguistic remains in Anatolia, one may think of three alternatives: they represent either the proto-Aryan stage or the Irano-Aryan stage or the Indo-Aryan stage. A critical and comparative study of all this material, in the details of which it is neither possible nor Decessary to enter here, has led to the conclusion that the language presupposed by the various forms is nearest to the Vedic Sanskrit.&#xA;The mention of the four Vedic gods in the Mitanni-Hittite treaty is particularly significant in this connection. It has been shown that these four gods are mentioned together also in the Rgveda (X, 125. 1 ) and the Atharvaveda (III. 4, 4) and that in the Rgveda they are not unoften celebrated as protectors of treaties or contracts.17&#xA;How can this superimposition of the Vedic Aryan element on Mitapoi be historically explained ? It would seem that, after the dark period following the fall of Babylon in about 1650 B. C., the Hurrans spread over a major part of Syria and Mesopotamia and established in that region the kingdom of Mitanni. In this adventure of theirs, the Hurrians were led by Aryan warriors, often referred to as mariann (Vedic marya), who, though comparatively few in number, eventually emerged as rulers and noblemen. Five or six generations of Aryad rulers of Mitanni can be attested from the available records. Two facts need to be emphasized at this stage: (1) The names of the Mitapoi prince involved in the treaty recorded on the Bogazkoi tablet and his father - Mattiwaza and Tuśratta - are unmistakably Indo-Aryan, 19 (2) Besides the four Indo-Aryan gods, quite a large number of other gods, presumably Hurrian, are mentioned on the Bogazkoi tablet. It would, therefore, not be wrong to suppose that the Indo-Aryan gods belonged to the Indo-Aryan ruling family and noblemen, while the other gods belonged to the large Hurrian population. It is rightly suggested by HERZFELD that it could have&#xA;17. P. TATEME, * The * Aryan&amp;rsquo; Gods of the Mitanni trcaties &amp;ldquo;, JAOS 80, 301-317.&#xA;18. The names may be rendered in Vedic Sanskrit as mathivaja and Icesaratha.&#xA;54&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;been only&amp;rsquo; a group of Aryan condotierri and their troops &amp;lsquo;18 who were inyolved in the establishment of the kingdom of Mitan01&#xA;I visualise the entire course of history in this connection roughly as follows 20 The earliest common habitat of the speakers of proto IE (who, however, did not necessarily belong to the same racial stock), which can be attested on the strength of the available linguistic, archaeological, anthropological, and culture historical evidence, is the North Kirghiz steppes between the Urals and Altai In view of the facts that the proto-Hellenes can be shown to have catered Greece in about 2200 BC, that the Hittites, as will be soon pointed out, started on their isolated migration in about 2800 BC, and that the proto-Aryans must be assumed to have separated from the main stock in about 2600 BC. the proto IE unity can be. with reasonable certainty, dated from 3500 B C It has now been shown that the Hittite language is the oldest offshoot of the proto IE family It shows considerable alipity with proto IE but it cannot be assigned to any specific IE branch We may, therefore, assume th. there occurred an isolated migration of the Hittites from the common proto-lE habitat even before the JE speech bad assumed its specific form The Hittites proceeded towards the south west and occupied the region between the Caucasus mountain and the Caspian sea This may have happened about 2800 B C After a few centuries of comparative able vion, the Hittites are known to have pushed forth further towards the south-west through the Cilician gates and to have established their sovereignty over the highlands in the great bend of the Halys river in the course of their further expansion, they scem, on the one hand, to have reached the Mediterranean sea towards the south west, and, on the other, to have established some kind of suzerainty over the Mitannian kingdom towards the&#xA;19 F HERZFELD, Iran in the Ancient Cast, 1941, p192&#xA;20 For fuller statement on the subject, Bec &amp;ldquo;The antoccdents and the carly beginnings of the Vedic period&amp;rsquo;, publuhed elsewhere in this Volume It will be seen that I have goodified my carlier ViCW regarding the m gration of the Proto-Aryans towards Anatolia The spellings of some words&#xA;CWJg la thu context basc also been changedINDO-MEDITERRANEAN CONTACTS&#xA;south-cast. So far as the former event is concerned, it has been pointed out that the contact with the sea had great significance for the laod-locked people like the Hittites, and the sea (aruna in Hittitel ) was, therefore, much glorified in their texts. As for the latter event, it has been pointed out that, in spite of the fairly long period of proximity of the Hittites and the Hurrians, there do not seem to have occurred any significant political-cultural contacts between them until the middle of thc 14th century B. C., when, through a treaty recorded on the Bogazhoi clay tablet, a political and matrimonial alliance came to be established between king Mattiwaza of Mitanni and his suzerain king Suppiluliuma of the Hittites.&#xA;But we have anticipated a little. Let us go back to the migrations of the proto-IE-speaking peoples. Even after the isolated migration of the Hittites in the initial stage of the development of proto-IE, the remaining proto-IE-speakers, who may now be designated as JE-speakers, continued to live in the North Kirghiz region for some time. The next landmark in the history of these people is represented by two major migra tions. The earlier major migration was in the south-eastera direction. Some of the tribes of the IE-speakers separated from the main body of the IE-speakers and migrated to a locality not very different from their Urheimat, namely, to the region round about Balkh. The other major migration was towards the Pripet region from where there later occurred further secondary migra tions towards, among others, the Aegean world, Italy, and Germa nic lands. We are, however, concerned here more with the tribes which migrated to and eventually settled down in the Balkh region. Here, between 2500 B, C. and 2300 B, C.. the proto Aryan language, which, on the one hand, had evolved out of IE and, on the other, was the ancestor of ancient Iranian and Vedic Sanskrit, as also the proto-Aryan religious ideology, which represented the anterior stage of the Avestan and the Vedic religious ideology, attained characterization.&#xA;21. Perhaps comparable with OIA amas, arpada.&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;As from the Pripet region, so too from Balkh there occurred, in course of time, secondary migrations - first of the proto-Indo Aryans towards the land of seven rivers in the south-east and, presumably much later, of the proto-Irano-Aryans towards Iran in the rest. There is reason to believe that, while the proto-Indo Aryans were fighting out their way towards India, their language and religious ideology gradually developed the specifically Vedic character. It was also during the course of this their onward march, under the leadership of Vr̥trahā Indra, that some adven turists from among them, instead of proceeding towards Sapta sindhu with their comrades, turned back and wended their perilous and protracted way towards the north-west. It was the descendants, by several generations, of these yaliant proto-Indo Aryaa defectors who ultimately reached the central bend of the Fertile Crescent, iasinuated themselves among the local Hurrians as their leaders, and eventually established the Mitaoni Kingdom under their sovereignty.3: The Mitannian kings were ncither the ancestors of the Indo-Aryans, nor were they, strictly speaking, the Indo-Aryans who had migrated from India to East Anatolia. Their ancestors had, however, been closely related to the ancestors of the Indo-Aryans as members of one and the same linguistic and religious fraternity. But they had separated themselves from the latter even before thc latter had entered fadia and had thus become proper Indo-Aryans. One branch of the proto-Indo Aryans entered Saptasindhu by the end of the third millennium B. C. and soon succceded in firmly laying the foundation of Vedic religion and culture. The other branch of the proto-Indo Aryans made its appearance, a few gcacrations later, in Asia Minor&amp;rdquo; as the group of condoticeri who cstablished the kingdom of Mitanni by the middle of the sccond century B. C. The lates of these two branches of the prolo-Indo-Aryan community proved to be quite distinct from cach other. The proto-Indo-Aryans migrating into North-Western India ucrc comparatively few in&#xA;22. Though usually referred to as Tayern Anatolis, the Mitsoni kingdom graphixally coincided with a maine part of ancient Afesogtamis.&#xA;23, Sce the preceding foot pote.&#xA;INDO-MEDITERRANEAN CONTACTS&#xA;57&#xA;number, but they seem to have possessed tremendous power to diffuse their language and culture so that, instead of being absorbed by the indigenous population, they could superimpose their own language and culture on that population. The Vedic language and culture soon became deeply and permanently rooted in the Indian soil. As against this, the proto-Indo-Aryans, who had made a detour in the direction of the Near East and who must have lost many of the features of their proto-lodo Aryan language and religious ideology already in the long process of that detour, could influence the indigenous Hurrian population of that region, through their language and religion, only super ficially and that too because they had manoeuvered to establish themselves as a ruling class withia that population. Unlike their brethren in India, they disappeared from the scene of history, politically and culturally, within less than 200 years. It is only on the hypothesis as stated above that the stray Indo-Aryan elements in the Mitannian and allied records of about the middle of the second millennium B. C. can be adequately accounted for.&#xA;An important aspect of the Indo-Mediterranean contacts was represented by the contacts between the Phoenicians and the Indians. But very little archaeological, linguistic, or historical evidence is available for it being possible to make any adequate statement about those contacts. A suggestion is often made that the Panis mentioned in the Rgreda must have been Phocpician merchants. The Panis are no doubt described in the Rgveda as rich traders and usurers, but the Rgveda also gives the impression that the Panis were not mere casual traders. They seem to have become more or less permanently settled in India, and the Vedic Aryans, in the course of their colonization, continually encountered them and that too in a hostile manner. This would certainly go against their identification with the Phoenicians. The Panis seem to have been connected, in a special way, with Divodása, the river Sarasvati, and the family of the Bharadvājas. Then there is the legend that Saramā discovered the place where the Panis had kept the kine of the Vedic Aryans in captivity. All this does not conform with the general character of the Phoeni.&#xA;58&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;cians as known from their history The Phoenicians were famous throughout antiquity for their maritime prowess which feature is hardly ever attributed to the Panis in the Rgveda 24 It was only after the end of the old Babylonian civilization that the region of Syria Palestine began to assume importance, and it was only as the result of the conflict between Egypt on the one hand and the Hittite Mitanni kingdoms on the other that the Phocnicians who had established themselves between Lebanon to the north and Palestine to the south enjoyed a period of inde pendence The earliest evidence of trade contacts between Phoenicia and Western India goes back only to 975 BC In that year, Hiram, king of Tyre, sent his fleet of ships of Tarsbish&amp;rsquo; from Egion Geber, at tbe head of the Gulf of Akaba in the Red Sea to fetch &amp;lsquo;ivory, apes, and peacocks from the port of Ophir (which is identified with Sopara) to decorate the palaces and the Temple of King Solomop 25 But this commerce in merchandise between India and Phoenicia does not seem to have been accompanied by commerce in other aspects of culture and cryilization&#xA;This however, happened in a distinctive manner - but, perhaps, in the reverse order - 11 the case of the contacts between the Greeks and the Indians It may be pointed out, at the outset, that as members of the collateral branches of the IE linguistic family, the Indians and the Greeks were, in a sense closely related to each other When however, they met again many centuries later, they did it as complete strangers In the 6th century BC Persia served as a link between the Greeks and the Indians Indian troops are known to have served under the Persians when they invaded the Greek possessions, while Greek officials and mercenaries are known to have served in the Persian administra tive set up even in India When, for instance, Darius had&#xA;21 A S ALTEKAR (Profeed ngs of the twenty second Ind on Ilustory Congress 1959, p 20 ) 1 inclined to ident fy the Pani w th the Harappans or with a section of them&#xA;25 LG RAWLINSON India in Luropean 1 terature and thought&amp;rsquo;, The Lepog of India, Oxford, 1962, p I&#xA;INDO-MEDITERRANEAN CONTACTS&#xA;39&#xA;advanced as far as the head-waters of the Indus in 510 B. C., he is reported to have sent a Greek mercenary, named Skylax, to sail down the Indus and make his way home via the Red Sea. Skylax took the old route followed by the Phoenician traders and arrived at Arsinoe (which is identified with modern Suez) after a voyage of two and a half years.26 For whatever he tells us about India, Herodotus (born in 484 B. C.) has apparently depended largely on the account of Skylax. Panini (6th-5th centuries B, C.) shows acquaintance with the Yavanas or the Ionian Greeks. In this connection it may be pointed out that the true classical Hellenic thought and culture origtoated and developed in lonia in West Anatolia rather than on the mainland of Greece. It is, indeed, surprising that, even after having come into sufficiently close contact with the lonian Greeks, the Indians, who were generally endowed with a sharp linguistic sense, had not noticed the similarities betwecn their own language and the language of the Yayanas. Ctesias, another Greek, who lived at the Persian court at Susa for a fairly long time, has also written about India, but his account has tended to be more romantic than realistic.&#xA;It seems that, before the times of Alexander the Great, thought travelled from the east towards the west. Thales (6th century B, C.), who is called the Father of Greek philosophy and who belonged to Miletus in Ionia, postulated a physical-natura listic principle, namely, water, as the one basic substance from which all else in the universe was composed. The Eleatic School aimed at discovering the ope reality underlying the material phenomena, and the Orphic movement emphasized that the soul, which was immortal and which was distinct from the body, sought release from the body. According to Heraclitus (540-475 B. C.), life was change and the entire universe was ever in flux, while Democritus (460-370 B, C.) believed that the reality was the mechanical motion of atoms. No direct evidence is available which might belp us to ascertain whether the Indian philosophica&#xA;26. RAWLINSON, op. cit., pp. 2-3.&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;thought bad exercised any significant influence on these and similar Greek speculations. But the facts such as that these and allied philosophical doctrines had already been known in India, that many of these doctrines had originated among the Tonian Greeks (or the Yavadas) who had close contacts with Persia and through Persia with India, that, according to his biographer Iamblichus, Pythagoras (born in 580 B. C.) had studied the esoteric teachings of, among others, the Brāhmaṇas, and that there is the traditional account of the meeting in Athens between Socrates and some learned Brāhmanas, point to the high probability of the influence of Indian thought on Greek philo sophical speculatioss.&#xA;Alexander&amp;rsquo;s momentous campaigns in the East brought the Greeks in closer and more direct contact with the Indians than heretofore. Alexander, educated under the tutorship of Aristotle, set out on his victorious march in 334 B. C. and conquered ja quick succession Asia Minor, Syria, Palestine, and Egypt where he founded the city of Alexandria, Then he turned eastward, marched over the Fertile Crescent and defeated the large Persian&#xA;forces of Darius III in the battle of Arbela in 331 B. C. Five years later he reached Panjab. Alexander was not only a conqueros, he was also an explorer. During his military exped! tions he was always accompanied by trained historians, scientists, and philosophers. Indeed, he was the pioneer of the Hellenistic (as against Hellenic) movement, which had for its aim the &amp;rsquo;extension of Hellenic culture among the non-Greeks. His dream &amp;lsquo;of bringing about the marriage of Europe and Asia&amp;rsquo; did not materialise, but, in the course of his attempts in that direction, the centre of gravity of Greek culture came to be shifted from Greece to Asia. Alexandria developed into the biggest city of the realm-a great cosmopolitan centre of academic and commer cial activities. Alexander&amp;rsquo;s conquests gave rise to a new move ment of colonial expansion in the East, which implied the establishment of a number of new cities and kingdoms with Greek rulers and Greek advisers and the diffusion of Greek culture. It must, however, be noted that the vast mass of the&#xA;INDO-MEDITERRANEAN CONTACTS&#xA;61&#xA;people, on whom the Greek rule had been clamped, did not become hellenized.&#xA;Alexander&amp;rsquo;s Indian conquests proved almost ephemeral, so much so that they have been rarely mentioned in contemporary literature. But their general impact was vomistakable. For one thing, it is not unlikely that Kautilya&amp;rsquo;s exaltation of the king&amp;rsquo;s absolute authority and his emphasis on the vast bureaucratic governmental machinery with centralised control, which did not fit in well into the pattern of India&amp;rsquo;s traditional polity, were the result of the influence which the Hellenistic model in that regard must have exercised on that sagacious political teacher and administrator. It was again through Greek (and Persian) contacts with India in the 5th-4th centuries B. C. that iron is said to have been brought to India 27 Those contacts also resulted in a kind of second urbanisation,&amp;lsquo;28 and cities like Charsada and Taxila came to be built. It is suggested that the builders of megaliths in South India were a people of Mediterra nean stock who probably came to the West coast by sea, entered South India in about 500 B, C, and then spread northwards.to Trade between India and the Hellenistic world received great impetus. There were several trade-routes, the two more common having been: (1) overland ; Pāçalıputra-Taxıla-Bactra (the capital of Bactria ) - tben west by south across the long stretches of the Persian and the Median territory to Seleucia - and from there either up the Euphrates reaching Antioch, or via Edessa to the Mediterranean; and (2) by sea : From India&amp;rsquo;s west coast - to ports of the Persian Gulf – then up the Tigris to Seleucia - and then onwards by either of the two routes mentioned above. A large number of merchants from India could be seen on the&#xA;27. Mortimer VVATEELER, Carly India and Pakistan, 21 and 171. [It is, however, now sought to bc established that iron was introduced into India by the PGW people about 1000 B C and that the Aryans know iron beforc they entered India (N R. BANERJEE, The Iron Age in India, Delhi, 1965 ) J.&#xA;28 H. D. SANKALIA, Indian Archaeology Today, 124. The first urbanisa ton&amp;rsquo; was encouraged by the lado Mesopotamian contacts described above.&#xA;29 Thu is the viow of C von FORER-HATTENDORF, cf. IAC, January 1954, 238-7.&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;streets of Alexandria, and Strabo (the Greek historian) was told that 120 vessels sailed to India every year from the Egyptian ports&#xA;After the death of Alexander at Babylon in 323 B, C, his vast empire broke up into four parts - the Ptolemaic empire in Egypt, the Seleucid empire in Syria and Persia, Antigonus&amp;rsquo; empire in Macedonia and Greece, and the Oriental Greek and Bactrian kingdoms to the north-west of India Seleucos Nekator of the Syrian Persian Greek empire, who tried to emulate Alexander by invading Pataliputra, was defeated by Candragupla Maurya (322-298 B C ), and a matrimonial alliance is reported to have been concluded between the two. Seleucos also appoin ted Megasthenes as his ambassador in the court of Pataliputra The cultural contacts between the Maurya and the Seleucid realms continued even after Candragupta&amp;rsquo;s death, and the amusing episode 18 narrated that Bindusara, Candragupta&amp;rsquo;s successor, wrote to his contemporary Antiochus I of Syria asking for a sample of Greek wine and some raisins and a sophist who would teach him how to argue, and that Antiochus, while sending the wine and raisins with great pleasure, informed him that it was not good form among the Greeks to trade in philosophers. After Asoka (273-232 B, C.) became converted to the religion of the Buddha, he, as mentioned in his thirteenth rock-edict, dispatched missionaries to Antiochus and four other Greek kings, namely, Ptolemy Philadelphus of Egypt, Antigonus Gopatas of Macedonia, Magas of Cyrene, and Alexander of Epirus,30 with a view to winning them over to the Law of Piety and World Peace. It is also noteworthy that a special board in charge of foreigners in Jodia had been set up in the Maurya administrative system.si&#xA;After Asoha&amp;rsquo;s death in 232 B, C., the direct lado-Greek contacts were broken off, But India and Greece continued to influence each other through the Indo-Bactrians on the one hand and, to a certain extent, through the Indo-Roman contacts on the&#xA;30 The names as mentioned in the rock edict read Antayoga, Tula. maya, Amtckina, Maka, Alikyasudala&#xA;31 Bela LANIRI, “Impact of forcign trade on coins of ancient India QRHS 5, 194,&#xA;INDO-MEDITERRANEAN CONTACTS&#xA;other. Rome entered into Hellenistic affairs in 212 B, C., but the acme of the Graeco-Roman civilization, which was characte rized by the assimilation of the Hellenic elements and the preservation of Hellenistic culture in the East, was reached during Pax Romapa (that is from Augustus (30 B, C) to Marcus Aurelius [ 170 A. D. ]).&#xA;During this period, the Gāndhāra region had become the main centre where the Indian culture and the Graeco-Roman culture encountered each other and often fused together. Trade was perhaps the most essential link of this cultural contact. Indeed, the Kusāna prosperity seems to have depended largely on foreign trade. It is not unlikely that the advent of the Kusānas in Shen-to (that is, the lower Indus region) was primarily motivated by the prospects of rich gains from its thriving Indo Roman commerce. 82 During the Kusāna rule, the Graeco Roman trade with the East was at its height. A sea-captain from Alexandria who had then visited India has reported that spices and silks left Indian ports to be exchanged for Roman gold coins, Greek wines, and choice girls for the royal harems. The Milindpanha ( Ist century A. D.) also contains references to brisk maritime trade between India and Alexandria, The two great cities of Gāndhāra, namely, Begram and Taxila, had developed into veritable trade-centres on the Balkh-Gandhāra route. There bave been found at Begram ruins of a &amp;lsquo;palace (assignable to the 2nd-3rd centuries A D.), two rooms of which have yielded a hoard of Mediterranean and oriental wares, such as glass vessels from Syria and Egypt, Indian ivories, bronze bowls from Western factories, steelyard-weights in the form of busts of Minerva and Mars, and a good deal of specimens of Roman art like figures of Harpocrates, Hercules, and the grotesque philosopher&amp;rsquo; of the Alexandrian type. According to Mortimer WHEELER, this must have been a customs depot.&#xA;32. B. N. MUKIERJEE, &amp;quot; Impact of foreign trade on political history-an illustration&amp;rdquo;, QRHS 5, 183.&#xA;83. Kalyan Kumar Das Gupta, &amp;ldquo;Forcign trade and Gandhara art&amp;rdquo;, QRHS 5, 2012&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;Evidence is available to show that equally active and rich trade was carried on between the Tamil region in South India and the Roman empire, in the early centuries A. D. As a matter of fact, even before the Romans had come on the scene, the Tamil country was engaged in prosperous trade and commerce with Egypt and the Greek kingdoms. In this connection it is note worthy that the Hebrew word for peacock and the Greek words for ginger, cinnamon, and rice have been derived from Tamil. The Periplus of the Er; threan Sea by an Alexandrian sea-farer, of about the time of Nero, describes the journey from the Red Sea along the Indian coast from the mouth of the Indus to that of the Gangā But the most frequently followed trade-route seems to have been : Alexandria-Aden-Indian Ocean-Muziris ( Cran. ganore ) in Malbar. The discovery of the Monsoon in about 50 A. D must have given added fillip to the sea-journey from the Gulf of Aden to India between May and October and the return journey between November and March. According to Pliny, who complained of the drain of Eastern luxuries upon Rome, Rome used to pay fifty million sesterces annually for balance of trade with India The large hordes of Roman coins found in South India would also bear ample testimony to the magnitude of trade between India and the Roman world. The exports from India consisted mainly of pepper, cinnamon, spices, drugs, pearls, silks, and muslins, while among the merchandise imported into Jadia were precious metals, pottery, glassware, wine, silverware, and human cargo (constituted of craftsmen and masons). It is certainly not without significance that several specimens of Roman glass have been discovered in the excavations at Dharoikota (Dhanakataka ) in Andhra.4 Attention may further be drawn to the fact that Tamil authors have referred in their writings to Roman colonies in South India at places like Muziris, Madura, and Pukar - the colonists having mainly been the natives of Syria and Egypt with Roman officers in charge. Incidentally, it may also be mentioned that, in the course of excavations at Pompeii in 1939, there has been discovered a fine ivory statuette&#xA;34. B B. LAL, Indian Archarology since Independence, 34,INDO-MEDITERRANEAN CONTACTS&#xA;of Indian workmanship supposedly portraying the Hindu goddess Laksmi. Some merchant must have brought it bome after his Indian adventure, before 79 A. D. when Pompeii was over whelmed. 35&#xA;So far as political relations are concerned it may be men tioned that the Kuṣāpa king Kadphises III had sent an embassy to Rome in 99 A, D. to congratulate Trajan on his accession. Actually, more than a century earlier, a Pandya embassy, under the leadership of Zarmannchegas (Śramanācārya), had left Bhțgukaccha in 25 B, C, and waited upon Augustus at Samos in 21 B. C. with presents for the Emperor which are said to have consisted, among other things, of gigantic python, huge tortoises, and an armless boy who could shoot arrows with his feet. Indeed, at least nine ambassadors from India are known to have visited Roman emperors up to the times of Constantine, The purpose of these embassies must have been both diplomatic and commercial&#xA;Indian philosophy seems to have made a tremendous impres sion upon the thinkers of the Graeco-Roman world. We are told that Appollonius of Tyana ( 50 A. D.) had gone to Taxila to study under the Brāhmana teachers there, while the gaostic Baroksanes had learnt many curious facts about India from the Iodian embassy in Syria (218-222 A. D.) Indeed, gnosticism came to be described as orientalism in a Hellenic garb&amp;rsquo;. Clement of Alexandria (150-218 A. D.), who, incidentally, was the first Greek writer to mention the Buddha by pame, even went to the extent of asserting that the Greeks had stolen their philo sophy from the barbarians (by which term he must have meant the Indians As if to counterbalance this, the Indian astronomes Varāhamihira admonished his readers, a couple of centuries later, that the science of astronomy was well-established among the Yavanas and that, therefore, though they were barbarians, they must be respected like India&amp;rsquo;s own ancient sages. It is, therefore,&#xA;35. fortimer WIFEELER, Ront Beyond the Imperial Frontiers, 135 SANKALLA (op al., 120, f. n. 81) Jocs not think that the statuette portrays Lakym.&#xA;66&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;not surprising that two of the five principal schools of Indian astronomy came to be named Romaka (after Rome) and Pauliśa (after Paul of Alexandria, 378 A. D.). The assumption of some kind of Hellenistic influence on the growth of Sanskrit drama during the Kusāna period would not be altogether unwarranted. Similarly the type of coinage introduced by the Indo-Bactrian kings was essentially Hellenistic in character. For one thing, those coins either had the names and portraits of the rulers inscribed on them or they showed figures of divinities belonging to the Greek pantheon. Secondly, the names given to some of those cojas, such as Dīpāra and Dramma, are obviously Indian forms of Greek Dinarius and Drachma. The standardızation of this coinage in respect of form and weight was also something which had been unknown in India in the earlier periods.97&#xA;But perhaps the most enduring monument of the Indo Hellenistic cultural fusion is to be seen in the Gāndhāra art, which is also significantly called the Graeco-Buddhist art. This school of art was actually inaugurated only after the direct Greek domination in the North-Western region of India had ended, and was patronised mainly by the Sakas and the Kusānas who had continued the tradition of their Hellenistic predecessors. The themes of the Gāndhāra art are essentially Buddhistic, while the style of execution is undeniably Hellenistic. The Gāndhāra Buddha, for instance, looks like an Apollo wearing costumes whose &amp;lsquo;wet&amp;rsquo; drapery is derived from the Classical art. Indian sages and priests are clearly reminiscent of bearded philosophers and sages of the Hellenistic world, and the Yaksas, the Garudas, the Nāgas, and other semi-mythical beings appear to be mere eastern versions of the genit of the Hellenistic pantheon. The influence of the Hellenistic art-forms is unmistakably reflected in&#xA;36. I have suggested (&amp;ldquo;East and West&amp;rdquo;, published elsewhere in this Volume) that one may sce in this the influence of the anthropocentric West. Also see foot note 38.&#xA;37. It has been pointed out by Lallanji Gopal (QRHS 5, 188 ) that the literally golden period of Indian coinage system was the period which wit nessed India&amp;rsquo;s trade activity at its peak&amp;rsquo;,&#xA;INDO-MEDITERRANEAN CONTACTS&#xA;physiognomy, drapery, the wavy treatment of the hair, the use of Corinthian colonette as a space-divider in relief compositions, etc., adopted by the Gāndhāra artists.3: Verily, the religious penchant of Indian culture, united with the aesthetic penchant of Greek culture, has produced this sublime and creative school of art.&#xA;[First published : ABORI 50, 1969, 57–74. Also published : Drogenes 71, 1970, 18-38.1&#xA;38. According to K. K. Das GUPTA (op. cit., 201-202), the art of Gin dhira was &amp;lsquo;but an integral part of itellenistic art and it derived its suste Dance from Budahum and capitalism, the latter being an outgrowth of Inilo Roman commcrcc&amp;rsquo;. In connection with the Cindhára art, I have said (&amp;ldquo;East and West&amp;rdquo;): &amp;ldquo;The traditional cosmic non individualistic outlook of the Indians did not encourage the sculptures of individual, isolated figures. It must have been the contact with the anthropocentric West which had inspired the sculpture of the figures of the Buldhr&amp;rsquo;,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>King election</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/King_election/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/King_election/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;ATHARVAVEDA III. 4 : &amp;ldquo;ELECTION OF A KING&amp;rdquo;&#xA;Introduction&#xA;It is usually suggested that the ancient Indian thinker possessed only a &amp;rsquo;theological&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;philosophical&amp;rsquo; mind. The large amount of ancient Indian literature relating, either directly or indirectly, to political science (Arthaśāstra or Dandaniti) would, however, clearly indicate that he also possessed what may be called a political&amp;rsquo; and &amp;rsquo;economic&amp;rsquo; mind. Indeed, some of the thinkers of ancient India went to the extent of claiming that Arthaśāstra or Dandaniti was the most fundamental of all sciences,&#xA;One of the most basic concepts in ancient Indian polity was that of kingsbip. In the Vedic literature - more particularly, in the Brāhmaṇas - we come across various speculations, mostly embodied in mythical legends, about such topics as the origin and nature of kingship, the functions of the king, the types of sovereignty, and the checks on the autocracy of the king. So far as the origin of kingship is concerned, one may distinguish between two main currents of thought. It is pointed out in one of the Brāhmaṇa passages that the highest god (Prajāpati) bestowed his own special power upon one of the gods (Indra) and thus enabled him, though a jupior, to rule over the gods. There is another significapt variation of this theory of the divine origin of kingship. The Mahābhārata, for instance, speaks of a Mare di nature irom Wrich Prajapati rescued Ype &amp;lsquo;auman race by laying down a code of conduct for all people and by creating the institution of kingship,3 The Great Epic here refers to three&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>mahAbhArata - origin and growth</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/mahAbhArata_-_origin_and_growth/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/mahAbhArata_-_origin_and_growth/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THE MAHABHARATA : ORIGIN AND GROWTH&#xA;In the history of Indological studies there has been evident a tendency to exaggerate the importance of the Vedic Aryan element in India&amp;rsquo;s culture-complex According to this school of thought the Veda has made the greatest contribution to the moulding of the Indian way of life and thought through the ages As a matter of fact, ancient Indian culture, or, more precisely, the Hindu culture, as a whole, is not infrequently characterised as Vedic culture Even a casual survey of the Hindu way of life and thought would, however, lay bare the inadequacy of such a characterisation The principal gods of the Vedic pantheon, such as Indra and Varuṇa, are now no longer worshipped, their place has long since been taken by the gods of the people, like Visou and Rudra Siva Mythology and demonology other than those of the Veda have been ushered in and now cater to the instinctive demands of the people in connection with what may be called the embellishment and ornamentation of religion. The elaborate system of sacrifice, which had been evolved and consolidated dur jog the Brāhmana period and resuscitated and reorganised during the Sūtra period and which had come to be recognised almost as the hallmark of the Vedic religious practice, has now become well nigh extinct. The profound philosophical speculations of the Upanısads, which were once regarded as the last word in the field of mysticism and spiritualism, have either undergone vital modi. fications or have been cotirely superseded by other systems of thought The fastidious rules governing man&amp;rsquo;s personal, domes tic, and social life, prescribed by the Sūtras, have given way to a Dew ethical code In short, the ideals sponsored by the Veda have long since ceased to operate as the exclusive motive force so far as the Indian way of life and thought are concerned There. forc, the claim that no litcrary work has influenced and still conti. nucs to influencc India&amp;rsquo;s cultural life to such a remarkable extent As the Veda can be regarded as hardly warranted It has to be&#xA;THE MAHABHĀRATA : ORIGIN AND GROWTH&#xA;263&#xA;realised that Brahmanism of the Veda has long since disappeared, and Hinduism, which traditionally claims to have derived its inspiration from the Veda but which, historically speaking, bas actually assimilated within itself perhaps more non-Vedic elements than the Vedic ones, has become the dominaot force in the socio religious life of India. And the literary works, which have left an abiding imprint on the socio-religious life sponsored by Hinduism, are not so much the Veda as the popular epics.&#xA;Even, among these popular epics, if there is any one single work which has proved to be of the greatest significance in the mak ing of the life and thought of the Indian people and whose tradi tion continues to live even to this day and influenee, in one way or another, the various aspects of Indian life, it is the Mahābhārata, the great national epic of India. Men and women in India from one end of the country to the other, whether young or old, whether rich or poor, whether high or low, whether simple or sophisticated, still derive enlightenment, entertainment, inspira tion, and guidance from the Mahābhārata. In times of stress and trial, the Mahābhārata has given consolation and brought a message of hope as much to an illiterate villager as to an experi enced statesman, Indian writers, ancient and modern, have found in the stories of the great epic excellent vehicles for the expression of their creative genius. If we were to consider, for instance, the popular folk-songs, or the ballads sung by itinerant bards, or the well-known literary works written in various Indian languages by eminent men of letters, we would find that many of these had drawn their inspiration and material from the Mahābhārata. There is, indeed, no department of Indian life, public or private, which is not vitally influenced by the great epic. It would not be an exaggeration to say that the people of India have learnt to think and act in terms of the Maltābhārata.&#xA;The Mahābhārata is, indeed, a unique phenomenon in the literary history not only of India but of the world. Just consider its extent. The Mahabharata, as we know it today, consists of 1,00,000 stanzas. It is thus by far the biggest single literary work known to man. A comparative statement would, perhaps, make&#xA;264&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;the enormity of the work more patent. The Mahabharata is eight times as big as Homer&amp;rsquo;s Illiad and Odyssey put together; it is, indeed, bigger than all the epic poems in European languages put together. The tradition about the various forms in which the Mahābhārata is known to have existed, as mentioned in the epic itself, is still more astounding. We are told that the great Vyäsa produced the Mfahābharata consisting of six million stanzas. Of these six million, three million are recited among the gods, one an half million among the pilars, one million and four lacs among the Gandharvas, and the remaining 1,00,000 have been assigned to the earth for the human beings. The mythical character of this tradition apart, there is no doubt that it contains some indications regarding the history of the text of the Mahābhārata. This much at least can be safely assumed on the strength of that tradition, namely, that, in its long course, the literary activity, which even tually gave rise to the great epic, was characterised by the processes both of compression and expansion. At this stage, attention may be incidentally drawn to another remarkable feature of the Mahābhārata In spite of its vast extent, the epic does not give the impression of being a motley mass piled up together. Without dilating upon the Mahābhārata as a piece of literary art, one can say with conviction that, on a closer study, one finds .the epic, as a whole, presenting a surprisingly well-balanced and harmonious structure.&#xA;But it is not only its size that entitles the Mahābhārata to the claim of uniqueness. Its contents too are unique in many rese pects. Even a casual reader of the Mahābhārata would be struck by its essentially encyclopaedic character. Indeed, it may be said to be embodying almost all knowledge about Indian religion and mythology, law, ethics and philosophy, statecraft and art of war, and history and ethnology, which had been current in that epocb. Vyāsocchistam jagat sarvam: There is no subject under the sun which the versatile Vyasa, the traditionally recognised author of the epic, has not tackled, The Mahābhārata constitutes a very&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>mahAbhArata critical edition</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/mahAbhArata_critical_edition/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/mahAbhArata_critical_edition/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ud&#34;&gt;THE MAHĀBHARATA AND ITS CRITICAL EDITION&#xA;It is generally believed that the Veda has made the most significant contribution to the moulding of the Indian way of life and thought, through the ages As a matter of fact, ancient Indian culture, or, more precisely, the Hindu culture, as a whole, is not infrequently characterised as the Vedic culture A critical analysis of the Hindu way of life and thought would, however, expose the inadequacy of such characterisation The principal gods of the Vedic pantheon, like Indra and Varuṇa, are now rarely worshipped The elaborate system of sacrifice, which had been evolved and consolidated during the Brāhmaṇa period and resuscitated and reorganised during the Sutra period and which had come to be recognised almost as the hall mark of the Vedic religion, has pow been almost entirely relegated to the back ground The philosophical speculations of the Upanisads have either undergone vital modifications or have been superseded by other systems of thought In short, the values sponsored by the Veda have long since ceased to operate as the essential motive force of the Indian Weltanschauung It is not the Brahmanism of the Veda, but popular Hinduism, which traditionally claims to have derived its inspiration from the Veda but which, historically speaking, has assimilated within itself perhaps more non Vedic elements than the Vedic opes, that dominates the socio religious life of India And the literary works which have left an abiding imprint on the socio religious life sponsored by Hinduism are not so much the Vedas as the popular epics Even among these popular epics, if there is any one single work which has proved to be a factor of inestimable import in the making of the life and thought of the Indian people and which still continues to&#xA;1 Extens on lecture delivered under the auspices of the Mysore Univer sty in August 1961 Inevitably, the first part of this lecture constitutes a sort of summary of The Mahabharata origin and growth which precede this article&#xA;THB MAVĀBHARATA AND ITS CRITICAL EDITION&#xA;293&#xA;be a living force in Indian life, it is the Mahabharata, the great national epic of India.&#xA;The Mahābhārata is, indeed, a unique phenomenon in the literary history not only of India but of the whole world. For one thing this epic, which is traditionally believed to consist of 100,000 stanzas, is the biggest single literary work kaown to man. It is eight times as big as Homer&amp;rsquo;s Ilhad and Odyssey put together. But it is not only its size which entitles the Mahābhārata to the claim of uniqueness. Its contents too are unique in many respects. Even a casual reader of the Mahābhārata would be struck by its truly encyclopaedic character. The Mahābhārata constitutes a dynamic record of an extensive period of India&amp;rsquo;s history - a record which is prepared by poets who possessed a marvellous insight into the lives of men and women belonging to all strata of society. It is well and truly said that in the Mahā bhārata breathe the united soul of Jodia and the individual souls of ber people. But the appeal of the Mahābhārata is not merely Indian or national; it is essentially human or universal. As the author of the epic justifiably claims :&#xA;dharnie cā &amp;lsquo;rthe ca häme ca rrokse ca bliaratarsablia /&#xA;yad ihā &amp;lsquo;sti tad anyatra yan ne &amp;lsquo;hā &amp;lsquo;sti na tat kvacit // In matters relating to religion and ethics, to material progress and prosperity, to the enjoyment of the pleasures of personal and social life, and to spiritual emancipation, whatever is embodied 10 this epic may be found elsewhere; but what is not found here it will be impossible to find anywhere else. Indeed, it will not be an exaggeration to say that there is hardly any human thought or sentiment which has not found expression in the Mahabharata; and there is hardly any situation conceivable in human life which has not been portrayed in it.&#xA;How did this unique work - vast in extent, encyclopaedic in content, and universal in appeal - come into being ? Prima facie, the Malābhārata does not appear to have been the creation of one&#xA;.&#xA;2. MBA, 18.5.38.&#xA;294&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;author or even of one generation of authors. It must have been the outcome of a long and continuous literary activity spread over many centuries, Scholars like DAHLMANN, however, believe that the Mahābhārata is a unified work, that in it two elements - the epic and the didactic - have been artistically welded together, and that this welding together has been accomplished by a single inspired poet. More or less similar views have been put forth by SORENSEN, BARTH, and Sylvain LÉVI. OLDEN BERG, on the other hand, has characterised - justifiably but rather in strong terms - all such attempts at discovering in the&#xA;ibhārata a unified work as constituting &amp;lsquo;scientific monstro sity.&amp;rsquo; He, therefore, advocated the analytical method as the only sound method for the study of the epic. An analytical approach inevitably leads one to the assumption that, through the centuries, the epic has been subjected to several revisions and redactions involving numerous variations, additions, and omissions. This process of constant revision and redaction of the epic has, however, been represented differently by different scholars Adolf HOLTZMANN, for instance, suggested that in its original form the epic was a poem in which the Kauravas were the heroes. Later on, however, on account of changed historical circumstances, the epic was, as it were, set upon its head. It was subjected to a process of tendentious inversion, with the result that the Kauravas, who were the righteous party in the original epic, now came to be represented as the villains, while the Pāndavas, with all their unchivalrous ways, were made the heroes. It is obviously not possible here to examine HOLTZMANN&amp;rsquo;S views at any great length. Suffice it to say that this and similar other theories have to be regarded as being more ingenious than convinciog.&#xA;Let me briefly state my own view regarding the origin and the growth of the Mahābhārata. A critical student of ancient Indian literature knows ibat in the earliest period of the literary history of India there developed, side by side, two distinct literary traditions, which for the sake of convenience I have chosen to call the süta-tradition and the mantra-tradition.&#xA;THE MAHABHARATA AND ITS CRITICAL EDITION&#xA;295&#xA;Broadly speaking, the mantra-tradition related to religious thought and practice while the stīta-tradition related to secular matters and the doings of human heroes. The mantra-tradition consisted of mythological legends, prayers, and panegyrics, magical incanta tions, ritual formulas, and mystic speculations of the ancient Vedic Indiaos, while the sūta-tradition comprised a large amount of popular, bardic, legendary, and historical material. It may be safely presumed that, in the initial stages, both these traditions were fluid in character. In course of time, however, the very nature of the mantra-tradition made it imperative that its contents be properly organised and given a fixed literary form. The early literary monuments belonging to the mantra-tradition have been preserved for us in the form of the Vedic literature. The sūta tradition, on the other hand, continued to remain in fluid and floating condition. No doubt some of its elements had inevitably crept into the mantra-tradition and had been reduced to a fixed&#xA;literary form. Accordingly, in the Vedic literature also we come across such sautic material as the dána-stutis and the gathās, and the pāriplalas and the nārāśamsis. But, by and large, the sita tradition continued to remain fluid for a pretty long time, presumably because there had not been in existence any central motif or any adequate literary pucleus which could have served as a unifying factor for its many and varied elements,&#xA;Such a literary nucleus, however, soon offered itself in the form of a bardic-historical poem relating to the Bhārata war. The antecedents of this war are too well known to need recount ing. As the result of the famous Vedic battle of the ten kings the clan of the Bharatas had attained a kind of sovereignty over the other contemporary states and principalities, both Aryan and non-Aryan.3 The scions of this great clan continued to dominate politically a major part of Northern India almost unchallenged until some time between the 14th and the 12th centuries B. C. About that time, there arose among the Kauravas and the Pandavas, both of whom claimed to be the legal heirs to the&#xA;3. Scc &amp;ldquo;The Disarājāa” published elsewhere 19 thus Volume,&#xA;298&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;couraged these popular religions to a certain extent For, Cher must have soon realised that the challenge of the heterosol movements could not be effectively met by mere revivalist ellorts. A common popular front was required to be built up against them Consequently, most of the popular religions, wila buku variety of gods and religious practices, came to be organised w one single but multi charactered whole, which was held togeul by means of the thin thread of allegiance to the Veda SUCAS the genesis of Hinduism One very significant constituent or all inclusive Hinduism was Krsnaism This Krsoaism se have originated and spread among the tribes of Westen Central India like the Vţsnis, the Satvatas, the Abhiras, and Yādavas 6&#xA;The rise of Krsnaism on the religious horizon of apciems India synchronised with the partially accomplished process of enlarging the bardıc historical poem Java into the epic Bharus This newly created literary monument belonging to the sun tradition had jostantly caught the imagination of the P What wonder then that the practical minded sponsors of Krsus should have thought of employing this popular epic as a You for propagating their religious teaching? They, according redacted the partially completed epic Bharata in such a way as o make it serve their own purpose They started by associating heroes of the epic, the Pandavas, with Krsna Krsna came to represented as a close relative of the Pandavas, codeed as the guide, friend, and philosopher Actually he became the ce figure of the epic, the pivot round which all persons and events the epic revolved All credit is, indeed, due to the remarkable ingenuity and resourcefulness of the Krsnite redactors, WAO brought about these basic changes in the older epic in Suc manner as not to give any cause for even a faint suspicion mi the character of Kssna was really extraneous to the original ep Of course, thc real cornerstone of this Krsnite superstructure was&#xA;6 Sce DANDELAR,&amp;rdquo; Vairogvism and Saivism (particularly, pp 241-249)&#xA;in Insights into Hudl&#xA;THE MAHĀBHARATA AND ITS CRITICAL EDITION&#xA;299&#xA;the Bhagavadgilā. The Bhagaradgitā epitomises the religious, ethical, and philosophical teachings of Krṣņa, and the Krṣpite redactors of the epic must be said to have conceived a very dramatic back-ground and form for it.&#xA;Broadly speaking, the epic Bhārata is thus the result of the operation of two processes on the bardic-historical poem Jaya, namely, of the process of bardic enlargement and that of Krṣaite redaction. It may be noted that the large amount of bardic and egendary material which came to be added to that poem as also the religious teachings and ethical code which came to be propagated through the epic were mostly derived from the non Brahmapic sources. In the religious history of India, two move ments, originatiog in two distinct ideologies, seem to have been jointly responsible for stemming the advance of the heterodox systems of thought, which had strengtheped their position during the interregnum following the Upanisadic period. They were the sūtra-yedariga Brahmanism and the popular Hinduism. By its very nature, however, it was the latter which held the field after the decline of the heterodox religions. But once the danger of the avowedly anti-Brahmanic religions was past, the sponsors of Brahmanism again began gradually to assert themselves. They knew that, though the popular Hinduism represented, in some respects, a definite reaction against Brahmanism, it was not avowedly anti-Brahmanic. It was, therefore, possible to bring about a workable compromise between Brahmanism and the popular Hinduism - that is to say, so far as the present context is concerned, between Brahmanism and Kțsnaism. The sponsors of Brahmanism accordingly attempted to brahmanise, so to say, the popular religion of Krsoa as far as it was feasible to do so. Indeed, they attempted thus to brahmanise several minor popular religious sects. So far as Kęsnaism was concerned, the sponsors of Brahmanism seem to have started their brahmanising operation with the epic Blärata which had, by then, almost come to be regarded as an authentic Kțsnite document. They introduced in&#xA;7. Sec * The cultural background of the Veda&amp;quot; published elsewhere in thuVolumc.300&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;the epic - sometimes in place, but more often out of place - 2 large amount of material relating to Brahmanıc learning and culture Whole tracts dealing with Brahmanic religion and philosophy, law and ethics cosmology and mysticism, and social and political theories found their way into the epic In most of the legends, which came to be newly introduced into the epic Bharata in the wake of this new material, the heroes of the epic came to be represented as tbe defenders of Brahmanic faith and culture In this context, it may be incidenrally pointed out that, in comparison with the methods of the Krsnite redactors, those of the Brahmanic redactors were obviously gross As a matter of fact the activity of the sponsors of Brahmanism ought to be described not as artistic redaction but as flagrant interpolation&#xA;The elements relating to Brabmanic dharnia and nitt were thus superimposed upon the bardic-historical elements derived from the suta tradition and the religio ethical elements derived from Krsnaism - and eventually the Bharata was transformed into the Mahabharata&#xA;The transmission of the Mahabharata (or the śatasālasri Samhita) is characterised by a truly bewildering mass of versions and sub versions Indeed no other work illustrates the dictum &amp;ldquo;as many manuscripts so many texts, more aptly than the great epic This phenomenon of luxuriant growth and indiscriminate fusion of versions can be explained only on the assumption that after its composition the Mahabharata had, in the course of all these centuries been handed down in different forms and sizes from bard to bard througli oral tradition and that therefore, no special care had been taken to guard its text against partial corruption and elaboration or against arbitrary emendation and normalization This state of things must have continued even after the text of the epic had been reduced to writing The epic itself seems to bear testimony to this process, for, while referring to the five direct pupils of Vyasa namely, Sumuntu Jaimini, Paila, Suka, and Vaisam pāyana, it says&#xA;samlitas laih prihakivena bharalasy a prahasılah 8 8 AIBA 1 57 75&#xA;THE MAHĀBHARATA AND ITS CRITICAL EDITION&#xA;301&#xA;Accordingly, even in its early phases, the Mahābhārata text tradition had been not singular and uniform but multiple and polygenous. And this is, indeed, what is to be expected of &amp;amp; work which has proved to be a vital force in the life of a volatile people. The numerous variants, additions, and omissions which distinguish the various versions of the Mahabharata are indicative of the dynamic character of the epic. They cmphasise the fact that thMahābhārata had been organically related to the life of the people as a book of constant inspiration and guidance.&#xA;But it was also natural that, with the advance of scientific Indology which had become evident in India and outside in the course of the past hundred years, the need should have been felt for a critical edition of the Mahābhārata. The credit for first voicing this need, in more or less clear terms, goes to WINTER NITZ who, in his paper presented before the 11th International Congress of Orientalists held at Paris in 1897, laid special stress on this desideratum of a critical edition of the Mahābhārala &amp;ldquo;as the only sound basis for all Mahābliärata studies, nay, for all studies connected with the epic literature of India.&amp;rdquo; There were, no doubt, available in India scveral printed cditions of the epic. The Molībhārata was first published at Calcutta, in four volumes, during the years 1834-39. This was followed in 1862 by the well-loown police edition lithographed in Bombay by Ganpat Krishnaji, who issued the same in printed form in the following year. In South India, there had been current a text of the epic which differed substantially from the texts of the Calcutta and the Bombay editions. All these cditions were, however, sadly deficient from the critical scliolar&amp;rsquo;s point of view, for, they either merely reproduced the version of a particular type of manuscripts or else were eclectic on no recognizable principles and, therefore, failed to remove the uncertainty of the text. WINTERNITZ who was convinced that a critical edition of the Nialūbhūrala was a sine qua non for all historical and critical research regarding the great epic of India,&amp;rdquo; persisted in his efforts, as the result of which the International Union of Academies resolved in 1904 to under take the preparation of such an edition. Funds were raised for&#xA;302&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;the purpose, and a specimen of the edition prepared by LÜDERS was actually published for private circulation among scholars. But then came the first world war which interrupted all scholarly work in the West However, soon after the Bhandarkar Oriental Research Institute was founded in 1917, its workers, in their youthful enthusiasm, decided to venture upon the critical edition, making a fresh start. Accordingly, in April 1919, Ramakrishna Gopal Bhandarkar formally inaugurated the work by writing on the collation sheet the mangala-sloka of the epic :&#xA;nārāyanam namaskrtya naram cai &amp;lsquo;va narottamam/&#xA;devin sarasvatiṁ cai &amp;lsquo;va tato jayam udirayet // Ever since the time when the question of the critical edition of the Mahābhārata was first mooted, it had been clearly realised that, on account of the peculiar manner in which the epic had been transmitted through the centuries, it was not possible to apply to it the special canons of textual criticism which were derived from a study of classical ( Greek and Latin ) texts and which depended ultimately upon there being a more or less complete concatenation of copies and examplars reaching finally back to a single authentic written archetype. It was, therefore, necessary to tackle the problem of the Mahābhārata textual criticism in a different manner. The method of the Mahabharata textual criticism bad to be evolved only from a special study of the Mahābhārata manuscripts and of the peculiar conditions of the transmission of the text of the epic And such a study made it clear, almost at the very beginning, that an eclectic but cautious utilization of all manuscript classes was the only method which could be fruitfully employed in respect of the Mahābhārata. Since all categories of manuscripts had their strong points and their weak points, each variant had to be judged on its own merits A text constituted on eclectic principles, with due circum spection, was bound to present a more faithful picture of the elusive &amp;quot; original” than any single extant codex could do.&#xA;9. This is usually regarded as the first stanza of the A1Bk. Critical Edition rightly treats it as a benedictory stanza.&#xA;But the&#xA;THE MAHĀBHĀRATA AND ITS CRITICAL EDITION 303&#xA;I shall now attempt to state-of course, in broad outline - the methodology of the Mahābhārata textual criticism adopted by the Institute. The first step was obviously the search for and collection of as many manuscripts of the epic - that is to say, manuscripts comprising the entire epic ( which however are rare) or a group of parvans or a single parvan (which last are the most numerous) - as possible.&#xA;The collection of manuscripts was followed by the collation of manuscripts. For this purpose, the text of the epic popularised by the commentator Nilakantha was taken as the vulgate. The various manuscripts were compared with the vulgate, letter by letter, and the differences in readings, etc., were carefully recorded. This collation-work was a stupendous task involving many lacs of collation-units.10 Of course, not all the collected manuscripts were thus collated. The dictum which served as the main guidiog principle in the matter of the selection of manuscripts was that, in textual criticism, it was not the number of manus-, cripts of a given text but the number of independent versions of that text that really mattered. In this connection it was observed that manuscripts written in a particular script, which were more or less exclusively derived from the region in which that script was used, usually represented a distinct version. This is the reason Why the various versions of the Mahābhārata are, except in one case, denoted in the critical edition by the names of the relevant scripts. 11 It must, however, be pointed out that the case of the Devanāgari script was peculiar in that it was a sort of a .vulgar script, widely used and understood in India. Similarly, as has been already indicated, the process of free comparison of manus&#xA;10. The following figures may be found interesting : number of manus cript examined : 1,259, number of manuscripts actually used : 734; sumber of collation-units : (approximately) 49,20,000.&#xA;11. The version which is not denoted by the name of a script is Kashmiri (K). For all practical purposes, this version may be regarded as having been made up of Devanagarl transcripts of the Sāradā (%) manus cripts. See infra.&#xA;304&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;cripts and extensive mutual borrowings had always been in evidence, and the Devanagari was the chief medium of contami nation between the different recensions and versions Another criterion for the selection of manuscripts for collation was their age Old manuscripts, even though fragmentary and partly illegible, were preferred to modern looking manuscripts, though complete and well preserved Within a version discrepant types were chosen in preference to similar types&#xA;A critical study of the voluminous collations pertaining to any parvan of the Mahabharata at once brings out the fact that the epic has been handed down in two major recensions or text traditions, namely, a Northern (N) recension and 1 Southern (S) recension Further, it also shows that cach of these recensions is characterised by a plurality of versions, cach of which latter again contains a multiplicity of sub groups The Northern recension is represented by the manuscripts written in the scripts of Āryāvarta, such as Sarada, Nepall (Newari) Maithill, Bengali, and Devinigarl, while the Southern recension is represented by the manuscripts written in the scripts of Daksina. patha, such as Telugu, Grantha, and Malayalam Apart from these scriptal differences, the two recensions differ in the matter of the division of the Mahabharata into its various parvaps ror instance, against the commonly adopied conventional division of the cpic into eighteen parvans, there is a Southern tradition of&#xA;vision of the epic into twenty four parvans Besides this the manuscripts of the two recensions show numerous other discrepancies, big and small discrepancies in the spelling of the most ordinary words, c &amp;amp; N irida S srila or rrila, especially of proper names N Naimṣa, S aimiśa, in the readings of words, phrases, lines, and stanzas, in the scquence of all these clements, 111 the relative position of single adhy lyas, and in the relative sequence of wholc crisodes &amp;ldquo;Then there are numerous additions and omissions It may be pointed out that the Southern&#xA;12 Hanums po in a few other kt pts have also beon tatminto account for the criticated won&#xA;THE MAHĀBHÄRATA AND ITS CRITICAL EDITION&#xA;305&#xA;recension is longer than the Northern recepsion, because of the additional passages which have been distributed all over that recension of the epic. The story in the Southern recension is richer in details and elaborate in treatment. Altogether that recension gives the impression of a deliberate attempt at precision, schematization, and a thoroughly practical outlook. The Northern recension, on the other hand, is vague, unsystematic, and inconse quent. The Southern recension, which may be said to present the textus ornatior, is marked by a distinct ethical bias and is full of septentious maxims, while the Northern recension contains a naively narrated story. In spite of these differences between the two recensions of the Mahābhārata - differences which must not by any means be underrated - the two recensions also reveal a distinct and undeniable family resemblance. In other words, a study of the manuscripts belonging to the two recensions unmistakably leads us to the conclusion that they must have been independent copies of a single orally transmitted text.&#xA;The stemma codicum or the genealogy of the Mahābhārata manuscripts may then be represented somewhat as follows: The Ur-Mahābhārata, the origin and growth of which I have already attempted to trace, had, at some stage in the course of its oral transmission through different rhapsodists who recited the epic differently, consolidated itself into two distinct text-traditions or recensions, namely, the Northern recension and the Southern recension. The Northern recension is then seen to have branched off into two major sub-recensions - the North-western sub recension and the Central sub-recension. The North-westera sub-recension further gave rise to two versions, namely, the Säradā and the Kashmiri versions, while the Central sub-recension grew into two groups, the Eastern group, comprising the Nepāli, the Maithili, and the Bengāli versions, and the Central group which is represented by the Devanagari version. The Southern Tecension seems to have branched off into two sub-recepsions - the Eastern sub-recension comprising the Telugu and the Grantha Versions, and the Western sub-recension comprising the Malaya lam version.&#xA;39&amp;hellip;&#xA;306&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;Now something about the main characteristics of the different versions : The Sāradā version which is, in a sense, an isolated version, being least contaminated with other versions, preserves the text of the epic in a more or less pristine form. It has, accordingly, proved to be of the greatest value for the critical edition. The Kāshmiri version is quite peculiar, for, though the manuscripts of this version are written in the Deva pāgari script, they show an unmistakable textual affinity with the Śäradā version. These manuscripts have, indeed, to be regarded as Devanāgari transcripts of the saradā versioD. Here, then, is a case where the script of the manuscripts does not determine their text-critical value. The Nepali, the Maithill, and the Bengali versions often go together, showing minimal mutual variations. Though the unitary character of the Bengali version becomes easily manifest, that version tooks, in many cases, like &amp;amp; sub version or an Eastern extension of the central Devanāgari version. The composite character of the Devanagari version becomes evident from the features of both the Northern and the Southern recensions partaken by it. The Telugu version stands on the border-land of the Northern and the Southern recensions, but its essential character as a version affiliated to the major Southern textual tradition is unmistakable. Among the Southern versions, the Telugu and the Grantha versions are closer to each other, while the Malayalam version often stands by itself. Indeed, in a sense, the Malayalam version may be regarded as being in relation to the Southern recension what the Sarada version is in relation to the Northern recension.&#xA;Apart from the large number of manuscripts belonging to the various versions mentioned above. certain testimonia or aids of a particular or subsidiary character have been used by way of critical apparatus for the critical cdition of the Mahabharata. Thcsc testimonia normally consist of (1) the adaptations of the cpic like the Javanesc adaptation Bläratam ( about A. D. 1000) And the Telugu adaptation by Nannaya (about A. D. 1025 ) called Andhra Bhūralamu, (2) the epitomcs in Sanskrit like the Bhāratamarjari of Ksemondra (about A. D. 1050 }, the Bald.&#xA;THE MAHĀBHĀRATA AND ITS CRITICAL EDITION&#xA;307&#xA;ud&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;--&#34;&gt;&amp;ndash;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;bharata of Amaracandra Süri (13th century A. D.), and the Pāndavacarita of Maladhāri Devaprabha (16th century A. D.), and (3) the various commentaries on the epic, like the Jhāna. dipika of Devabodha (early 11th century A. D.7), which is, incidentally, the oldest available commentary, the Viṣamasloki of&#xA;Vimalabodha (between A. D. 1150 and A. D. 1300), the Bhārata i rthaprakāśa of Sarvajña Nārāyaṇa, the Bharatārthapradipikā of&#xA;Arjunamiśra (15th century A. D.), the Laksālanikāra of Vādirāja (16th century A.D.), and the Bhāratabhāvadipa of Nilakaotha (17th century A. D.).&#xA;It is on the basis of all this elaborate critical apparatus that | the text of the epic is finally constituted. It is neither possible&#xA;nor necessary to dilate. here, upon the canons which have governed the copstitution of the text in the critical edition. Some broad indications may, however, be given here. The first principle of the Mahābhārala textual criticism is to accept as original a reading or a feature, which is documented uniformly by all manuscripts alike. In other words, in order that a reading or a feature should be regarded as authentic, it must satisfy the condition of the originality of agreement between what may be proved to be inore or less independent versions. The rule arising out of such agreement between independent recensions or versions, which may be stated as N=S=constituted text, is easy to compre hend and simple to apply: only its sphere of operation is rather restricted. Difficulties arise when there is fluctuation; and that is the normal state. When there is such fluctuation, the choice falls, as a corollary of the previous rule, upon a reading which is documented by the largest number of more or less independent versions, and which is supported by intrinsic probability. The presumption of originality in these cases is frequently confirmed by a lack of definite agreement between the discrepant versions. Uccasionally we get « double&amp;rdquo; agreement, that is, agreement&#xA;etween two or more groups of each recension; for instance, the Sarada and the Kashmiri versions of the Northern recension agree with the Malayālam version of the Southern recension, and simul taneously, the Bengālī version of the Northern recension agrees&#xA;308&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;with the Telugu and the Grantha versions of the Southern recen sion. In these circumstances, one of the agreements must, generally speaking, be accidental, since both can hardly be original; and either may de adopted if they have equal intrinsic merit. However, owing to the much greater correctness and reliability of the Sarada and the Kashmiri versions, the readings of this group have, as a rule, been adopted in the critical edition, other things being equal.&#xA;The general tendency in the course of the transmission of an ancient text is to simplify a difficult word or expression. A common rule of textual criticism, therefore, is that a lectio difficilior is more origipal than a lectio facilior. Similarly, grammatically irregular forms are more original thap regularised variants. This holds good also in the case of the Mahabharata. Therefore, solecisms, when shown to be original by a clear agree ment on this point between independent versions, have been all owed to stand uncorrected. In this connection it should be remembered that the original text of the epic may not have been necessarily a correct text or a felicitous text throughout. Attention may also be drawn, at this stage, to another rule of textual criticism, namely, that a textus simplicior is generally more origi pal than textus ornatior. Further, as a general rule, preference is given to a reading which best suggests how the other readings may have arisen. Another important rule which the editors of the Mahābhārata have scrupulously observed is that, irrespective of the result that it may lead to, the objective documentary evidence must be, as far as possible, the final deciding factor in the constitution of the text. In other words, interpretation must be given precedence over emendation. Accordingly, emendation has played a very inconspicuous role in the critical edition. Actually it has been resorted to merely for the purpose of unify. ing divergent and conflicting manuscript evidence, never in opposition to clear and unanimous testimony of manuscripts. The editors have always been careful not to force their subjective views in the matter of the constitution of the text. Wherever the manuscript evidence in respect of a line, phrase, word, or word.&#xA;THE MAHẤBHARATA AND ITS CRITICAL EDITION 309&#xA;part is equally balanced, this fact is indicated by a wavy line printed under that element of the text. A wavy line is thus used when the transmitted readings appear to be obviously corrupt or when the Northern and the Southern receasions offer two different readings of equal value or when the evidence pro et contra of documentary and intrinsic probability is equally balanced. Inci dentally it may be added that the high hopes entertained by some scholars that the Parvasamgrahaparvan would supply a decisive clue for the reconstruction of the original Mahabharata have been found to be not well founded.&#xA;What did the critical edition aim at and what does it claim for itself? To begin with, it must be pojated out that the critical edition did not aim - indeed, it could not have aimed - at presenting anything like the original copy of the epic as Vyāsa may bave written it. It did not also aim at a reconstruction of the Ur-Mahābhārata, that ideal but impossible desideratum. It did not, again, seek to reproduce the text of the poem as recited by Vaiśampāyana before Janamejaya or even by the Sūta before Saunaka. The critical edition modestly aimed at presenting a text of the epic as old as the extant manuscript material permitted with some semblance of confidence. If the editorial work has been done properly, the critical edition may claim to embody the most ancient text of the epic accordiog to the direct line of transmission - a text which is purer than others in so far as it is free from the obvious errors of copying and spurious additions, The constituted text may claim to be the ancestor of all the extant manuscripts of the epic. As indicated above, the constituted text is not necessarily a correct text from the grammatical point of view por a felicitous text from the literary point of view. It contains loose and archaic lipguistic forms and constructions, apacoluthons and lack of syntactical concord. There remain many contradictions and superfluities. There is an evident lack of literary finish. These features - and aren&amp;rsquo;t they natural in dynamic poetry? - must have been inherent in the old poem. Where they are met with in the critical text, they are documented by the manuscripts themselves or at least are inferable from them310&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;with a high degree of probability. The critical edition has only cleansed the text of the Mahābhārata of puerile modern accretions and obvious errors of repetition. On the other hand, it has rescued from undeserved oblivion many an authentic archaism. which had been gradually ousted in the course of the transmission of the text.&#xA;The critical edition of the Mahābhārata claims to be an edition in the preparation of which all the important extant versions of the Great Epic have been taken into consideration and all important manuscripts collated, estimated, and turned to account; it is, further, an edition in the preparation of which the various collateral testimonia have also been critically utilized, Another important feature of this edition is this : Since all diver gent readings of any importance are given in the critical notes printed at the foot of the page, this edition, for the first time, renders it possible for the reader to bave before him the entire significant evidence for each individual passage. The value of this method for scientific javestigation of the epic is obvious. Further, since not even the seemingly most irrelevant line or stanza actually found in a Mahābhārata manuscript collated for the edition is on any account omitted, this edition of the Maha bhārata is, in a sease, more complete than any previous edition, It is a veritable thesaurus of the Mahabharata tradition,&#xA;[First published: IAC 11, 1962, 39-53. ]&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monarchy checks</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/Monarchy_checks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/Monarchy_checks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;ATHARVAVEDA VII, 12 &amp;ldquo;CHECKS ON MONARCHY : POPULAR ASSEMBLICS&#xA;Introduction&#xA;Though the normal form of state in ancient India had been monarchy, sufficient care was taken to see that it did not tend to degenerate joto autocracy. The ancient Indian monarch func tioned under various checks - direct or indirect, constitutional or otherwise.&#xA;(1) Firstly, it was cmphatically laid down that Dharma (= law) was superior to Kṣatra (=sovereign power of the king): Indeed, Dharma was described as the “ Kṣatra of Ksatra.&amp;rdquo; A passage in the Brhadāranyaka-Upaniṣad,1 for instance, sets forth three significant principles of ancient Indian polity, namely, (a) that the society cannot flourish in the absence of any of its four constituents - Brahiman, Ksatra, Vis, and Sūdra, (b) that Brahman or spiritual power is the source of Kṣatra or martial power, and (c) that Dharma or law is the ultimate authority in social and political matters. The Upaniṣad points out that there is nothing higher than Dharma and that Dharma serves as a solid guarantee even for a weaker man against the possible oppression by a stronger man. The absolute supremacy of Dharma thus constitutes one of the most basic concepts of ancient Indian social and political philosophy.&#xA;(2) Then there was the Purohita who, as the embodiment of Brabman, functioned as the inevitable mentor of the king not only in spiritual but also in temporal matters. Ailareya-Brāhmaṇa VIII. 24-27 asserts that a king is by no means self-sufficient he has to depend on the Purohita for his spiritual and temporal well being and progress. The Purohita is said to possess five formi dable powers. &amp;ldquo;Surrounding the king with these powers (for his protection ) he stands like the sea (surrounding) the earth.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>saMvAdasUkta</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/saMvAdasUkta/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/saMvAdasUkta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THE SANVĀDASŪKTA IN THE ATHARVAVEDA&#xA;The Samvadasūktas or dialogue-hymns constitutc one of the distinctive features of Rgvedic hymnody. Various views have been put forth by scholars regarding the genesis and nature of these hymns. OLDENBERG, for iastance, speaks of the ancient Akhyānas or narratives made up of prose and verse and suggests that only the verse-portions of some of such narratives, which were perhaps supplemented by extempore prose additions by the narrator, are preserved in the form of the so-called Samvāda sūktas. He, therefore, characterises these hymns as ākhyāda hymns. CHARPENTIER, however, regards these hymns as pieces of epic poetry which do not need any additional prose.* OLDEN BERG&amp;rsquo;s Akhyāna-theory is rejected, among others, by HERTEL and VON SCHROEDER, who look upon these hymns as frag ments of ritual dramas. W. H. RIDGEWAYS who emphasizes the religious origin of drama, HILLEBRANDT, WINDISCH, ind Sylvain LÉVI according to whom the Samvadasūktas are like some sort of rough sketches of drama, support the Vedic drama heory, While accepting the essential dramatic character of the Samvādasūktas and the probability that they presuppose some kind of Drśya entertainment, some scholars have expressed doubt as to their connection with ritual.&#xA;There is also the suggestion - which can be hardly accepted - that the Sanvādasūktas are merely the result of the Vedic poets&#39;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SOMATISM OF VEDIC PSYCHOLOGY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/SOMATISM_OF_VEDIC_PSYCHOLOGY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/SOMATISM_OF_VEDIC_PSYCHOLOGY/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Manas is the buman faculty which is usually associated in the Veda with a variety of psychological activities. The considera tion of the genesis of the Vedic concept of manas brings forth a number of unique characteristics of that human faculty. Let us first approach the question of the origin of the concept of manas from the linguistic point of view. It is believed by some scholars that the words, manas, manus, manyu, mensch, mann, etc., are derived from the Indo-European (IE) root men- which has the sense of thinking&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;mental activity&amp;rsquo;, etc. The possibility is thereby suggested of the notion of man as a thinking being&amp;rsquo;, having been prevalent even in a very remote period. The anthro pological investigations have, however, led to a doubt as to whether the proposed etymology is correct. The idea of man as a thinking being&amp;rsquo;, as against beasts and other creatures who are supposed to have been denied the faculty of thinking, cannot possibly have prevailed in that age. The primitives generally did not believe in any kind of essential differentiation among the several aspects of creation, whose existence was, according to them, wholly dependent upon a universal all-penetrating magic fluid like Aronda or the Vedic asu.? It was the amount of such magic fluid, and not the possession or non-possession of any special mental or physical faculties, that determined the gradation among the beings io the universe.&#xA;There is another fact to be noted in this connection. A fair kuowledge of the human anatomy on the part of the IE people has given rise to a large number of words denoting several parts of the human body, which are to be found in many IE languages and which are linguistically connected with one another. It may be further observed that the words, in several IE languages, de poting&amp;rsquo; sensations&amp;rsquo;, &amp;rsquo;emotions, and other such non-physical (or&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two births of vasiShTha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/Two_births_of_vasiShTha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/Two_births_of_vasiShTha/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THE TWO BIRTHS OF VASISTHA A FRESH STUDY OF RGVEDA VII 33. 9-141&#xA;Gantertācarjasamsmrtyai rasisthasye &amp;lsquo;ha janmanoh | karoti nutanām vjakhyam rāmo vāsısthagotrajah&#xA;It is suggested that every regular family book (mandala ) of the Rgveda contains what may be called a family-hymn, the main purpose of which is to glorify the progenitor of the family and to celebrate some special attainments and characteristic cxploits of that family as a whole Such family hymds usually occur at the end of the group of hymns relating to Indra, for, it is believed that the peculiar distinction achieved by the family is essentially the result of Indra&amp;rsquo;s benign favour. The thirty third hymn in the seventh mandala of the Rgveda has, accord 10gly, to be regarded as the family-lıymn of the Vāsiṣṭhas who are traditionally recognised as the authors of that mandala ?&#xA;The Anukramanı of Katyāyana characterises RV VII 33 as a samstava, which term is explained by the commentator Sad gurusisya as sahastuti In other words, according to Kätyāyana, the hymn contains mutual laudation by Vasistha, the progenitor of the family, and his descendants As the commentator has ela borated, in the first nine stanzas, Vasistha praises his descendants,&#xA;me&#xA;1 For facility of reference, those stanzas have been reproduced at the end of this paper&#xA;2 katyayana&amp;rsquo;s Sarvanukyamapi says saptaman mandalat vasest ho &amp;lsquo;pasyal This is confirmed by Sayana and Sadgurusisya Also cf Arsenukramapi agni nara si to etat saptamant mandala pran sir Dasistho dugo murd, arunayok sutok / It may be addel that agnim narah are the init al words of the first hymn of the seventh book Apart from this scholastic evidence, attention may be drawn to the facts that a majority of the hymns in this book end with the typical refrain of the Vas athas (97) at prila svastıbh 1 sada nah), that the name Vas stha (whether un singular or in plural) occurs in this mandala, as many as 43 times and that the imprint of Vas ṣba&amp;rsquo;s personally, style, and idcology is quite unmistakable in many of the passages in this mapdala&#xA;te may berita bola den that was phase iphone in plaas iba&amp;rsquo;s pers&#xA;THE TWO BIRTHS OF VASISTHA&#xA;99&#xA;while, in the last five, the descendants praise their great ancestors According to Saunaka&amp;rsquo;s Brhaddevatā (V 163 ff ), the hymn is a dialogue-hymn — the Sarianukramanı also alternatively suggests : vasiṣthasja saputrasye &amp;rsquo;ndrena 1ā samvadah &amp;ndash; or it is merely an Indrasukta, a hymn in praise of Indra Both these views, how ever, seem to be upacceptable&#xA;Actually the present hymn is a kind of ballad which seeks to glorify Maitrāvarun Vaststha, the progenitor of the Vasistha family, and shows many of the characteristics of a ballad For instance, like a ballad, it is made up partly of direct speech, whereby either the bard himself assumes the roles of the different characters in the story and speaks out their speeches (1 and 4. of Indra, 14 of Agastya) or he rhetorically addresses the person who is being glorified, samely, Maitrāvaruni Vasistha (as in 10 and 11), and partly of narration in the third person The hymn is further characterised by such features as repetition (eg be gingings of the first three quarters of 3, 9 cd and 12 cd), ellipsis (9, 10, 14 ), absence of proper sequence of stanzas, impromptu addition (12 b), and parenthesis (12 a), which are common to oral poetry like ballad + That the central theme of this hymn 15 the glorification of Vasistha is skilfully brought out by the poet by deliberately introducing the word vasistha, whether in singular or in plural and in different cases, in all its stanzas, In this connection, it may be pointed out that, even where the word occurs in plural, it can be understood as referring to the progenitor of the family himself, the plural having been used as a token of respect (ādararthe)&#xA;3 GELDNER (Der Rig Veda, Part II, p 211 ) adds A Vási tha as the tpokesman of the whole family proclaims, in the presence of his ancestor, the latter&amp;rsquo;s glory and indirectly that of his descendants Indra joins in this glori fication and supplements (st 1 4) as it were the parralion by that Vísisha&#xA;4 Indeed most of these features may be said to distinguisb Vassthas style generally&#xA;5 This Iterary device, which, nadcntally, is rarely met with in the Raredo, also confirms the ballad-character of the hymn&#xA;6 The only passage where the plural tasishab u used unequnocally to denote the descendants of Maiträvarudi 13 st 4 (cf vab pilpum in 4a, it 19&#xA;(Continued on the next page)&#xA;100&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;This family hymn of the Vāsiṣṭhas can be divided into three clear-cut sections (a) 1-6 Vasistha personally called upon Indra (st 1 abhi pra manduh, the Gopatha-Brāhmaṇa 2 2 13 also says that Vasistha was the only seer who had personally seen Indra sayo va indram pratyaksam na &amp;lsquo;paśyams tam asistha eva pratyaksam apaśyat) and won him over to his own side, that is to say, to the side of the Trtsus and the Bharatas (2), and, through Indra&amp;rsquo;s favour (3) and Vasistha&amp;rsquo;s priestcraft (4) prayers (5), and leadership (6) the Trtsu-Bharatas became victorious in the Dasarajña, (b) 78 Vasistha was a master of mystic knowledge and inimitable priestly prowess, and (c) 9-14 the two births of Vasistha It will be easily realised that the sequence of these three sections should properly have been the other way round namely, first, the section dealing with Vasistha&amp;rsquo;s double birth, secondly, the one eulogising the special attainments of Vasistha, and, finally, the one celebrating the victory in the Daśarajña&#xA;The story of Vasistha&amp;rsquo;s birth has, obviously, to be regarded as the core and kernel of this whole hymn For, it is, indeed, the peculiar character of the birth of Vasistha which may be said to distinguish him essentially from the other Vedic seers More over, while the other two topics namely, Vasistha&amp;rsquo;s priesterait and his positive role in the Dasarajña, have occurred in several other passages in the seventh book, a more or less detailed refe rence to his miraculous birth is to be found only in the present hymn Four things need to be clearly borne in mind before any attempt is made to analyse the section dealing with the birth of Vasistha (9-14) First, the various stages in this story have not been set forth here in their proper sequence It is, therefore, necessary to rearrange many of the quarters (pādas )&#xA;(Cont pued from the last page) interesting to notc that, even here the plural trnamn refers to the greal ancestor ) St 1 sccms to be contextually connected with VII 18 21 (cl pra mandih in 33 1 a and pra amamaduh in 18 21 a), and since in the latter passage, Parasara batayitu and Vas atha arc mentioncd, the plural pasistha in 33 id may also be understood as referring to Vas stha and some of his descendants&#xA;THE TWO DIRTHS OF VASISTHA&#xA;! 101&#xA;of these six stanzas so as to make them yield a logically consistent account. Secondly, the word vasiṣtha, whether used in singular or in plural in these stanzas, is invariably to be understood as referring to the progenitor of the family of the Vāsiṣṭhas. Thirdly, the various features of ballad-poetry, mentioned above, parti cularly ellipsis and mixing up of third person narration and second person locution are quite conspicuous in this part of the hymn. And lastly. this hyma evidently constitutes a kind of an appendix to the original Samhita - among other things, it does not have the usual refrain - and thus contains many ideas which are reminiscent of a slightly later age.&#xA;The poet begins by proclaiming (9 ab) that he (te : used ādararthe), that is, Vasistha, alone (11), on account of the light of his heart (hrdayasya praketaih) or inper vision, moves about freely in, that is to say, is quite familiar with abhi saṁ caranti) the thousand-branched mystery sahasravalsam ninyam) that this manifold and multifarious phenomenal world is. The use of the present tense, in this context, is intended to suggest that such knowledge was natural and innate to Vasiṣtba. Since Vasiṣṭha already possessed that knowledge, he did not feel either any curio sity or any enticement in respect of being born in this world and actually experiencing the various vicissitudes of the worldly life or saṁsära. And yet, he did become inclined to take birth in this world, because, as the poet tells us (9 c), he wanted to weave fur ther (vayantah) the garment (paridhn) which Yama had started weaving (yamena tatam ). Yama was, according to the Vedic mythology, the progenitor of the human race. This idea is ex pressed here through the imagery of the starting of the weaving of a garment. Every one is obligated to see that the weaving of this garment, which Yama has initiated, continues uninterrupted ly, lest the buman race itself may otherwise eventually disappear from the face of the earth. It is verily this reasoning which&#xA;7. CE. VII. 33. 8 a : szryasyo &amp;lsquo;va vaksatho Jyodir eṣām. 8. To be understood in the desiderative sense.&#xA;9. Scc : DANDEKAR, &amp;ldquo;Yama in the Veda&amp;rdquo;, Vedic Mythological Tracts, 118-140.&#xA;102&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;underl.es the concept of pier-rna (= debt which one owes to his fathers), which is one of the three major debts that it is incumbent on every one to requite.10 Vasistha thought of taking birth in this world not because he was in any way enamoured of this samsåra - he alreadly had the innate knowledge of all its secrets, good and evil, without having had to get physically involved in it; but there was this obligation of ensuring the uninterrupted conti. nuity of the human race.&#xA;The pādas 9 ab are usually interpreted as if they referred to Vasistha&amp;rsquo;s behaviour after his advent in this world. Vasistha is said to have moved about fearlessly within the thousandfold mystery of this world. 11 This is, however, too literal and obviously pointless. Moreover, with such an interpretation, the words hrdaj asya praheraih would lose all their significance. So too would the reference to the weaving further of the garment of the human race. This latter reference actually provides a definite cosmic-ethical motivation for the event of Vasistha&amp;rsquo;s birth, and undoubtedly elevates, though perhaps indirectly, the character ol Vasistha. The poet seems to have been particular about this point. That is why he repeats that statement once more in 12 cd, where, incidentally, the desiderative sense is clearly brought out (vayisyan). The deliberate use, in 9 ab, of the present tense abhi san caranti, which verb, in view of the phrase hrdayasya praketaih, is necessarily to be understood in a figurative sense, and of the narrative past (upa seduh) in 9 cd, should not be underestimated. The verse-halves, 9 ab and 9 cd, have, therefore, to be syntactically joined to each other with some such words as&#xA;and yet words which the bard presumably did utter while singing the ballad. It was only with a view to fulfilling his cosmic ethical obligation of promoting the continuity of the human race that Vasistha, as the poet tells us (9 d), approached the celestial nymph (apsarasah: plural ādararthe) with reverence (upa seduh)&#xA;10. Cf. Tasttriya-San. VI. 3. 10.5 : jayamano vai brahmanas tribhur fraud dyato brahmacaryepa (subhyo yajñena deocbhyah prajayd patybhyah.&#xA;11. Cf, for instance, VELANXAR, Rgpeda Mapdala VII, English Trans lation, p. 86.&#xA;THE TWO BIRTHS OF VASISTHA&#xA;103&#xA;due to a mother.12 The päda 12 d confirms this by stating that Vasistha was born of the celestial nymph (apsarasaḥ pari jajñe pasisthah). How did this happen?&#xA;Once upon a time, Mitra-Varuņa (Mitrāvarunau ) were pre vailed upon by means of salutations (13 a : isitä namobhih) to attend a long Soma-sacrificial session (sattra), which was being performed by Viśve Devāh (mentioned in 11 d). Indeed, they were ioitiated to officiate as priests (jätau) at that saftra. There they happened to see the celestial nymph Urvasi (mentioned in 11 b), who was also present at the satira presumably to participate in the ritual drama connected with the sattra, and, were intensely allured by her superb beauty. They could not control their passion, and, suddenly and simultaneously (13 b: samânam) discharged their fecundating fluid (relah sisicatuh ), which was eventually collected in a jar (kumbhe).&#xA;The dual of jātau and iṣıtā (in 13 a) leaves no doubt that those two participles have to be connected with Mitrāvaruņā, who have been mentioned in 10b - mitrāı arunā being the only noun in dual in the present context. The phrase satire ha (13 a) is interpreted variously. It is read (against the Samhitāpātha and the Padapātha) as satrā ha; and the phrase satrā ha jātau (= verily, born together ) is then understood as emphasizing the simultaneous birth of Mitra-Varuṇa.13 It will, however, be agreed that the mention of the simultaneous birth of Mitra Varuṇa has no relevance whatsoever to the main theme. More over, changing the reading sattre ha to satrā ha would seem to be quite upwarranted. It is alternatively suggested that one might analyse sattre lia in the Sanhitāpātha as safrā iha (against the Padapātha ): Mitra-Varuṇa arrived (jätau = prāptau) at that place (tha) together (satra). Such a reference too is hardly pertinent. On the other hand, it may be pointed out that, with out the assumption of a satira, it would be very difficult ratio&#xA;12. &amp;ldquo;The poet rouses the curiosity and sustains the interest of his audience by such casual but pregnant statements.&#xA;13. The two phrases salrd jalau (13 a) and samanan sificatur ( 13 b) are said to denote some kind of correspondence.&#xA;104&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;Dally to explain the simultaneous presence of Mitra-Varuṇa Viśve Devāh, and Uryası at one and the same place 16 In the present context, the word jātau is used in the technical sense of diksitau (initiated) The Artareya Brāhmaṇa (VII 22 4), for instance, clearly states that one who gets himself initiated is, 10 deed, born again from the sacrifice yajñād u ha vā esa punar jāyale yo dik sate Mitra Varuṇa did not attend that sattra as its dividities It is also obvious that, in that sattra, they were initiated as officiating priests and not as sacrificer ( Yajamāna), for, they are said to have been persuaded with salutations to be present at the sattra and accept the priestly office Attention may be incidentally drawn here to the character of Mitra Varuṇa as divine priests 16 It may also be presumed that the Maitrāvaruna, who is one of the sixteen principal priests of the later Vedic ritual, has something to do with the priestly character of Vedic Mitra Varuṇa For, while the names of most of these sixteen priests are indicative of their specific functions in the ritual, that of the Maitrāyaruna seems to have been directly derived from his divine prototype&#xA;The suggestion that Mitra Varuṇa were seduced by Urvasi by means of obeisance ([ urvaśyā] namobhih 15ıtā) in attending the sattra is evidently unwarranted it clearly militates against Urvasi&amp;rsquo;s role in this drama as indicated in 11 b (it would, indeed, appear from 9 d that Urvasi did not take any initiative but had to be induced to mother Vasistha ), against the statement in 13 b (which suggests suddenness of action on the part of Mitra Varuṇa), and also against the usual story-motif prevailing in similar situations in Indian legends It would seem that, when Mitra-Varuṇa happened to have a glimpse of Urvasi, their erotic emotion was roused and they could not control the consequent sudden (as seems to have been implied by the word samānam ) discharge of their semen. In order that that potent fluid should&#xA;14 Thc Sarodnul ramon and the Bihaddevald also speak of a sallra&#xA;15. Dumezil suggests (Lidéologue in parte des Indo-Europeens) that, from among the threc functions, namely, of priests warriors, and producers, that of the priests is represented in Vedic mythology by Mitra Varuṇa,THE TWO BİRTHS OF VASISTHA&#xA;VOS&#xA;not be wasted or should not cause any damage by falling on the ground, it was made to flow into, that is, it was collected in a jar.16 Before proceeding with the further details of the central theme of Vasistha&amp;rsquo;s birth, the poet tells us ( 13 cd )- almost parenthetically-that, out of that semen (tatah), verily (ha), arose ( ud iyāja) Māna or Agastya from the middle ( madhyāt) of the jar, 17 and that the seer born out of that very semen they call Vasistha (tato jātam rsim āhur vasistham).18 The words fatah madhyāt (13 c) are also interpreted as tasya kumbhasya madhyāt (from the middle of that kumbha) and tataḥ (13 d) as tasmāt kumbhat bahh (outside the kumbha)! But this is rather farfetched and also unnecessary. It is, however, possible to understand tatah (in 13 d) in the sense of thereafter&amp;rsquo;, for, Vasiṣṭha is traditionally believed to have been born after Agastya and to have accordingly been Agastya&amp;rsquo;s younger brother,20&#xA;Now to revert to the main theme (11 cd ). While the fecun dating fluid of Mitra-Varuṇa was being collected in the jar (13 b), a drop of it fell out. But the sacrificers Vißve Devāh, pre sumably apprehensive of the disaster which that drop might cause if it was allowed to reach the ground, promptly held it fast upon a lotus (drapsaṁ skannam viśye devah puskare adadanta). It was of course by no means easy to tackle with that concentrate of virsle power, but Viśve Devāh were cnabled to do so with the help of the divine, magically potent spell (darvyena brahmana)&#xA;16 The Sarudnukramani on RV I, 166 says that it was the jar of the vasalivari water,&#xA;17. This explains why Māna, which is only another name of secr Aga stya, 13 also known as Kumbhayoni.&#xA;18. This may be regarded as another instance of the bardic device of making a pregnant statement in a more or less casual parenthetical manner and thereby holding the interest of the audience. One may also note the ballad-like ring in 13 d&#xA;19 According to the Sardanukramani on RV. I, 166, both Agastya and Vanxha were born out of the semen in the jar, Sadgurusiqya says : tatah kumdhan mahaghasad agastya-basishap ajayelim The Byhaddepata (V. 151-152), on the other hand, states that Vasıfjha was born on the ground (sthala) while Agastya took birth in the jar.&#xA;20. Thu tradition is confirmed by 10 d and 14.&#xA;14.&#xA;106&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;wbich they commanded 21 And here the bard, rhetorically addressing Vasistha, says In that Viśve Devāh held up that drop of the semen of Mitra-Varuṇa on a lotus, they actually &amp;quot; held you&amp;rdquo; (na adadanta) 22 It may be added that, in this context, the word två is used proleptically&#xA;How this was so is explained in 10 ab This passage is ex ceedingly elliptical As has been mentioned above, Vasistha wanted to take birth in this world in order to weave further the web of Yama He now saw the most propitious opportunity to do so Moving away from, that is to say, abandoning his natural essential existence, Vasistha, like a flash of lightning as it were (vidyuto jyotih [ iva), entered into the drop of the semen of Mitra-Varuṇa, which had been held up on a lotus by Viśve Devāh, with a view to taking birth out of that drop The imagery of the flash of lightnjog suggests, on the one hand, the resplendence that constituted the original basic form of Vaṣistha, and, on the other, the spontaneity with which Vasistha decided to avail himself of the unique opportunity for carrying out his cosmic ethical mission Approvingly, Mitra Varuṇa watched Vasistha abandoning (part sam pihånam, in the secondary seose) his natural essential form and entering into the drop of their semen and blessed him When (yad in 10 b) this happeged, an important phase of the great event of Vasistha&amp;rsquo;s first birth may be said to have been accomplished (10 c) Incidentally it may be pointed out that it is possible to interpret 10 a as (When Mitra Varuṇa saw you) going away from your original lightning ( splendour-) form (vidyutah ab! ) to the mass of light (Jyoth acc ), that is to say, to the drop of semen But, as indicated above, the earlier interpretation would seem to be poetically more apposite&#xA;It was at this stage that Urvası, the celestial nymph, interve ned. She came to know that Vasistha, having forsaken his subtle essential form, had entered into the drop of the semen of Mitra.&#xA;21 Brāhmaṇa dayana is to be syntactically connected not with skannam, but with adadanta (from the root dd to grasp, to hold fast&#xA;22 By means of this statement, the bard again rouses the curiosity ol the audience&#xA;THE TWO BIRTHS OF VASISTHA&#xA;107&#xA;Varuṇa. She also realised that a female agency, in some form or the other, was necessary in the process of the germination of that seed. Presumably the poet wanted to suggest that Urvasi received some kind of inner reverential appeal from Vasistha himself this might be implied by 9 d: apsarasah upa sedur vasisthāh&amp;ndash; and was thereby induced to act as she did. She meditated upon that seed, and this eventually resulted in the birth of Vasıṣtha,23 “ You, o Vasistha &amp;ldquo;, says the bard addressing him, &amp;ldquo;are, verily, the child of Mitra-Varuṇa, and at the same time, you, o Brahman, are born from the mind of Urvaśī&amp;rdquo; (11 ab). The appellation, Brabman, may be taken to have been used here proleptically.** The interpretation of urvaśyāḥ in, 11 b as an ablative form (&amp;ldquo;born from Urvaśī— from [her] mental power&amp;rdquo;) is rather odd. Similarly to suggest that urvaśyah may be understood as an object-genitive and may be figuratively connected with manas in the sense of passion&amp;rsquo; (&amp;rsquo;t born out of the passion (of Mitra Varuṇa for Urvası”) is ingenious, but it manifestly misses the main point. The word manas in this context denotes the mental activity on the part of Urvasi. She fixed her mind (abhidhyāna) on the drop of the semen of Mitra-Varuṇa caught up by Viśve Devāh on the lotus, thereby exercising her volition (sanikalpa) that a son be born out of that drop. The birth of Vaṣiṣtha was not the result of any normal physical activity - Vasistha was not yonija - and this fact at once establishes the superhuman cha racter of his birth.25&#xA;“This, then &amp;ldquo;, says the poet, &amp;ldquo;was your one (first) birth (10 c).20 When Agastya took you ( and introduced you) to the clan (of the Tetsus; cf. St. 6), (there occurred your other&#xA;23. It would thus be clear why, in Il cd, the holding up of the drop of the semen (drapsa) on the lotus was regarded as being tantamount to the holding of Vasıfsha himself (fa). Attention has already been drawn to the proleptic use of tua in that context.&#xA;44 Sec the sequel 25. This Lind of abnormal birth, parucularly in respect of great persona. lities, is a common motif in the mythologies of the world.&#xA;26. GELDNER, Der Rig Veda, Part 2, P 213, joins the words ula ekath rasistha syntactically to 10 d.&amp;rdquo; This is your (one) birth, and the other) onc, o Vasiffha, (was) when&amp;hellip;.&amp;rdquo;.&#xA;108&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;[second] birth )&amp;rdquo; (10 d ) 27 The Padapātha reads viśah with the accent on the second syllable When it is so accepted, the form silah has to be understood either as ablative singular or genitive singular The passage is, therefore, translated as “When Agastya brought you from the clan (viśah, abl.) (of gods to the clan of men But this is unacceptable, for, there has been no indication whatsoever of Vasistha&amp;rsquo;s having belonged to the clan of gods It is possible to take visah as accusative plural (of course, ignoring the accent) and translate : &amp;ldquo;When Agastya brought you over to the Tștsu people (cf St 6)&amp;rdquo; But, idiomati cally, the accusative would not go quite well with a jabhara Under these circumstances, one would feel inclined to ignore the Pada pātha and read yıse (dat sing 28&#xA;Before proceeding to elaborate the second birth of Vasistha the bard proclaims (12 a) presumably with a view to reiterat ing the initial statement made by him in 9 ab, that “ (Vasistha ), being endowed with inner light ( sapraketah), had the full prior knowledge (pravidvan) of both ( ubhayasya) (his births)” It may be noted that the word sapraketah establishes a corres pondence between 12 a and 9 ab, which seem to echo each other This correspondence is further confirmed by the near identity of 9 cd and 12 cd However, here again we have to go against the Samhitāpātha and the Padapatha and read sapraketah instead of sa praketah (which latter would hardly make any sense) One cannot think of interpreting praketah as an adjective, for, if no where occurs in the Rgveda as an adjective Nor would it be natural to read prakete (loc ) and translate it with “in (that is, on account of his inner light&amp;quot; In view of the whole context, there is hardly any doubt that ubhayasya refers to the two births and not, as sometimes suggested, to the two worlds, heaven and earth, or to the two peoples, divine and human The pada 12 b contains some kind of impromptu statement made by the bard, but its sense is not at all clear&#xA;27 This pida as elliptical&#xA;28 Perhaps as a lesser cul! In none of these cases, however, will it be necessary to change the Sambıtāpatha, ufa ajabhara&#xA;THE TWO BIRTHS OF VASISTHA&#xA;109&#xA;Mitra-Varuņa and Urvasi were responsible for bringing Vasistha into this phenomenal world. But mere biological birth was not going to help Vasiṣṭha in the fulfilment of his cosmic ethical mission. It was at best only a necessary precondition. What was now needed was what may be called a social birth or a socio-ethical personality.29 Agastya, the elder brother, is, there fore, said to have presented Vasistha to the clan of the Títsus urging them to receive him as their Purohita.30 Addressing the Trtsus, Agastya says: &amp;ldquo;Here would Vasiṣṭha come unto you, o Pratrds (14 d); do you receive him with honour, entertaining good will (for him)” (14c). The Pratçds32 are evidently to be identified with the Tįtsus mentioned in st. 6 of this hymn. For one thing, both names are derived from the same root trd. Further, the name Prated would easily remind one of Pratardana who was one of the early kings of the Trtsu-Bharatas.92&#xA;What is, however, particularly important for our present pur pose is that, while introducing Vasistha to the Pratsds, Agastya emphasizes the special priestcraft of Vasistha (14 ab). The pâdas 14 ab are variously explained. It is suggested that 14 ab form a part of the narrative, while 14 cd constitute the direct address of Agastya to the Títsus. In that case, bibharti ( narrative present) in 14 a is connected with ā jabhāra in 10 d. and its subject is taken to be Agastya. Agastya, bearing the Soma-crush ing stone (grāvānam bibhrat; grāyan to be understood as the symbol of the Adhvaryu&amp;rsquo;s office), that is, in his capacity as the Adhvaryu, takes (bibharti) Vasiṣṭha, who is a bearer of Ukthas (that is, a master of the Rgvedic ritual; Hotr) and a bearer of Sāmans (that is, a master of the Sámavedic ritual; Vågāts), to the Trtsus, and announces before them (agre pra vadāti: &amp;ldquo;Here would Vasistha . etc.&amp;rdquo;. It must, however, be pointed&#xA;29. In a similar context, the Manusmp. II. 147-148 uses the two signi ficant words, sathbhan and jāli,&#xA;30 Does this indicate that Agastya was originally the Purohita of the Tfisus, and that, while returiog, le recommended his younger brother Vasisha for that august ofice ?&#xA;31. This name occurs but once in the Rgoeda, 32. Cl. Kathaka-Sat, 21, 10; Kausitaki-Up. 3. 1.&#xA;110&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;out that strictly speaking the root hhr has two altogether diffe rent senses in bibhart, and a jabhira There is, again no point in referring to Agastya as the Adhvaryu And, finally, the charac terization of Vasıṣtha as a master of both the Rgicdic and the Sāmavedic rituals is quite unwarranted A far better sense could be derived from st 14, if that whole stanza was regarded as consti tuting the speech of Agastya &amp;ldquo;(This one, here ) &amp;ldquo;, says Agastya to the Titsus ( 14 ab), &amp;ldquo;supports (bibharti) the supporter of Ukthas (the Hot) and the supporter of Sūmans (the Udgült), (and he also supports him who) is the supporter of the Soma crushing stone (the Adhvaryu ) (elliptical, jah) gravanam bibhrat (sarjate tam api bibliariil), and (he alone) may speak with authority in front of all of them (agre pra vadall)&amp;rdquo; 11 will be clear that this entire description in 14 ab applies aptly to the Brahman Agastya eulogiscs Vasistha as the Brahman par excellence The significance of the appellation brahman prolepti cally used with reference to Vasistha in 11 b may now be properly realised The Brahman generally supervises and maintains in order (bibharti) the activities of the other three principal priests (who are here denoted by means of the symbols of their special functions, namely, Uktha, Saman and graian) It is again the Brahman who has the authority to sanction (pra vadati), as it were, the performance of the various sacrificial rites * We often find, for jostance, that, when the Adhvaryu announces that he would start a particular rits, the Brahman is required to acquiesce before the Adhvaryu actually starts that site Incidentally, in&#xA;officiating as ahvaryu namely to interpret 1400 the reual as&#xA;33 Or agre (san) = being at the forefront of the r tual as it were&#xA;34 It would be incorrect to interpret 14 ab as if it referred to Vasistha&amp;rsquo;s role as the Adhvaryu pamely as This here, bearing the gravan that is officiating as the Adhvaryu supports the Hotr and the Udgate and at the beg aning of a site ( ago) gives out a call pra vad att prais) for act on on the part of the other pr ests The Adhvaryu can hardly be regarded as&#xA;supporting the Hots and the Udgatp It is also not 1 kely that the phrase pro vadån denotes the pra sa of the Adhvaryu (aha s the ward normally used in such contexts) Nor again 35 Vas stha known for hs adhvaryava Inci dentally it may be ment oned that pra vad in ( makes a sound ) 13 some times connected wth gridan (yah) agre pra vadalt (tan) gr wanar biblural This is manifestly farfetched&#xA;THE TWO BIRTHS OF VASISTHA&#xA;111&#xA;view of the comparative lateness of this hymn (to which a reference has already been made ), such specification of the duties of the four principal priests of the Vedic ritual may not be regarded as anachronistic, It is quite understandable that Agastya should have recommended Vasistha to the Pratṣds in such glow ing terms, for, Vasiṣṭha, though a seer of the Rgveda, has been traditionally recognised as a master of Atharvanic practices, and, therefore, as being best qualified to officiate as Brahman and Purobita,35&#xA;Rgveda VII. 33. 9-14&#xA;tá in ninyám hrdayasya praketaih&#xA;sahásravaltam abhí sám caranti / yaména tatám paridhim váyanto&#xA;&amp;lsquo;psarása úpa sedur rásisshāh || 9 // vidyúto jyótih pári samjihānan&#xA;mitráiárunā zád ápasyatān iva / tát te jánimo &amp;lsquo;ai &amp;lsquo;kam vasiṣthā.&#xA;&amp;lsquo;gástyo yát nā viśá ajabhára // 10 // utá &amp;lsquo;si maitrāvarunó vasistho&#xA;Prváśyā brahman mánasó &amp;lsquo;dhi jätaḥ / drapsář skannám bráhmanā daivyena&#xA;víśve devaḥ páskare två &amp;ldquo;dadanta // 11 // sá prakerá ubháyasya pravidvant&#xA;sahasradâng tttt và sảdanah ! yaména tatán paridhim vayisyánn&#xA;apsarásah pári jajñe vásiṣthah // 12 // sattré ha järấv isilá námoblih&#xA;kumbhé rétah sisicatuh samānám /&#xA;35 Cf. Taittiriya Sam. III, 5.2.1 : tało zasisthapurohitih prajah pragdyanta tasmad vasıfjho brahma karyah prai &amp;lsquo;oa juyals.&#xA;112&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;túto ha mana sirt tayo madhya!&#xA;sáto jätám éṣını dikur sásiṣthanı // 13 // ukthabhrtam sāmablıçram bibharlı&#xA;grávānam biblırat prá vadīty ágre/ upai nam ādham sumanas) amāna&#xA;á 10 gacchali pratrdo vásisthah || 14 ||&#xA;I First published Hernann Cuntert Gedenkschrift, Innsbruck 1979, 425-432 )&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VARUNA, VASISTHA, AND BHAKTI</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/VARUNA_VASISTHA_AND_BHAKTI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/VARUNA_VASISTHA_AND_BHAKTI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The sage Vasistha has played a very significant role in the cultural history of ancient India. There is, indeed, hardly any period of the Vedic and the Epic ages on which Vasiṣṭha and his family have not left the special stamp of their almost inimitable personality. Even if one restricted oneself to the copsideration of the period of the Rgveda, one would not fail to be struck by the remarkable contribution made by Vasistha and the Vasiṣṭhas, particularly to the socio-political and religious aspects of the culture of that period. As the Purobita of Sudās Bharata, Vasiṣṭha was vitally javolved in the &amp;ldquo;battle of the ten kings &amp;ldquo;, victory in which ultimately gave Sudās supremacy over the entire contemporary Aryandom. But Vasiṣṭha&amp;rsquo;s contribution to the religion of the Rgveda was perhaps of a far greater consequence. It is well known that, at a certain stage in the evolution of Vedic religion and mythology, there inevitably developed a kind of conflict between the older Varuṇa-cult and the newer Indra-cult. The credit for bringing about a compromise between these two cults and thereby avertiog a schism in the Vedic community largely belongs to Vasiṣṭha. The group of hymns in the seventh mandala relating to Indrāvaruņau ( 82-85) bear ample testimony&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Veda cultural background</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/Veda_cultural_background/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/Veda_cultural_background/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THE CULTURAL BACKGROUND OF THE VEDA&#xA;It is generally believed - and, to a large extent, rightly believed that a proper understanding of the Veda affords the master-key which can uprave many a problem relating to ancient Indian culture and civilization. Every serious student of ancient Indian civilization, therefore, begins, naturally enough, by asking himself the question: What is the Veda? Let me also then, by way of a general introduction to my lectures, today begin by posing such broad questions as : What exactly is connoted by the term, Veda? What is its real nature? What is its extent and what its cultural background?&#xA;When we speak, in more or less general terms, of Sanskrit language and of Sanskrit literature, we are actually speaking of two languages and of two literatures. In other words, there are, strictly speaking, two Sanskrit languages, the Vedic Sanskrit and the Classical Sanskrit, the one being distinct from the other in respect of several essential linguistic characteristics. Corres pondingly, there are two Sanskrit literatures, the Vedic literature and the classical Sanskrit literature, the one being distinct from the other in respect of nature, extent, and cultural background. I shall try briefly to elaborate this point. In what way is the Vedic language distinct from the classical Sanskrit? It is well known that the science of comparative philology has established the position of Sanskrit as a very important member of the family of Indo-European languages. It is, however, not so very well known that by &amp;ldquo;Sanskrit&amp;rsquo; is here meant principally the Vedic language and not so much the classical Sanskrit. The implica tions, from the linguistic point of view, of what I have just now said are indeed manifold. Without, however, going into the details of this question, I shall only emphasize what is pertinent to our present purpose, namely that, so far as the study of Indo&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vedic period antecedents</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/Vedic_period_antecedents/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/Vedic_period_antecedents/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THE ANTECEDENTS AND THE EARLY BEGINNINGS OF THE VEDIC PERIOD&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On this occasion,&amp;quot; I propose to place before you, for your consideration and criticism, some of my ideas relating to the antecedents and the early beginnings of the Vedic period. A considerable amount of work of really sterling merit has been done in this field by generations of scholars — Indian as well as foreign. I am, however, inclined to think that, generally speak ing, the Vedic period has been studied, up till now, more or less as an isolated period. Efforts must now be made to fix up that period into the whole scheme of the history of India, which latter, in its turn, must be properly linked up with the history of the world. In other words, we must not study the various problems connected with the Vedic period, each by itself; we must study them all together, mutually correlating, at every stage, the results of our investigations in each case, To my mind, any attempt in the direction of reconstructing the history of the Vedic period, to the fullest possible extent and with the highest possible plausibi lity, must necessarily be governed by the consideration of the following five points : (1) The relation of the Vedic Aryan with the other Indo-European-speaking people of the world. As I shall presently endeavour to show, the Vedic period of Indian history began, in more senses than one, outside the geographical limits of India - that is to say, outside the geographical limits of the pre-15th of August India, and most certainly of the post-15th of August India. (2) The relation of the Vedic Indians with the Harappan civilisation, more generally known as&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VEDIC RELIGION AND MYTHOLOGY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/VEDIC_RELIGION_AND_MYTHOLOGY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/VEDIC_RELIGION_AND_MYTHOLOGY/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A Survey of the Work of some Western Scholars&#xA;In 1805, Henry Thomas COLEBROOKE published his essay, &amp;quot; On the Vedas, or Sacred Writings of the Hindus,&amp;rsquo;&amp;ldquo;1 and thereby became entitled to the distinction of being perhaps the first Western scholar ever to write at some length about the Veda.&amp;rdquo; In this essay, COLEBROOKE deals with what may be called the * externals&amp;rsquo; of the Vedic literature rather than with its contents. He gives, mainly on the strength of the manuscripts coliccted by himself, the first sketch, in any European language, of the Rgreda (RV) and, to a smaller cxtent, of the other three Vedas. He also speaks of the Vedic rṣis, the various Vedic schools, and the Vedic commentaries, and incidentally touches upon the question of the authority of the Veda. He further refers to the Aitareya Brāhmaṇa, tre Sarikhāyana-Brīlimana, and the Sarapatha-Brālt mana. From among the Vedangas, hc mentions the Sūtras only in passing, but he emphasises the importance of the Nirukta and evinces special interest in Jyotiṣa. About the Vedic religion and mythology as such he has hardly anything to say. Whatever information about the Veda COLEBROOKE has given in his essay is generally correct, but his writing also shows that he had not made any deep study of the Veda. Indeed, COLEBROOKE cannot be said to have even formed a proper estimate of the Veda. He says that the Vedas are far too extensive to be trans lated in entirety and that the ancient dialect in which they are written is exceedingly difficult and obscure, and further adds that their contents are such as would render such translation bardly rewarding either to the reader or to the translator, COLEBROOKE&amp;rsquo;s attitude towards the Veda was thus somewhat resigned&amp;rsquo;, and,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>vena sUkta</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/vena_sUkta/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/vena_sUkta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THE VENA SŪKTA IN THE ATHARVAVEDA&#xA;The first sūkta in the second kanda of the Atharvaveda (AV) has, according to the Anukramani, Veda for its rst and brahman atman for its devatā WAITNEY characterises the hymn as mysticł, while WEBER2 and, following him, GRIFFITHS mention&#xA;glorification of the prime cause of all things&amp;rsquo; as its theme in spite of the fact that the Kaufika Sūtra (37 3) and the commen tary on the AV prescribe this hymn, wholly or in part, for addressing various articles out of whose behaviour afterward signs of success or the contrary, and the like oracular responses, are to be drawn, its essential philosophical character becomes quite evident even on a cursory reading Indeed, this sukta-parti cularly its first stanzas which it is proposed to discuss here at some length – is very important from the point of view of the development of Indian philosophical thought This whole sukta appears with many variants as a part of the Mahanarayana Upa. misad (2 3-7 = Taitt Ar X 1 4, VS 32 8-12)&#xA;Various views have been put forth about Vena The commentary on the passage in the Tartt Ar says veno nāma&#xA;1 Atharvaoeda Translat on and Moles (HOS 7), 37 f WHUTNEY speaks of a bit of labored obscurity in connection with this hymn He further adds that kandas 4 and 5 of the AV also begin with saktas which are rendered deli berately obscure&#xA;2 Ind Stud 13, 129 ff 3 The Hymns of the Atharva Veda Vol 1, 41 ff&#xA;4 The Va land-Sutra prescribes the third stanza of thu hymn in the Upa casatha rite of the Agn cagana&#xA;5 The stanza reads&#xA;venas tat pafyat paramar guha yad yatra osoath bhavaly ckarzpam dath prfnir aduha jayamanal&#xA;sparrido obhyandsala dh II 6 Mahindrayapa Upanisad 23, which corresponds with AV I I I. Teads Denas tal pasyan o frd bhutanani o doon yatra noanh bhavaty skandam&#xA;yasmin dari sari ca o cau &amp;lsquo;kam sa olak prolaf ca nbhu prajasu // Accordiog to Bhattabhāskara, thus tzaza contains a description of rupaprapanca&#xA;134&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;gandhariaha AV II. 1 2 also suggests the identity of Vena with Gandharva This identity seems to be further confirmed by RV X 123, which has many points in common with AV II.1? In RVI 83 5, on the other hand, Surya is referred to as Vena Vena is elsewhere characterised as sūryasya subuh and is accord ingly identified with the rainbow. The commentary on AV II I I explains Vena as Aditya or as parjanyātmā madhyamasthāno devaho Nārāyana, in his Dipikä on the Mahānārājana-Upanisad, seems to derive the word vena from the root ve (to weave) and accordingly paraphrases it as venah visvasūtrakrt 10 It is not relevant for our purpose to examine these interpretations of the word vena in detail It may only be pointed out that in the present context it would be appropriate to understand the word in its derivative sense WEBER rightly refers, in this connection, to the Zend root vaên (to see ) 11 Vena, therefore, means &amp;ldquo;seer&amp;rsquo; 12 Significantly enough, Vena is traditionally mentioned as the rs113 of AV III It is pertinent to note that, in the first stanza of the sūkia, the word vena is actually connected with the Verbal form passat&#xA;The object of paśyat is tar This tat is qualified by two relativo clauses, namely, ja parantam guha and zatra viśiam&#xA;6a CF AV II 12 ob pra lad voc d amplasya tiduan gandharto diama paramath guhajat&#xA;7 Attcation is, for instance, drawn to the common expressions occurring in the two bytas such as prsnih, samanath yonim, abhyanaṣala bah It is suggested that the playsıcal characteristics of Vena Candharva disappear, more OT Icus, in all,&#xA;&amp;amp; AL X 123 1 9 ROTit and GRASSVANY Identify Vena mentioned in the Sankhdyana&#xA;Brahmone WhartabiliAskara desire) a&#xA;10 Bhattabhāskara also interprets the word etymologically He connects it with the root trn ( to desire) and explains Vena as the Lord who willed the creation of the universo Bhattabhåskara explains Sandharpa as go dharogaft 11, that w as neda imalajaa Accord ng to hitn, Gandharva is the divine principic in which expressions remain as mystic sound&#xA;meletala biharta yang permologically&#xA;Pouple in mu&#xA;12 Czune (110S 33 ) translates tona in RV I 83 5 as spy&amp;rsquo; Thc word 11 explained in tic rullo as a synonym of medhacun (3 19 3 ) or of&#xA;te (19 5) It is also explained as sarralokakantah (10 38 1 )&#xA;13 ct flur darlandTHE VENA-SŪKTA IN THE ATHARYAVEDA&#xA;135&#xA;ekarūpam bhavati. Tai denotes the entity which is the highest one (paramam), and which is hidded or secret or esoteric (guhā), that is to say, which is beyond the comprehension of ordinary men.14 In other words, tat stands for the ultimate philosophical reality.15 Only a “seer&amp;rdquo; (Vena) can have a true knowledge of it; indeed, Vena does not only &amp;ldquo;koow&amp;rdquo; it in an indirect manner, but he &amp;ldquo;sees&amp;rdquo; it, that is to say, he has a direct intuitive perception or realisation of this ultimate reality.18 The use of the words, vena and paśyat, is thus very significant from the point of view of the real objective of Indian philosophy which is not merely indirect knowledge but direct experience or realisation.&#xA;Now this ultimate reality, which is the same thing as the prime cause of the universe, is described as that in which the universe becomes of one form. Here we find the later Upanisadic doctrine in its germinal form. In the Upanisads, the first cause is said to be one, uniform, and subtle, but its effect in the form of the universe to be many, manifold, and gross.12 Essentially, the universe is but a fiction of names and forms,18 it is not different from the ultimate reality. What transitorily appears as visa ( many, manifold, gross ) is, before it issues forth from the one cause (at the so-called creation), and also becomes, after it is absorbed into the one cause (at the so-called dissolution), ekarūpa (one, uniform, subtle ),19 The paraman guha, wbich Vena “sees” thus clearly reminds us of the Upaniṣadic brahman or sat. The doctrine set forth in the first half of AV II. 1. 1 is seen to have been further elaborated in the Upaniṣads.&#xA;14. The clausetat paremat guhi pat may be variously explained as yat paramai yac ca) guhy, tal (as accepted above), or as yat guha, lat paramam (that highest entity which is hidden), or as guna ja paramari, tat (that cntity which is the highest among the secret ones). In the ultimate analysis, however, the sense is the same in all these interprctauons.&#xA;15. Onc may recall, in this connection, the lat of the Upaniyadic tat fram asi.&#xA;16. It is said that Indian philosophy is often referred to as darsana for this very reason.&#xA;17. Cf. Ch. Up. 6.2. 1-4;6.8. 7. 18. Cf. Ch. Up. 6.1, 14; 6. 3. 2. 19. C. Taittiriya Up. 3. 1.&#xA;136&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;If in the second quarter of AV II. 1. 1 we find the Upaniṣadıc doctrine of sat (or brahman) and jagat in its germinal form, in the third quarter we find the classical Sãókhya doctrine of prakril in its germinal form. Prśni is here said to have produced (aduhat), on the one hand, idam, and on the other jāyamanah The word prsni usually means &amp;ldquo;spotted one,&amp;rdquo; &amp;quot; one of variegated colour,&amp;ldquo;30 The Sankhya praksli, which represents the state of equipoise of the three gunas &amp;ndash; sattva, rajas, and tamas-, is often described as being of three colours - white, red, and black respectively corresponding with the three gunas. One may recall, in this context, the she-goat (ajā), of the Svetāśvatara-Upanisad, which is red-white-black.21 This she-goat also is suggestive of the Sānkhya prakrt1.22 While, in AV II. 1. 1c, the concept of the Sānkhya prakrti is visualised in the form of a cow (?) of varlega. ted colour, in the Upanisad, it is visualised in the form of a red white-black she-goat. Peśni (= mūlaprakrti) produced idan, that is, the material world, on the one hand, and jāyamānāḥ of generations of the human race, on the other. It will be seen that, according to this interpretation, aduhar is understood to mean &amp;quot; yielded by way of milk&amp;rdquo;,&amp;ldquo;produced.” Just as a cow (prśni) yields or produces milk, so too prśni (mülaprakrti) yields or produces idam and jāyamānāh. WEBER23 seems to understand duh in the sense of sto milk” and not of “to yield milk.&amp;rdquo;** According to him, Prśni is the &amp;quot; milker&amp;quot; and not the &amp;ldquo;yielder of milk.” He so construes the quarter that it means that Prśoi milked out jāyamnānäh from idam (Prśni correspondiog to the&#xA;20. Like the word vena, the word prsni also is interpreted variously aj &amp;quot; the cloud regarded as the mother of the Maruts,&amp;rdquo; or as &amp;ldquo;the common name of sky and sun,&amp;rdquo; or as &amp;ldquo;the principle of abundance symbolised by water.&amp;rdquo;&#xA;21. Seet&#xA;or as &amp;quot; the Prince of the Marutes interpreted ,&#xA;22. It may be noted that ad also means &amp;ldquo;the unborn onc&amp;rdquo; and the Sankhya pralli 13 avikylt (that is to say, it 19 not the effect of anything ).&#xA;23. Op. cf, 130.&#xA;24. Duh has both these senses. Cf. to mdk: dudoha guth sa yanad (Raghu. I. 26); to yield mulk : kuman dugdhe Diprakarsaty alakṣmim (URG 5, 31).&#xA;THE VENA-SŪKTA IN THE ATHARVAVEDA&#xA;137&#xA;milker, idam to cow, and jāyamānal to the milk). Further, according to WEBER, idam stands for tat paramani gultā in the first half of the stanza. GRIFFITH follows WEBER. It would, however, be strange if one and the same entity was referred to as lat in the first half of the stanza and as idam in the second, without any special reason. Similarly, if, as suggested above, tat implied the one ultimate cause (the Upanisadic brahman), it would not be convincing to posit by its side any other entity of equal status like Pęśni which was supposed to have extracted the beings (jājamānah) out of that tal. Further, when the word prsni clearly denoted a cow, it would not be appropriate if it was made to mean a &amp;ldquo;milker,&amp;rdquo; Attention may also be incidentally drawn to the impropriety of a peuter word idam being made to suggest something which is milked from rather than something which is milked out.&#xA;This whole incongruity has arisen on account of the attempt made by WEBER and others to combine the two halves of this stanza syntactically as well as ideologically. As a matter of fact, two distinct doctrines have been adumbrated in this stanza &amp;ndash; tho Upanisadic doctrine of brahman in the second pāda and the classical Sankhya doctrine of prakrtı in the third pāda. The word idam in the third pāda need not be connected syntactically with the word fat in the first pāda; actually it implies something which is quite different from what is implied by tat. In the present context, idam (this) may be best interpreted as &amp;ldquo;this that we sce round about us,&amp;rdquo; that is to say, the world, particularly the material world. The sarnıkrstatva (nearness) suggested by this demostaatérve Mamun and the zeder yerden und voila siguificant here. The word jāyamānā(fem. acc. pl.) obviously stands for the generations of human beings that are being born. It is not quite necessary either to add here any substantive like prajäh or to connect jayamánál with vrah in the fourth pada. The word jāyanânâh may itself be understood in the sense of prajūl.&#xA;Now the idea that Pțśni produced this material world on the one hand and the human beings on the other may be&#xA;18&#xA;138&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;compared with the process of creation according to the Sankhya This latter can be represented in the following forms.&#xA;prakrti&#xA;nahat (intellect)&#xA;panica tanmārrāni (five subtle primary elements)&#xA;ahamkāra (individuality)&#xA;pañca mahābinutanı&#xA;panca pañca manas (five gross elements )&amp;quot; jñanendrijas karmendrijas (mind)&#xA;(five sense. (five organs&#xA;organs ) of action )* The aspect of creation indicated by five tanmätras and the five malabhūras derived from those fannātras clearly corresponds with the material world (idan of AV II 1 1c), while the aspect of creation indicated by alamkāra, the five mñanendrijas, the five karmendriyas, and manas corresponds with the generations of human beings ayamānáh of AV II 1 1c) 80&#xA;It is suggested that we might so emend the text of the third pāda as to read jayamana (fem nom sing ) for jāyamanah&#xA;25 Sankhya Kaniku 3&#xA;malaprak tır avikylı mahadadyah prakrliorkyta) ah sapta/&#xA;fodasakas ca vrtáro na prakılır na viktih puruṣah // The tabulated form given above follows the interpretation of Vijnana Bhiku According to Vacaspatı, ahankara evolyed from mahai and from ahamikor there evolved the five tanmatras on the onc hand and the ten senses and mind on the other (CE S N DASGUPTA, A History of Indian Philosophy, Vol 1, Pp 225 26 ) Vynana Bhikṣu s interpretation 15 more rational&#xA;26 sabda, sparfa rupa rasa, and gandha 27 akasa, vayu, tejas ap, and prihuvi 28 srotra tvak, caksuh, rasand and ghrana 29 vak, pani, pada payu, and upastha&#xA;30 The significance of the occurrence of the stage of mahal between prakrtı on the one hand and the two aspects of creation on the other is casily understandable&#xA;THE VENA-SUKTA IN THE ATHARVAVEDA&#xA;139&#xA;(Tem. acc. pl.) and then connect this jāyamānā with the sub stantive prsnih.si It is further suggested that the clause might then be made to mean that Prśni, who was born (of fat or brahnian), on her part, produced idam (jagat). In other words, Peśni is to be understood as the creative power32 (or mājā) of tat-a kind of Demiurge who operates on behalf of iar which by its very nature is not prone to any action. Pęśni is accordingly supposed to play the role of Isvara. Such an inter pretation may fit in with the Vedāntic theory of creation, but we would hesitate to accept it in the present context. And this, for the following reasons. Firstly, the emendation of jāyamānāḥ into jāyamāna is quite unwarranted. Secondly, the word jāyamānā literally means “ being born&amp;quot;, and this meaning will not suit the suggested interpretation. For, Prśni cannot be thought of as “having produced” (aduhat) something while she herself is * being born.&amp;quot; On the other hand, jāyanānal in the sense of &amp;ldquo;those that are being bora&amp;rdquo; would suggest the continuous process of the birth of generations of human beings. It may also be added that, from the strict Vedāntic point of view, īśvara or mājā is not &amp;quot; born” of the brahman. It is, therefore, more reasonable to vaderstand jāyamanah in the sense of prajah and as the second object of aduhat,33&#xA;The fourth pâda of this stanza refers to the fact that hosts of beings, who discovered light for the first time (that is to say, who were afforded the opportunity of being born ), shouted in joy at this great wonder of creation.31&#xA;AV II, 1, 1 may thus be regarded as reflecting two currents of philosophical thought which must have been in vogue in its&#xA;31. WHITNEY, Op. cit.&#xA;32. According to GRIFTITII ( Op ), Prsai bere appears, like the cow Audhumbla of the Scandinavian mythology, to represent the creative power of Naturc.&#xA;33. To the third pada, ca has to be taken as being understood, connecting the two objects of adulat, namely, idam and jajananch.&#xA;34. Not at Vena&amp;rsquo;s realisation of the highest reality (as nuggested by some),&#xA;140&#xA;EXERCISES IN INDOLOGY&#xA;time. One of these is seen to have been further developed in the Upanisads and the other in classical Sānkbya. It is a patent fact that the so-called philosophical suktas of the AV do not set forth any one consistent and connected doctrine. Rather, they usually embody stray and mutually unconnected philosophical coocepts.&#xA;[First published&#xA;Aftrashi Felicitation Volume, 1965, 24-30.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
