<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Indology exercises on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Indology exercises on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>ANCIENT INDIAN POLITY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/ANCIENT_INDIAN_POLITY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/ANCIENT_INDIAN_POLITY/</guid>
      <description>A proper integration of the interests of the individual and the society may be said to constitutc the central problem of all social philosophy So far as the ancient Indian thinkers were concerned, they had developed in this field two distinct disciplines, namely Dharmaśāstra and Arthaśāstra. As a matter of fact, the ancient Indian concept of Dharma is very comprehensive and touches all aspects of man&amp;rsquo;s relation with the society. One such aspect is political in character and often manifests itself in the form of the relation between the subject and the state.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>dAsharAjJNa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/dAsharAjJNa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/dAsharAjJNa/</guid>
      <description>TIC DĀśARAJÑA
(Some time ago a friend and colleague wrote to me asking me a few general questions regarding the Dāśarājña in reply, I sent him a brief note embodying in broad outline my views on the subject. In the forward n, letter ( dated August 4 1972), I wrote - There are many theories about the Dāśarājña. Besides the historical interpretation, naturalist, astronomical and symbolical interpretations of the event have also been attempted.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>East and west</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/East_and_west/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/East_and_west/</guid>
      <description>THE EAST AND THE WEST 1
Characteristics of Eastern Culture It would be convenient if I begap by defining, to a certain extent, the implications of the terms, “Eastern,&amp;quot; &amp;quot; Culture,&amp;quot; and “Characteristics,&amp;quot; so far as the present paper was concerned. It has now become almost trite to say that the categorisation of thought and culture as Eastern&amp;rsquo; and Western&amp;rsquo; is not at all scientific. There are, as we all know, great and fundamental differences between the various ideologies that have originated apd grown in the geographical East.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>hRd in vedas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/hRd_in_vedas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/hRd_in_vedas/</guid>
      <description>Another current of thought also is associated with the notion of hrd. A study of certain words in Gk, Lat, etc., possessing psychological significance, such as phren, phrénes, kérdos, vecors, recordari, proves that the human faculties of feeling, willing, etc, were connected by the people speaking those languages more parti cularly with the heart. The same feature is to be noticed in the Veda also, It is obviously on account of certain distinctive features of hrd, such as its being the innermost as well as the most vital and the most sensitive organ in the human body, that certain primary psychological functions have come to be connected with it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>INDEX</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/word-INDEX/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/word-INDEX/</guid>
      <description>arrya 5 Aalto, Pentti 49n. ahamkāra 138, 138n. abhıcārila 83, 158n, Ahavaniya (fire) 70, 203 Abhidhamma 251, Ahura Mazdah 39, 77, 173, 187, Abbiras 287, 298 187n, 207, 2070, 224 Abhyavartın 190 Abıyard 190 Artareya Aranyaka 75n abstract divinities 208 Antareya-Brāhmaṇa 104, 1430, acara 348 1440, 146, 149, 1500, 169, 177n, accent 12, 69 351, activisation 334 Aitihasikas 235 activistic 336 aja 136 Adbhuta-Brāhmaṇa 176n Ajamidha 1910 Adbhuadhyaya 176n Ajas 234, adevism 184n aj: 199, 243n Adhvaryu 109, 110, 110, 158, ajya 199 159.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>INDIAN PATTERN OF LIFE AND THOUGHT</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/INDIAN_PATTERN_OF_LIFE_AND_THOUGHT/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/INDIAN_PATTERN_OF_LIFE_AND_THOUGHT/</guid>
      <description>A GLIMPSE OF ITS EARLY PHASES It is customary to regard the Veda as the starting point of the entire ancient Indian way of life and thought. A critical consideration of the question regardiog the genesis of several significant concepts and practices which had prevailed in ancient India would, however, show that they could by no means be traced back to the Veda, either ideologically or from the point of view of literary documentation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Indo Mediterranean contacts</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/Indo_Mediterranean_contacts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/Indo_Mediterranean_contacts/</guid>
      <description>SOME ASPECTS OF THE INDO-MEDITERRANEAN CONTACTS The subject of my lecturel is : Some Aspects of the Contacts between India and the Mediterranean World. Let me begin by defining my subject geographically and chronologically. For the purpose of this paper, by &amp;quot; Mediterranean World &amp;quot; I have under stood, on the one hand, the Levant which included Asia Minor and the Fertile Crescent with Egypt at its western terminus, Syria Palestine forming its western band, and Assyria-Babylonia con stituting its eastern bow, and, on the other, Greece and Rome.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>King election</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/King_election/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/King_election/</guid>
      <description>ATHARVAVEDA III. 4 : &amp;ldquo;ELECTION OF A KING&amp;rdquo; Introduction It is usually suggested that the ancient Indian thinker possessed only a &amp;rsquo;theological&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;philosophical&amp;rsquo; mind. The large amount of ancient Indian literature relating, either directly or indirectly, to political science (Arthaśāstra or Dandaniti) would, however, clearly indicate that he also possessed what may be called a political&amp;rsquo; and &amp;rsquo;economic&amp;rsquo; mind. Indeed, some of the thinkers of ancient India went to the extent of claiming that Arthaśāstra or Dandaniti was the most fundamental of all sciences, One of the most basic concepts in ancient Indian polity was that of kingsbip.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>mahAbhArata - origin and growth</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/mahAbhArata_-_origin_and_growth/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/mahAbhArata_-_origin_and_growth/</guid>
      <description>THE MAHABHARATA : ORIGIN AND GROWTH In the history of Indological studies there has been evident a tendency to exaggerate the importance of the Vedic Aryan element in India&amp;rsquo;s culture-complex According to this school of thought the Veda has made the greatest contribution to the moulding of the Indian way of life and thought through the ages As a matter of fact, ancient Indian culture, or, more precisely, the Hindu culture, as a whole, is not infrequently characterised as Vedic culture Even a casual survey of the Hindu way of life and thought would, however, lay bare the inadequacy of such a characterisation The principal gods of the Vedic pantheon, such as Indra and Varuṇa, are now no longer worshipped, their place has long since been taken by the gods of the people, like Visou and Rudra Siva Mythology and demonology other than those of the Veda have been ushered in and now cater to the instinctive demands of the people in connection with what may be called the embellishment and ornamentation of religion.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>mahAbhArata critical edition</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/mahAbhArata_critical_edition/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/mahAbhArata_critical_edition/</guid>
      <description>THE MAHĀBHARATA AND ITS CRITICAL EDITION It is generally believed that the Veda has made the most significant contribution to the moulding of the Indian way of life and thought, through the ages As a matter of fact, ancient Indian culture, or, more precisely, the Hindu culture, as a whole, is not infrequently characterised as the Vedic culture A critical analysis of the Hindu way of life and thought would, however, expose the inadequacy of such characterisation The principal gods of the Vedic pantheon, like Indra and Varuṇa, are now rarely worshipped The elaborate system of sacrifice, which had been evolved and consolidated during the Brāhmaṇa period and resuscitated and reorganised during the Sutra period and which had come to be recognised almost as the hall mark of the Vedic religion, has pow been almost entirely relegated to the back ground The philosophical speculations of the Upanisads have either undergone vital modifications or have been superseded by other systems of thought In short, the values sponsored by the Veda have long since ceased to operate as the essential motive force of the Indian Weltanschauung It is not the Brahmanism of the Veda, but popular Hinduism, which traditionally claims to have derived its inspiration from the Veda but which, historically speaking, has assimilated within itself perhaps more non Vedic elements than the Vedic opes, that dominates the socio religious life of India And the literary works which have left an abiding imprint on the socio religious life sponsored by Hinduism are not so much the Vedas as the popular epics Even among these popular epics, if there is any one single work which has proved to be a factor of inestimable import in the making of the life and thought of the Indian people and which still continues to 1 Extens on lecture delivered under the auspices of the Mysore Univer sty in August 1961 Inevitably, the first part of this lecture constitutes a sort of summary of The Mahabharata origin and growth which precede this article THB MAVĀBHARATA AND ITS CRITICAL EDITION 293 be a living force in Indian life, it is the Mahabharata, the great national epic of India.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monarchy checks</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/Monarchy_checks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/Monarchy_checks/</guid>
      <description>ATHARVAVEDA VII, 12 &amp;ldquo;CHECKS ON MONARCHY : POPULAR ASSEMBLICS Introduction Though the normal form of state in ancient India had been monarchy, sufficient care was taken to see that it did not tend to degenerate joto autocracy. The ancient Indian monarch func tioned under various checks - direct or indirect, constitutional or otherwise. (1) Firstly, it was cmphatically laid down that Dharma (= law) was superior to Kṣatra (=sovereign power of the king): Indeed, Dharma was described as the “ Kṣatra of Ksatra.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>saMvAdasUkta</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/saMvAdasUkta/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/saMvAdasUkta/</guid>
      <description>THE SANVĀDASŪKTA IN THE ATHARVAVEDA The Samvadasūktas or dialogue-hymns constitutc one of the distinctive features of Rgvedic hymnody. Various views have been put forth by scholars regarding the genesis and nature of these hymns. OLDENBERG, for iastance, speaks of the ancient Akhyānas or narratives made up of prose and verse and suggests that only the verse-portions of some of such narratives, which were perhaps supplemented by extempore prose additions by the narrator, are preserved in the form of the so-called Samvāda sūktas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SOMATISM OF VEDIC PSYCHOLOGY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/SOMATISM_OF_VEDIC_PSYCHOLOGY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/SOMATISM_OF_VEDIC_PSYCHOLOGY/</guid>
      <description>Manas is the buman faculty which is usually associated in the Veda with a variety of psychological activities. The considera tion of the genesis of the Vedic concept of manas brings forth a number of unique characteristics of that human faculty. Let us first approach the question of the origin of the concept of manas from the linguistic point of view. It is believed by some scholars that the words, manas, manus, manyu, mensch, mann, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two births of vasiShTha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/Two_births_of_vasiShTha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/Two_births_of_vasiShTha/</guid>
      <description>THE TWO BIRTHS OF VASISTHA A FRESH STUDY OF RGVEDA VII 33. 9-141 Gantertācarjasamsmrtyai rasisthasye &amp;lsquo;ha janmanoh | karoti nutanām vjakhyam rāmo vāsısthagotrajah It is suggested that every regular family book (mandala ) of the Rgveda contains what may be called a family-hymn, the main purpose of which is to glorify the progenitor of the family and to celebrate some special attainments and characteristic cxploits of that family as a whole Such family hymds usually occur at the end of the group of hymns relating to Indra, for, it is believed that the peculiar distinction achieved by the family is essentially the result of Indra&amp;rsquo;s benign favour.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>VARUNA, VASISTHA, AND BHAKTI</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/VARUNA_VASISTHA_AND_BHAKTI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/VARUNA_VASISTHA_AND_BHAKTI/</guid>
      <description>The sage Vasistha has played a very significant role in the cultural history of ancient India. There is, indeed, hardly any period of the Vedic and the Epic ages on which Vasiṣṭha and his family have not left the special stamp of their almost inimitable personality. Even if one restricted oneself to the copsideration of the period of the Rgveda, one would not fail to be struck by the remarkable contribution made by Vasistha and the Vasiṣṭhas, particularly to the socio-political and religious aspects of the culture of that period.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Veda cultural background</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/Veda_cultural_background/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/Veda_cultural_background/</guid>
      <description>THE CULTURAL BACKGROUND OF THE VEDA It is generally believed - and, to a large extent, rightly believed that a proper understanding of the Veda affords the master-key which can uprave many a problem relating to ancient Indian culture and civilization. Every serious student of ancient Indian civilization, therefore, begins, naturally enough, by asking himself the question: What is the Veda? Let me also then, by way of a general introduction to my lectures, today begin by posing such broad questions as : What exactly is connoted by the term, Veda?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vedic period antecedents</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/Vedic_period_antecedents/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/Vedic_period_antecedents/</guid>
      <description>THE ANTECEDENTS AND THE EARLY BEGINNINGS OF THE VEDIC PERIOD
On this occasion,&amp;quot; I propose to place before you, for your consideration and criticism, some of my ideas relating to the antecedents and the early beginnings of the Vedic period. A considerable amount of work of really sterling merit has been done in this field by generations of scholars — Indian as well as foreign. I am, however, inclined to think that, generally speak ing, the Vedic period has been studied, up till now, more or less as an isolated period.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>VEDIC RELIGION AND MYTHOLOGY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/VEDIC_RELIGION_AND_MYTHOLOGY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/VEDIC_RELIGION_AND_MYTHOLOGY/</guid>
      <description>A Survey of the Work of some Western Scholars In 1805, Henry Thomas COLEBROOKE published his essay, &amp;quot; On the Vedas, or Sacred Writings of the Hindus,&amp;rsquo;&amp;ldquo;1 and thereby became entitled to the distinction of being perhaps the first Western scholar ever to write at some length about the Veda.&amp;rdquo; In this essay, COLEBROOKE deals with what may be called the * externals&amp;rsquo; of the Vedic literature rather than with its contents.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>vena sUkta</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/vena_sUkta/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/dANDekaraH/indology-exercise/vena_sUkta/</guid>
      <description>THE VENA SŪKTA IN THE ATHARVAVEDA The first sūkta in the second kanda of the Atharvaveda (AV) has, according to the Anukramani, Veda for its rst and brahman atman for its devatā WAITNEY characterises the hymn as mysticł, while WEBER2 and, following him, GRIFFITHS mention glorification of the prime cause of all things&amp;rsquo; as its theme in spite of the fact that the Kaufika Sūtra (37 3) and the commen tary on the AV prescribe this hymn, wholly or in part, for addressing various articles out of whose behaviour afterward signs of success or the contrary, and the like oracular responses, are to be drawn, its essential philosophical character becomes quite evident even on a cursory reading Indeed, this sukta-parti cularly its first stanzas which it is proposed to discuss here at some length – is very important from the point of view of the development of Indian philosophical thought This whole sukta appears with many variants as a part of the Mahanarayana Upa.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
