<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;04 The Four Vedas on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/04_The_Four_Vedas/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;04 The Four Vedas on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/04_The_Four_Vedas/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Early Vedic</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/04_The_Four_Vedas/01_Early_Vedic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/04_The_Four_Vedas/01_Early_Vedic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This form of Vedic was spoken in the Indus Valley, ca. 1700–1200 BCE, by families and clans, the Vedic Indians by definition, whose language was adopted by others along with their mantras partly because of the power or alleged power of the latter. We are already familiar with some of its features because it is the period of the Rigveda. It resulted in verse that described sublime language (&lt;em&gt;bráhman&lt;/em&gt; as well as &lt;em&gt;vāc&lt;/em&gt;) as all-knowing (&lt;em&gt;viśva-vid&lt;/em&gt;), a compound derived from &lt;em&gt;viśva&lt;/em&gt; and the same verbal root &lt;em&gt;vid-&lt;/em&gt; ‘know’ or ‘see’ from which the noun &lt;em&gt;veda&lt;/em&gt; derives. It restricts that power to seers, poets and priests (&lt;em&gt;brahmán&lt;/em&gt;, accented differently, or &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Middle Vedic</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/04_The_Four_Vedas/02_Middle_Vedic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/04_The_Four_Vedas/02_Middle_Vedic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This form of the language belongs to the period of Kuru and Pañcāla on the upper Gangetic plane between ca. 1200 and 700 BCE. The name Kuru is the name of a clan. The geographical regions where clans settled were generally called after them. In the case of the Kurus, this region was the district of Meerut and the territory situated some 100 miles north of Delhi called Kurukṣetra. That general area saw not only the codification of the Rigveda, but the putting together of three other collections that, together with other compositions, became the Sāma-, Yajur- and Atharvavedas. ‘The Kuru realm,’ as Witzel put it, ‘became the center of Brahmanical culture, with Kurukṣetra as the traditional heartland of Brahmanical orthopraxy’—that is, ritual.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Late Vedic</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/04_The_Four_Vedas/03_Late_Vedic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/04_The_Four_Vedas/03_Late_Vedic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Late Vedic characterizes the confederations of Kośala and Videha, ca. 700–450 BCE. During this period, the White Yajurveda was compiled or extracted from the Black (as will be explained below and more fully in Chapter 7), other Kuru compositions were modified or reworked (like the important Aitareya Brāhmaṇa of the Rigveda), but the chief event of the period from our Vedic point of view was the final canonization of the four Vedas. The paradigm of canonization was the fixation of the precise form of the Rigveda, based upon a linguistic analysis that separated the words (&lt;em&gt;pada&lt;/em&gt;) in each sentence from each other. It dissolved the &lt;em&gt;sandhi&lt;/em&gt; of continuous speech (&lt;em&gt;saṃhitā&lt;/em&gt;): the linking of the sounds of words with those that precede and follow in the sentence and in nominal composition, often discernible within words, that Vedic shares with later Sanskrit. English &lt;em&gt;sandhi&lt;/em&gt; is exemplified by the difference between ‘a mango’ and ‘an apple’. Here are the &lt;em&gt;Saṃhitā&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Padapāṭha&lt;/em&gt; of Rigveda 10.127.2:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 The Apotheosis of Schools</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/04_The_Four_Vedas/04_The_Apotheosis_of_Schools/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/04_The_Four_Vedas/04_The_Apotheosis_of_Schools/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The combination of the four Vedas with all their auxiliary texts into a single canon was inspired by Śākalya’s analysis and his separation of words. It took place, likewise, in the eastern territories and is associated with the name of king Janaka of Videha, who attracted learned men from the west to introduce Kuru orthopraxy to his court. A great debate is said to have ensued, in which Yājñavalkya, the local celebrity, defeated these alien experts. The old Yajurveda was now called Black Yajurveda and found its ultimate refuge in South India. The White Yajurveda was established in the north where it continues to the present day.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
