<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;2 Vedamlo, “Living in the Veda” on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/2_Vedamlo_Living_in_the_Veda/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;2 Vedamlo, “Living in the Veda” on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/2_Vedamlo_Living_in_the_Veda/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 The Vocabulary of the Veda Pandit</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/2_Vedamlo_Living_in_the_Veda/1_The_Vocabulary_of_the_Veda_Pandit/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/2_Vedamlo_Living_in_the_Veda/1_The_Vocabulary_of_the_Veda_Pandit/</guid>
      <description>Essential for an understanding of the structure of Vedic tradition are certain key terms that are common parlance among Vedic Brahmans. These will come into play in the personal biographies in Chapter 3. The Glossary at the end of the book includes these terms along with others appearing less frequently, all of them being Sanskrit unless noted as Telugu. A reader may wish to refer back to pages here at the outset of this chapter for context and details in addition to the brief Glossary definitions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2 Choices for Livelihood</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/2_Vedamlo_Living_in_the_Veda/2_Choices_for_Livelihood/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/2_Vedamlo_Living_in_the_Veda/2_Choices_for_Livelihood/</guid>
      <description>The score of capsule biographies in Chapter 3 illustrates a variety of career options for certified Veda pandits and how the scope of personal choices has broadened over the course of four generations. Some of those who have been recipients of cropland and houses donated by wealthy individuals who favor the Vedic tradition have been freed from financial concerns in order to teach, study, and in some cases perform sacrifices. As noted, some have taken up full- or part-time professions as domestic ritualists, Smarta Brahmans, while others recite as ghana-pathi for remuneration.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 The Vocabulary of an Ahitagni</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/2_Vedamlo_Living_in_the_Veda/3_The_Vocabulary_of_an_Ahitagni/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/2_Vedamlo_Living_in_the_Veda/3_The_Vocabulary_of_an_Ahitagni/</guid>
      <description>Veda pandits who have been nurtured within the embrace of srauta traditions will be strongly encouraged to continue their heritage and become ahitagni, sacrificers who maintain three hearths, not a single sacred fire; perform the twice-daily heated milk offering known as agni-hotra that entitles them to be known as rare and privileged agni-hotrin; and move on with soma sacrifice in mind to perform the ritual known as yajna, meaning the agni-stoma.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4 Bonding with Agni</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/2_Vedamlo_Living_in_the_Veda/4_Bonding_with_Agni/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/2_Vedamlo_Living_in_the_Veda/4_Bonding_with_Agni/</guid>
      <description>Chapter 3 illustrates the ways in which these extended rituals and all their sup porting intellectual and material preparations ornament the lives of ahitagni and patni and Chapter 6 enters the ritual life in far more detail. To conclude this chapter, however, it is instructive to review the significance of installing the god Agni as lord of house and family, and what his presence and the obli gations of constant ritual attentions mean in the way of creating an alternative reality.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5 The Voices of Ahitagni and Other</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/2_Vedamlo_Living_in_the_Veda/5_The_Voices_of_Ahitagni_and_Other/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/2_Vedamlo_Living_in_the_Veda/5_The_Voices_of_Ahitagni_and_Other/</guid>
      <description>Veda Pandits
In the next chapter, ten families are portrayed in capsule biographies of ahi tagni or other exemplary Veda pandits. Most of these families are now or were for their productive years located in agrahara or agrahara-like villages in or near Konasima. All families have multigenerational connections to Konasima through marriage and other ritual activities, although one is established across the Vasistha-Godavari in West Godavari District and another is split between two pilgrimage temple towns.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
