<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;2 Vedamlo, “Living in the Veda” on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/2_Vedamlo_Living_in_the_Veda/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;2 Vedamlo, “Living in the Veda” on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/2_Vedamlo_Living_in_the_Veda/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 The Vocabulary of the Veda Pandit</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/2_Vedamlo_Living_in_the_Veda/1_The_Vocabulary_of_the_Veda_Pandit/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/2_Vedamlo_Living_in_the_Veda/1_The_Vocabulary_of_the_Veda_Pandit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Essential for an understanding of the structure of Vedic tradition are certain  key terms that are common parlance among Vedic Brahmans. These will come  into play in the personal biographies in Chapter 3. The Glossary at the end of  the book includes these terms along with others appearing less frequently, all  of them being Sanskrit unless noted as Telugu. A reader may wish to refer back  to pages here at the outset of this chapter for context and details in addition to  the brief Glossary definitions. This chapter serves as a primer in living Vedic  tradition by introducing first the basic educational system of Vedic pandits  (Brahmans in hereditary Vedic families) as practiced today in coastal Andhra,  then an outline of choices for maintaining samsara, the worldly subsistence  of married and certified Veda pandit householders. The third section enters  the life of srauta, the extended sacrificial tradition of those who establish three  fires and become eligible to proceed to soma rituals.1 This requires presenta tion of a whole new vocabulary and advanced set of procedures. A fourth sec&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2 Choices for Livelihood</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/2_Vedamlo_Living_in_the_Veda/2_Choices_for_Livelihood/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/2_Vedamlo_Living_in_the_Veda/2_Choices_for_Livelihood/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The score of capsule biographies in Chapter 3 illustrates a variety of career  options for certified Veda pandits and how the scope of personal choices has  broadened over the course of four generations. Some of those who have been  recipients of cropland and houses donated by wealthy individuals who favor  the Vedic tradition have been freed from financial concerns in order to teach,  study, and in some cases perform sacrifices. As noted, some have taken up  full- or part-time professions as domestic ritualists, Smarta Brahmans, while  others recite as ghana-pathi for remuneration. Not available to the oldest of  those selected for study here but now undertaken by most Veda pandits is  the parayana system, usually called the “TTD Scheme,” borrowing an English  term applied to the Tirumala Tirupati Devasthanam and its program of finan cial support for Veda pandits in the form of honoraria and pensions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 The Vocabulary of an Ahitagni</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/2_Vedamlo_Living_in_the_Veda/3_The_Vocabulary_of_an_Ahitagni/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/2_Vedamlo_Living_in_the_Veda/3_The_Vocabulary_of_an_Ahitagni/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Veda pandits who have been nurtured within the embrace of srauta traditions  will be strongly encouraged to continue their heritage and become ahitagni,  sacrificers who maintain three hearths, not a single sacred fire; perform the  twice-daily heated milk offering known as agni-hotra that entitles them to be  known as rare and privileged agni-hotrin; and move on with soma sacrifice  in mind to perform the ritual known as yajna, meaning the agni-stoma. Of  the total of 626 ahitagni listed for India and Nepal by C.  G. Kashikar and  Asko Parpola, “A catalogue of ahitagnis and srauta traditions in recent times,”  nearly one-third (200) were residing in Andhra.9 The srauta ritual system, as  noted earlier, is an extended one in the sense that a simple domestic routine  has been replaced by one far more demanding on the religious energies of the  sacrificer and wife. A few may take the life-altering step into extended fires  early on, but many wait until mid-life or later. They speak repeatedly about  what is nitya, obligatory, and invariably distinguish between what is absolutely  necessary for the sacrificial life of a Vedic Brahman and what is set aside as  either kamya, a ritual for a personal desire (long life, for example, or the birth  of a son), or naimittika, a ritual that is occasional, not calendric (such as rites  for a funeral or for rain to end a drought). The last of these three categories,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4 Bonding with Agni</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/2_Vedamlo_Living_in_the_Veda/4_Bonding_with_Agni/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/2_Vedamlo_Living_in_the_Veda/4_Bonding_with_Agni/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Chapter 3 illustrates the ways in which these extended rituals and all their sup porting intellectual and material preparations ornament the lives of ahitagni and patni and Chapter 6 enters the ritual life in far more detail. To conclude  this chapter, however, it is instructive to review the significance of installing  the god Agni as lord of house and family, and what his presence and the obli gations of constant ritual attentions mean in the way of creating an alternative  reality. Some of this surfaces when we look at the multiple meanings of the  word agni-hotra. The god and his cult become synonymous when we see that  common parlance of ahitagni and patni employs agni-hotra to mean three sep arate entities: the daily offerings, the fires into which libations are made, and  the god Agni himself. So melded are these meanings that one nonagenarian  patni anxiously shouting “Agni-hotra! Agni-hotra!” in her final hours of breath  could have been signaling any one of the three. As Christopher Fuller has  observed of the standard Hindu worship, “Puja, at its heart, is the worshippers’  reception and entertainment of a distinguished and adored guest”15 and that&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 The Voices of Ahitagni and Other</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/2_Vedamlo_Living_in_the_Veda/5_The_Voices_of_Ahitagni_and_Other/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/2_Vedamlo_Living_in_the_Veda/5_The_Voices_of_Ahitagni_and_Other/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Veda Pandits&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the next chapter, ten families are portrayed in capsule biographies of ahi tagni or other exemplary Veda pandits. Most of these families are now or were  for their productive years located in agrahara or agrahara-like villages in or  near Konasima. All families have multigenerational connections to Konasima  through marriage and other ritual activities, although one is established across  the Vasistha-Godavari in West Godavari District and another is split between  two pilgrimage temple towns. Pillars of these ten families include seven ahi&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
