<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;14 PRIESTS AND HEROES on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/14_PRIESTS_AND_HEROES/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;14 PRIESTS AND HEROES on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/14_PRIESTS_AND_HEROES/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 The Priests of the Fire Cult</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/14_PRIESTS_AND_HEROES/1_The_Priests_of_the_Fire_Cult/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/14_PRIESTS_AND_HEROES/1_The_Priests_of_the_Fire_Cult/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;WITH the cult of fire are connected three great families of priests, the Añgirases, the Atharvans, and Bhṛgus, in all of whose cases it is at first sight impossible, and in any case difficult, to decide whether we have to do with real traditions of priestly families of the past, or with deities who have fallen in rank and become confounded with men. The case of the Añgirases is of special interest. Agni is not rarely called an Añgiras, but he is also called the chief or the most inspired Añgiras, and the name Añgiras is used in one passage of the god on the one hand, and on the other of the ancestor of the invoker of the god. On the other hand, Indra also is described as veriest Añgiras, and in his feat of the overthrow of Vala the Añgirases play a great part by their singing and their prayers. In point of fact the myth is sometimes attributed to them and not to Indra at all, or he is given a secondary role in it. They appear in the myth of the Panis as obtaining the cows: this is, it is probable, simply another side of the overthrow of Vala and the release of the cows, and Bṛhaspati who is credited with the same feat is once called Añgirasa, and once even Añgiras. They are repeatedly called fathers by the poets, they are associated with Manu and are once with the Atharvans and the Bhrgus connected with Yama: 1 but they appear also with the Adityas, Rudras, and Vasus, Soma is offered to them, they are invoked,2 and they are praised as sacrificers who attained Agni and won by the sacrifice immortality.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2 Other Ancient Priests</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/14_PRIESTS_AND_HEROES/2_Other_Ancient_Priests/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/14_PRIESTS_AND_HEROES/2_Other_Ancient_Priests/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Of other ancient seers the most famous are the Seven Seers, who are four times mentioned in the Rigveda. They are called divine fathers and secure Trasadasyu for Purukutsa&amp;rsquo;s wife in her dire need; possibly the number is merely the frequent mystic number seven, or again it may be derived from the seven priests of the ritual who again, however, may be due to the desire to make up the sacred number. Their names are not given before the Brāhmaṇas. In the Śatapatha 10 they are regarded as the seven stars in the constellation of the Great Bear, and are declared to have been in origin bears, a theory explained by the similarity of the words Rṣi, seer, and Ṛkṣa, which means both star 11 and bear.12 It is probably the same number who are the seven Hotṛs with whom Manu made his first offering.13 A couple of divine Hotṛs, who are mentioned about twelve times in the Rigveda,11 seem to be based on some pair of sacrificers in the ritual.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 Warriors</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/14_PRIESTS_AND_HEROES/3_Warriors/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/14_PRIESTS_AND_HEROES/3_Warriors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Of the warriors who are mentioned as having been engaged in battles and aided by the gods, we have absolutely no reason to assign the majority to any but the world of past reality. Historic reminiscence and poetic imagination are sufficient to account for what is said about them, just as the same factors together with aetiological myths explain adequately the legends of the priest of old days. To seek in any of them gods is erroneous: 1 treated as history, it is perfectly possible to make good sense out of the history of Sudās, and even of the older and more mystic Divodāsa Atithigva. With Sudās Viśvāmitra and Vasiṣṭha stand in the closest relation: we have a poem which tradition places in the mouth of Viśvamitra extolling the rivers Vipaś and Cutudri for giving an easy crossing to his master&amp;rsquo;s hosts, and another hymn recounts with jeers at the expense of Viśvamitra the failure of the great coalition which he had brought against his former master, and the success of the army of Sudās through the help of Vasiṣṭha.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4 The First of Men</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/14_PRIESTS_AND_HEROES/4_The_First_of_Men/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/14_PRIESTS_AND_HEROES/4_The_First_of_Men/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the Rigveda there can be no doubt as to who is the real first man: it is Manu or Manus, whose name, cognate perhaps with the Gothic manna, and the root man, &amp;rsquo;think&amp;rsquo;, appears as a definite forefather of men nearly forty times in the Rigveda. He is essentially the first of sacrificers, and the establisher of sacrifice, though he appears with other old sacrificers also, Añgiras, Bhṛgu, Atharvan, Dadhyañc, Atri, and Kaṇva. The gods, Mātariśvan, or Kāvya Uśanā, are said to have given Agni to Manu. Again it is the three lakes of the Soma of Manus that Indra drinks to strengthen himself for the fight with Vṛtra. A bird brings Soma to Manu. In the Brahmaṇas he con-&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
