<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2006 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The master of viliste~NgA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-12-12_the-master-of-vilistenga/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-12-12_the-master-of-vilistenga/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/12/12/the-master-of-vilistenga/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One who is in the grip of the vidyA-s of the dreaded dhUmAvatI and&#xA;rakta-jyeShThA will be released from them by the secret formula known as&#xA;the “bonds of the devI”. The one who goes beyond that step attains that&#xA;ancient and most secret vidyA known as the prayoga of viliste~NgA. It&#xA;was the secret of the atharvans of, that which arises from the herb&#xA;which was known to bhR^igu and ushanA kAvya. It is considered the crest&#xA;jewel of the mighty vidyA-s of ushAna kAvya himself – indeed it is&#xA;called the AsurI mAyA. Only the brAhmaNa of high caliber who masters the&#xA;deep rahasyas of the ritual practice can set himself on the path of&#xA;becoming the master of the viliste~NgA prayoga. He having changed his&#xA;yaj~nopavIta and performed his saMdhya as per the rules of the atharvan&#xA;lore moves in the southern direction. He performs the appropriate rites&#xA;of the paippalAda lore to the lord of the gods, with the sUktaM that a&#xA;knower of rahasya-s will attain identity to with indra. He is filled&#xA;with the mAyA of indra. He then invokes nirR^iti into himself and if he&#xA;has mastered the rahasya mantras he sends her away into a mule or&#xA;nematode worm. He is then ready to invoke the vidyA of viliste~NgA.&#xA;Even as he makes the oblations to her he experiences bliss, like a&#xA;long-lasting and unfading pleasure of maithuna with a most beautiful&#xA;strI. The very sight of viliste~NgA provides him indescribable bliss&#xA;that no one can experience in the regular world. Once viliste~NgA joins&#xA;him he is the master of prayogas. He becomes like a vR^iShabha filled&#xA;with the virility of ten males and attracts beautiful women easily. He&#xA;can cause instant stambhana of rivals and send deep bhaya into enemies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Attaining atharvaNa mantra GYAna</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-02-06_attaining-atharvana-mantra-gyana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-02-06_attaining-atharvana-mantra-gyana/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/02/06/attaining-atharvana-mantra-gyana/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Acquiring the atharvaveda either requires you to be born as a scion of&#xA;the atharvan clan or acquire it through a separate upanayanam. The key&#xA;to this new upanayanam is the need for the student to chant the sUktaM&#xA;known as triShaptIyam (AV-S 1.1 or AV-P 1.6). Only by chanting the&#xA;triShaptIyam does the power of the atharvanic mantras enter him so that&#xA;he can use them. Thus the triShaptIyam is also used before commencing&#xA;practice of atharvanic recitation or svAdhyAyaH. For deploying an&#xA;atharvanic spell for protection one needs the first mantra of the&#xA;triShaptiyam to be recited. In the atharvanic upanayanam there is a&#xA;special ritual apparently not seen in other vedic traditions. The father&#xA;or teacher ties feathers of a shUka (parrot), a sAri (myna) and a&#xA;kR^isha (Wren warbler) with a yellow string around the students neck.&#xA;Then these are offered in the sacrificial fire with the triShaptIyaM. In&#xA;a more gory shaunaka rite of the past the tongues of these birds were&#xA;similarly tied and eaten. This qualifies him to start acquiring&#xA;atharvanic vidya.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;AV-S 1.1&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ye triShaptAH pariyanti vishvA rUpANi bibhrataH /&lt;br&gt;&#xA;vAchaspatir balA teShAM tanvo adya dadhAtu me //1//&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Three times seven that go around, bearing all forms;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;let vAchaspati put their powers into my body’s [parts]&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The oral and textual traditions of the shaunakIya atharvaveda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-10-01_the-oral-and-textual-traditions-of-the-shaunakiya-atharvaveda/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-10-01_the-oral-and-textual-traditions-of-the-shaunakiya-atharvaveda/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/10/01/the-oral-and-textual-traditions-of-the-shaunakiya-atharvaveda/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The only complete surviving oral tradition is that of the 4th veda is&#xA;the shaunakIya(AV-S) recitation. Even this is dwindling now. The&#xA;paippalAda recitation (AV-P) is not preserved with svaras. An ekashruti&#xA;recitation is preserved amongst the Orissan atharvavedis, and a few&#xA;ritually critical mantras AV-P mantras with svaras, especially in the&#xA;context of the tantric rituals of kubjikA upaniShad (relating to&#xA;atharvaNa bhadrakAli and bagalamukhI) are known to some of the surviving&#xA;atharvavedis (but largely kept secret). S.S. Pandit and Satavalekar have&#xA;produced reasonable printed texts of the AV-S. Satavalekar’s edition&#xA;depended heavily on Pandit Ramachandra Shastri Ratate of Varanasi, who&#xA;knew the whole saMhita pATha orally. An examination of his son’s&#xA;Atharvan recitation illustrates that his had a high fidelity of svaras.&#xA;Pandit used multiple reciters of AV-S. Among them were Bapuji Jivanram&#xA;from Gujarata, who a good recitational musicality and knew much of the&#xA;saMhita orally and also pada pATha and krama pATha of the first 4&#xA;kANDas. The Maharastri AV scholar Keshava Bhatta from Mahuli near Thane&#xA;knew whole saMhitA and pada recitation except the funerary hymns and&#xA;also krama of kANDas 1-4. Venkan Bhatta another of Pandit’s sources was&#xA;the greatest Maharashtrian reciter of the AV-S who knew whole saMhitA,&#xA;pada and a considerable part of the krama and jaTA pAThas. The vikR^iti&#xA;pAThas of the AV-S saMhita are now largely extinct with the exception of&#xA;few ritually critical recitations that are known by a small number of&#xA;reciters.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Importance</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/importance/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/importance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.oocities.org/somasushma/atharva.html&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/vedAH_RkshAkalam/saMhitA/vishvAsa-prastutiH/10/014/06_angiraso_naH.md&#34;  newLevelForH1=&#34;5&#34; includeTitle=&#34;false&#34;&gt; &lt;/div&gt;  &#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/vedAH_RkshAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/10/014/06_angiraso_naH.md&#34;  newLevelForH1=&#34;5&#34; includeTitle=&#34;false&#34;&gt; &lt;/div&gt;  &#xA;&lt;p&gt;The fourth veda or the veda of the atharvAns is shrouded in much mystery. The main reason for its low popularity has been the comparatively low following it has had amidst the brAhmaNas due its association with technical matters. Another factor contributing to this has been the practice  of the atharva veda being largely restricted to the bhRgu and Angirasa clans.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;misconceptions&#34;&gt;Misconceptions&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Some popular misconceptions regarding the atharva veda (AV)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Raudra mahAnArAyaNa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/raudra_mahAnArAyaNa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/raudra_mahAnArAyaNa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The kubjikA upaniShad, a text at the smArta-pashchimAmnAya interface, cites the below 5 R^ik-s by  pratIka:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;sahasrashIrShaM rudraM sahasrAkSham |&#xA;te pa~ncharchyaH | tasyAH shikhAyA madhye puruShaH kubjeshvaraH sthitaH ||&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here kubjeshvara is navAtman bhairava, the consort of  kubjikA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To date, I have not been able to locate these verses in any Vedic text, even though the majority of the kubjikA upaniShad citations are traceable to the two extant atharvaveda saMhitA-s, in line with its explicit affiliation with the atharvan tradition.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>vasordhArA-godesses</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/vasordhArA-godesses/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/vasordhArA-godesses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://threadreaderapp.com/thread/1675379473930149888.html&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The yajurvedin-s of all schools use the incantations beginning with agnAviShNU sajoShasa&amp;hellip; known as the chamaka-prashna in their vasordhAra. The atharvaveda has an internal reference to what is taken as the vasordhAra:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;vasor yA dhArA madhunA prapInA&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ghR^itena mishrA amR^itasya nAbhayaH |&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The atharvan vasordhAra uses a wholly different set of incantations. It begins with brahma jaj~nAnam prathamam&amp;hellip;&#xA;Then it has the incantation:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;asmin vasu vasavo dhArayantv&lt;br&gt;&#xA;indraH pUShA varuNo mitro agniH |&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>परम्परा</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/paramparA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/paramparA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.oocities.org/somasushma/teachers.pdf&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.oocities.org/somasushma/atharva.html&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;From the paurANic text we may propose the following evolutionary history of the atharvAn texts:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;व्यासः&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;सुमन्ता&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;कबन्धः&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;देवदर्शः&lt;/strong&gt;, पथ्यः&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;मोद, पिप्पलादः (→? स्तौदः), शौल्कायनिः, ब्रह्मबलः/ ब्रह्मवदः (→? चारणविद्या)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;पथय&#34;&gt;पथ्यः&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;शौनकः, जाजलः, कुमुदः (→? जलदः)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;सैन्धवायनः, बभ्रुः&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;मुञ्जकेशः&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
