<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2006 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The master of viliste~NgA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-12-12_the-master-of-vilistenga/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-12-12_the-master-of-vilistenga/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
One who is in the grip of the vidyA-s of the dreaded dhUmAvatI and rakta-jyeShThA will be released from them by the secret formula known as the “bonds of the devI”. The one who goes beyond that step attains that ancient and most secret vidyA known as the prayoga of viliste~NgA. It was the secret of the atharvans of, that which arises from the herb which was known to bhR^igu and ushanA kAvya.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Attaining atharvaNa mantra GYAna</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-02-06_attaining-atharvana-mantra-gyana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-02-06_attaining-atharvana-mantra-gyana/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
Acquiring the atharvaveda either requires you to be born as a scion of the atharvan clan or acquire it through a separate upanayanam. The key to this new upanayanam is the need for the student to chant the sUktaM known as triShaptIyam (AV-S 1.1 or AV-P 1.6). Only by chanting the triShaptIyam does the power of the atharvanic mantras enter him so that he can use them. Thus the triShaptIyam is also used before commencing practice of atharvanic recitation or svAdhyAyaH.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The oral and textual traditions of the shaunakIya atharvaveda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-10-01_the-oral-and-textual-traditions-of-the-shaunakiya-atharvaveda/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-10-01_the-oral-and-textual-traditions-of-the-shaunakiya-atharvaveda/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The only complete surviving oral tradition is that of the 4th veda is the shaunakIya(AV-S) recitation. Even this is dwindling now. The paippalAda recitation (AV-P) is not preserved with svaras. An ekashruti recitation is preserved amongst the Orissan atharvavedis, and a few ritually critical mantras AV-P mantras with svaras, especially in the context of the tantric rituals of kubjikA upaniShad (relating to atharvaNa bhadrakAli and bagalamukhI) are known to some of the surviving atharvavedis (but largely kept secret).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Importance</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/importance/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/importance/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
The fourth veda or the veda of the atharvAns is shrouded in much mystery. The main reason for its low popularity has been the comparatively low following it has had amidst the brAhmaNas due its association with technical matters. Another factor contributing to this has been the practice of the atharva veda being largely restricted to the bhRgu and Angirasa clans.
Misconceptions Some popular misconceptions regarding the atharva veda (AV)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>vasordhArA-godesses</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/vasordhArA-godesses/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/vasordhArA-godesses/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
The yajurvedin-s of all schools use the incantations beginning with agnAviShNU sajoShasa&amp;hellip; known as the chamaka-prashna in their vasordhAra. The atharvaveda has an internal reference to what is taken as the vasordhAra:
vasor yA dhArA madhunA prapInA
ghR^itena mishrA amR^itasya nAbhayaH |
The atharvan vasordhAra uses a wholly different set of incantations. It begins with brahma jaj~nAnam prathamam&amp;hellip; Then it has the incantation:
asmin vasu vasavo dhArayantv
indraH pUShA varuNo mitro agniH |</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>परम्परा</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/paramparA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/paramparA/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
Source: TW
From the paurANic text we may propose the following evolutionary history of the atharvAn texts:
व्यासः सुमन्ता कबन्धः देवदर्शः, पथ्यः मोद, पिप्पलादः (→? स्तौदः), शौल्कायनिः, ब्रह्मबलः/ ब्रह्मवदः (→? चारणविद्या) पथ्यः शौनकः, जाजलः, कुमुदः (→? जलदः) सैन्धवायनः, बभ्रुः मुञ्जकेशः </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
