<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;02 Archaeology and the Oral Tradition on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/1_ORIGINS_AND_BACKGROUNDS/02_Archaeology_and_the_Oral_Tradition/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;02 Archaeology and the Oral Tradition on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/1_ORIGINS_AND_BACKGROUNDS/02_Archaeology_and_the_Oral_Tradition/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Diversities of Reliability</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/1_ORIGINS_AND_BACKGROUNDS/02_Archaeology_and_the_Oral_Tradition/01_Diversities_of_Reliability/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/1_ORIGINS_AND_BACKGROUNDS/02_Archaeology_and_the_Oral_Tradition/01_Diversities_of_Reliability/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So far we have looked at the geography and history of the Oral Tradition. We have also seen that the language of the Vedas is Indo-Aryan, a branch of the large family of Indo-European languages, which has undergone some influence of many other languages and language groups, some of them located within the subcontinent, others from other areas of Asia, including Central and South-east Asia.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Next, we should confront the Oral Tradition with the findings of archaeology. And we need to address more basic issues. We have a partly empirical question: to what extent will archaeology and the Oral Tradition be able to assist us in our search for the Vedas? And we have another that is, at least in part, theoretical in nature: what are the strengths and weaknesses of oral traditions and of archaeology? Where do they fail and how can they complement each other and come together? And what role is played by that third unspoken tradition we take for granted, the written tradition to which we as readers and writers belong ourselves?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Carts, Chariots and the Mind</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/1_ORIGINS_AND_BACKGROUNDS/02_Archaeology_and_the_Oral_Tradition/02_Carts_Chariots_and_the_Mind/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/1_ORIGINS_AND_BACKGROUNDS/02_Archaeology_and_the_Oral_Tradition/02_Carts_Chariots_and_the_Mind/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Figure 7 illustrates small models of toy carts, excavated at Harappa sites and dating from from 2100 to 1600 BCE. The first fourteen are made of terracotta, the last three are bronze. One shows draught animals (cattle) and all have solid wheels. Items number 13 and 14 do not show that there were wagons with four wheels as had been originally assumed (by Mackay and Wheeler). Figure 8 shows wheels from the side. They are all terracotta and belong to the period from 2600 to 1900 BCE. Some are painted in black and number 15, of which only a small part survives, is painted on both sides. All these wagons that were pulled by cattle show the only type of wagon with which the Indus Civilization was familiar. Similar carts were found in the Near East during the same period, but it is now assumed (by Kenoyer and others) that the Harappan development was autochthonous.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Indic Representations of Spoke-Wheeled Chariots</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/1_ORIGINS_AND_BACKGROUNDS/02_Archaeology_and_the_Oral_Tradition/03_Indic_Representations_of_Spoke-Wheeled_Chariots/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/1_ORIGINS_AND_BACKGROUNDS/02_Archaeology_and_the_Oral_Tradition/03_Indic_Representations_of_Spoke-Wheeled_Chariots/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Indus Civilization did not have a script but our information on the Vedas is lacking in another respect. The Vedas left no temples, friezes or icons as we have seen. It had ritual enclosures, but they were made of perishable materials and generally used only once. Connections have been sought between the Vedas and a type of grey-ware pottery, but these pots do not provide pictorial representations, let alone of spoke-wheeled chariots which are common, for instance, on Greek vases. The oral tradition speaks loud and clear, but for visual representations we must wait for the Buddhist era, after the Vedic period.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Sintashta</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/1_ORIGINS_AND_BACKGROUNDS/02_Archaeology_and_the_Oral_Tradition/04_Sintashta/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/1_ORIGINS_AND_BACKGROUNDS/02_Archaeology_and_the_Oral_Tradition/04_Sintashta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Where do we find the origins of the spoke-wheeled chariot? In Central Asia, the earliest known excavations take us to its northern rim: the Sintashta–Arkaim culture which flourished between approximately 2100 and 1800 BCE. It was situated near the source of the Ural River, southeast of the Ural Mountains and northeast of the Caspian Sea. It is, or was, a border zone between the forest and the treeless steppe. Some twenty-five years ago, Russian archaeologists started excavating grave sites there of tribal chiefs who were buried together with their weapons, horses and two-wheeled chariots. The most widely discussed site is illustrated in Figure 13. The numbers 1 to 3 denote ceramics and a halter, number 4 is a knife, number 5 and number 6 are arrow and spearheads. The horse and human skulls are close to each other and the wheels, which had spokes, stood upright in small trenches as is shown on the left and below, indicated by the Russian letters Z and E. Dimensions are given in centimetres.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Attested Locations on the Way to India</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/1_ORIGINS_AND_BACKGROUNDS/02_Archaeology_and_the_Oral_Tradition/05_Attested_Locations_on_the_Way_to_India/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/1_ORIGINS_AND_BACKGROUNDS/02_Archaeology_and_the_Oral_Tradition/05_Attested_Locations_on_the_Way_to_India/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are now ready for a conclusion which summarizes and recapitulates what is presently known about the origins and backgrounds of Vedic civilization insofar as it came from outside the Indic subcontinent, that is, India and Pakistan. That conclusion will put the pieces together in chronological order and fill some gaps. I shall do this with the help of the map of the Frontispiece, following the attested locations that are numbered there and indicated by arrows. The map has been placed at the beginning of the book, so that the reader can refer to it when studying the following more specialized notes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 Note on Aryan and Race</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/1_ORIGINS_AND_BACKGROUNDS/02_Archaeology_and_the_Oral_Tradition/06_Note_on_Aryan_and_Race/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/1_ORIGINS_AND_BACKGROUNDS/02_Archaeology_and_the_Oral_Tradition/06_Note_on_Aryan_and_Race/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We cannot conclude Part I without a word about the linguists’ unfortunate but continued use of the term &lt;em&gt;Aryan&lt;/em&gt;. ‘Indic’ would do just as well. I sometimes use ‘Indian,’ which parallels ‘Iranian’ and is still very common in these studies. There is some justification for that usage in cultural contexts, though it is odd in terms of modern boundaries since much of the area of the Indus Civilization and where the Rigveda was composed overlap with Pakistan.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
