<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;कस्तूरिः on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/kastUriH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;कस्तूरिः on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/kastUriH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Decline</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/kastUriH/decline/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/kastUriH/decline/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/RangaTheDude/status/1934870143236231470&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My tentative position (with heavy inputs from blog_supplement) is that AV practioners are late entrants to orthodoxy after kuru-panchala shrauta standardization where the trayi became standard property of v1s instead of individual clans.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The AV practitioners wanted exclusivity perhaps, and posited simpler rituals for various karman. Equivalent trayi rituals for the same goals are quite elaborated and complicated.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Since trayi folks had first mover advantage, the threat of ritual simplification from AV camp was countered with simplified vidhana, grihya and prayogas purely based on trayi (YV schools predominantly).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kaushika sAvitrI</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/kastUriH/kaushika-sAvitrI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/kastUriH/kaushika-sAvitrI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thread by @RangaTheDude on Thread Reader App – Thread Reader App&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A note on sAvitrI reference in Atharvaveda&amp;rsquo;s Kaushika grihya sutra.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Atharva vedic samhitas do not contain the famous vishvAmitra&amp;rsquo;s sAvitrI mantra in the gAyatrI meter. Still, we can infer that it is held in high regard in AV tradition.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;gopatha-explanation&#34;&gt;Gopatha explanation&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Gopatha brahmana devotes a chapter on this mantra as a discussion between maudgalya and glAva maitreya. Note the question and answer -&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>puruSha sukta</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/kastUriH/puruSha-sUkta-pATha-bheda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/kastUriH/puruSha-sUkta-pATha-bheda/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thread by @RangaTheDude on Thread Reader App – Thread Reader App&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A speculation on AV pAThabheda of the puruSha sukta Rik:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Purusha sukta is found in all the 4 vedas - RV 10.90, Taittiriya Aranyaka 3.12, Vajasaneyi 31.1, SV 6.4 and AV 19.6. It&amp;rsquo;s also quoted in the kAThaka brahmana fragments. Despite the deviations in words, the number of mantras, all except AV, have &amp;ldquo;sahasrashIrShA puruShaH&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;AV alone, (both vulgate and paippalada) has &amp;ldquo;sahasrabAhuH puruShaH&amp;rdquo;. IMO, this is not accidental. Granting that the compilation and consolidation of AV corpus still needs close study,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>shAnty-udaka prep</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/kastUriH/shAnty-udaka-prep/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/kastUriH/shAnty-udaka-prep/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;An important part of Atharvavedic initiation is the preparation of Shanti waters. Atharvan herbs are collected and put in water pot and with Japa of AV mantras shantyudaka is prepared. Shantyudaka is employed not just in initiation but all atharvanic rituals.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;An elaborate form of initiation begins with construction of shAlA and preparing a mandala in which atharvan deities are invoked.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The mandala in red cloth is on North West. From right to left, 16 matrikas in a grid if 4x4 and rAtrI Devi are invoked. On North East, on white cloth, navagrahas, mitAdi - set of deities including, bhrigu, angiras and paippalada, 8 nAgas with varaha in center&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Ganesha and ambika below the Naga group&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Haritaki, shrisha, shveta sharshapa, bilva and yava oshadhis&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>अथर्वगायत्रीग्रहणम्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/kastUriH/atharva-gAyatrI-grahaNam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/atharva/meta/articles/kastUriH/atharva-gAyatrI-grahaNam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Apastamba mentions one had to undergo punarupanayana to learn atharva veda. Paddhati quotes fragments of paițïnası gŕhya sūtra. Some notes on the procedure.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Hands are washed with &amp;ldquo;avareńum ava rajo&amp;rdquo; mantra.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Āchamana is done with &amp;ldquo;payasvatīh oşadhayah&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The āchamana as per one&amp;rsquo;s sampradaya.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A flower is crushed with both hands with - yaste gandha pŕthvi; alternatively gandha dvārām.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Pavitra is worn with &amp;ldquo;darbheņa tvam kŕńu&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Then āchārya varańam.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Ācharya performs svati vachana after sankalpa.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Deha shuddhi, ātma shuddhi and dravya shuddhi with atharvan mantras or kalpaja mantras.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Some striking features peculiar to this rite:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
