<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;04 THE AVESTA AND COMPARATIVE MYTHOLOGY on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/04_THE_AVESTA_AND_COMPARATIVE_MYTHOLOGY/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;04 THE AVESTA AND COMPARATIVE MYTHOLOGY on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/04_THE_AVESTA_AND_COMPARATIVE_MYTHOLOGY/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 The Avesta</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/04_THE_AVESTA_AND_COMPARATIVE_MYTHOLOGY/1_The_Avesta/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/04_THE_AVESTA_AND_COMPARATIVE_MYTHOLOGY/1_The_Avesta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;WHILE the literary evidences for Vedic religion are of quite exceptional value and importance, it must be admitted that of other material for realizing the mode in which the gods were conceived there is none available :&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;we have not the statues and other forms of representation, such as paintings, coins, seals, statuettes, &amp;amp;c., which are of such value in the case of Greek religion. No Indian art products or coins of the early Vedic period have been discovered, and that any should so be discovered is most improbable. On the other hand, great value attaches to the Avesta as a source for the understanding of Vedic religion. The close similarity in form of the Avestan language and the Vedic is beyond all doubt: certain changes in sounds make indeed an apparent external divergence, but the vocabulary, the formation of words, and the syntax correspond with much exactitude, and, what is even more important, the verses of the Avesta often breathe the same religious spirit as those of the Rigveda. The similarity of religious views in the pre- Zoroastrian period must have been of the most close and striking type: the prose formulae of the Veda no less than the verses show a profound likeness of form and content, and the practical identity of modes of thought between Iran and India is sufficiently indicated by the striking parallelism between the form of parts of the Buddhist canon and the Iranian literature. The extraordinary similarity of view as of speech, indeed, makes it hard to believe in any early separation of these two branches of the Indo-European family, and suggests that they must have continued to be in close touch with one another until a comparatively late period, when the advance of the Vedic section towards India interposed difficulties of communication between them and the Iranian tribes, and gave a decisive turn to divergences of view which were beginning to form themselves in the Aryan community. The divergence from the common religion of the still undivided Aryans is clearly far greater in the case of the Avesta: there is no good ground to doubt that its present form is the result of the definite individuality of Zoroaster at a comparatively late date, though doubtless he merely brought to a head tendencies which had&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2 Comparative Mythology and Religion</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/04_THE_AVESTA_AND_COMPARATIVE_MYTHOLOGY/2_Comparative_Mythology_and_Religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/04_THE_AVESTA_AND_COMPARATIVE_MYTHOLOGY/2_Comparative_Mythology_and_Religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;5&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;While in the case of the Avesta clear aid is available for the study of Vedic religion, comparatively little can be gained from the comparison of other Indo-European systems of religion. The reason for this fact is not any doubt that the Indo-Europeans before the separation of the race, in whatever way this took place, had a religious system: every probability points in this direction, but the question of the exact form of this system eludes scientific decision. The evidence as to the nature of Greek religion is large in quantity, and much of it is old, but it is perfectly certain that in Greece the Hellenes settled among men of another race and culture who had already developed a high or at least elaborate form of religion, and the Indo-European constituents of Greek religion are difficult to detect, and have been very variously estimated. Roman religion is partly obnoxious to the same defect and partly only known to us at a late date. For Celtic, German, Lettish, Lithuanian,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 The Origin of Religion</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/04_THE_AVESTA_AND_COMPARATIVE_MYTHOLOGY/3_The_Origin_of_Religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/04_THE_AVESTA_AND_COMPARATIVE_MYTHOLOGY/3_The_Origin_of_Religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A further error engendered by the belief in the uniformity of religious development is the theory that it is possible on empirical grounds to determine the origin of religion. The mistake is again a logical one: the origin of religion is a question of philosophy, and a fundamental one, the solution of which is far from probable. The hopelessness of any decision on empiric grounds may be seen from the diametrically opposite results which can be attained by arguing from the same facts. One theory, that of animism in one of its aspects,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4 The Mingling of Races and Cultures</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/04_THE_AVESTA_AND_COMPARATIVE_MYTHOLOGY/4_The_Mingling_of_Races_and_Cultures/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/04_THE_AVESTA_AND_COMPARATIVE_MYTHOLOGY/4_The_Mingling_of_Races_and_Cultures/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Modern views of the religion of Indo-European peoples are strongly influenced by recognition of the fact that race mixture must be assumed to have been an important factor in the development of the religions of the historic peoples such as the Greeks and the Romans. The view that Greek religion is a real representative of a primitive Indo-European religion has been necessarily abandoned, when it is realized that the lands occupied by the Greeks were already the scene of a great and energetic civilization, which cannot be supposed to have left no trace in the beliefs of the invaders, apart altogether from the fact that the physical type of the invaders may have been seriously modified by the intermixture. Similarly, just as the religion of the Homeric poems has been treated as belonging to a small invading aristocracy, so the religion of Rome as revealed to us in the Calendar of Numa in its sanity and moderation has been held to be the work of invaders superimposing a higher faith on the lower form of belief which existed formerly, a view which Dr. Warde Fowler now inclines to favour,5 urging in support the fact that we find a curious contrast between the orderly and decorous Parentalia as a festival of the dead in February and the Lemuria in May, which seems to have been a somewhat savage rite of the banning of ghosts. The latter he deems to&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 Popular and Hieratic Religion</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/04_THE_AVESTA_AND_COMPARATIVE_MYTHOLOGY/5_Popular_and_Hieratic_Religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/04_THE_AVESTA_AND_COMPARATIVE_MYTHOLOGY/5_Popular_and_Hieratic_Religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Nothing is more difficult than to determine in what measure the Vedic religion of the texts was really popular, and how far it merely represented the views of the priests. It would, of course, be folly to depreciate the value of knowledge of the latter, for it is to those only who deeply busy themselves with religion that, for good or bad, changes in popular views are ultimately due, and there is no valid reason to suppose that in the main the gulf between the religion of the Vedic priest and the Aryan people was greater than that between modern Churchmen and the ordinary citizen of the lower social orders.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
