<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;04 THE AVESTA AND COMPARATIVE MYTHOLOGY on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/04_THE_AVESTA_AND_COMPARATIVE_MYTHOLOGY/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;04 THE AVESTA AND COMPARATIVE MYTHOLOGY on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/04_THE_AVESTA_AND_COMPARATIVE_MYTHOLOGY/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 The Avesta</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/04_THE_AVESTA_AND_COMPARATIVE_MYTHOLOGY/1_The_Avesta/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/04_THE_AVESTA_AND_COMPARATIVE_MYTHOLOGY/1_The_Avesta/</guid>
      <description>2
WHILE the literary evidences for Vedic religion are of quite exceptional value and importance, it must be admitted that of other material for realizing the mode in which the gods were conceived there is none available :
we have not the statues and other forms of representation, such as paintings, coins, seals, statuettes, &amp;amp;c., which are of such value in the case of Greek religion. No Indian art products or coins of the early Vedic period have been discovered, and that any should so be discovered is most improbable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2 Comparative Mythology and Religion</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/04_THE_AVESTA_AND_COMPARATIVE_MYTHOLOGY/2_Comparative_Mythology_and_Religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/04_THE_AVESTA_AND_COMPARATIVE_MYTHOLOGY/2_Comparative_Mythology_and_Religion/</guid>
      <description>5
While in the case of the Avesta clear aid is available for the study of Vedic religion, comparatively little can be gained from the comparison of other Indo-European systems of religion. The reason for this fact is not any doubt that the Indo-Europeans before the separation of the race, in whatever way this took place, had a religious system: every probability points in this direction, but the question of the exact form of this system eludes scientific decision.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 The Origin of Religion</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/04_THE_AVESTA_AND_COMPARATIVE_MYTHOLOGY/3_The_Origin_of_Religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/04_THE_AVESTA_AND_COMPARATIVE_MYTHOLOGY/3_The_Origin_of_Religion/</guid>
      <description>1
A further error engendered by the belief in the uniformity of religious development is the theory that it is possible on empirical grounds to determine the origin of religion. The mistake is again a logical one: the origin of religion is a question of philosophy, and a fundamental one, the solution of which is far from probable. The hopelessness of any decision on empiric grounds may be seen from the diametrically opposite results which can be attained by arguing from the same facts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4 The Mingling of Races and Cultures</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/04_THE_AVESTA_AND_COMPARATIVE_MYTHOLOGY/4_The_Mingling_of_Races_and_Cultures/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/04_THE_AVESTA_AND_COMPARATIVE_MYTHOLOGY/4_The_Mingling_of_Races_and_Cultures/</guid>
      <description>Modern views of the religion of Indo-European peoples are strongly influenced by recognition of the fact that race mixture must be assumed to have been an important factor in the development of the religions of the historic peoples such as the Greeks and the Romans. The view that Greek religion is a real representative of a primitive Indo-European religion has been necessarily abandoned, when it is realized that the lands occupied by the Greeks were already the scene of a great and energetic civilization, which cannot be supposed to have left no trace in the beliefs of the invaders, apart altogether from the fact that the physical type of the invaders may have been seriously modified by the intermixture.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5 Popular and Hieratic Religion</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/04_THE_AVESTA_AND_COMPARATIVE_MYTHOLOGY/5_Popular_and_Hieratic_Religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/1_THE_SOURCES/04_THE_AVESTA_AND_COMPARATIVE_MYTHOLOGY/5_Popular_and_Hieratic_Religion/</guid>
      <description>Nothing is more difficult than to determine in what measure the Vedic religion of the texts was really popular, and how far it merely represented the views of the priests. It would, of course, be folly to depreciate the value of knowledge of the latter, for it is to those only who deeply busy themselves with religion that, for good or bad, changes in popular views are ultimately due, and there is no valid reason to suppose that in the main the gulf between the religion of the Vedic priest and the Aryan people was greater than that between modern Churchmen and the ordinary citizen of the lower social orders.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
