<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;12 ABSTRACT DEITIES AND SONDERGÖTTER on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/12_ABSTRACT_DEITIES_AND_SONDERGTTER/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;12 ABSTRACT DEITIES AND SONDERGÖTTER on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/12_ABSTRACT_DEITIES_AND_SONDERGTTER/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 The Nature of Abstract Deities</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/12_ABSTRACT_DEITIES_AND_SONDERGTTER/1_The_Nature_of_Abstract_Deities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/12_ABSTRACT_DEITIES_AND_SONDERGTTER/1_The_Nature_of_Abstract_Deities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is unfortunate that no term has yet been found which can be used to describe the gods, who do not rest on the basis of some natural phenomenon or some activity which is taking place in external nature, without conveying the false impression which is created by the adoption of the current term abstract. The idea of the deification of n abstraction inevitably suggest that the god was the production of priestly speculation; that he, therefore, could never be a really popular god; and that it could not be felt that the god was active and powerful to help in the same way as a god based on some phenomenon of nature. This is clearly far from being the case: whatever the origin of the gods which are called abstract, many of them attained in India to genuine and real popular belief, and were every whit as much living to the popular mind as gods for whom we can see a basis in nature.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2 Tvastṛ and other Agent Gods</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/12_ABSTRACT_DEITIES_AND_SONDERGTTER/2_tvastR_and_other_Agent_Gods/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/12_ABSTRACT_DEITIES_AND_SONDERGTTER/2_tvastR_and_other_Agent_Gods/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By far the most important of the agent gods is Tvastṛ, who is mentioned some sixty-five times in the Rigveda, most often in the late first and tenth books, but also in the family books, though rarely in the seventh of the Vasistha family, and in the eighth. Like the other gods of the Rigveda he goes to the heaven, and bestows blessings, but his characteristic feature is the&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This phase of belief is that currently&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 Deified States or Conditions</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/12_ABSTRACT_DEITIES_AND_SONDERGTTER/5_Deified_States_or_Conditions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/12_ABSTRACT_DEITIES_AND_SONDERGTTER/5_Deified_States_or_Conditions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;211&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Of these divine figures special interest attaches to Aramati, ‘devotion&amp;rsquo;, who is also described as the great one: in the Avesta Aramaiti is a genius of the earth and also of wisdom, and there seems no real reason for objection to the view that the personification goes back to the Indo-Iranian period,1 though it is doubtful whether we can see in the Rigvedic epithet &amp;lsquo;great&amp;rsquo; a suggestion that the earth which often bears this epithet was placed under the care of this spirit, and still more whether we can believe Sāyaṇa&amp;rsquo;s assertion that Aramati is the earth. Another spirit who may with propriety be referred to the Indo- Iranian period is Puraṁdhi, whose name occurs some nine times in the Rigveda: she is usually mentioned along with Bhaga, who himself is a representative of this class of gods, but who has become an Aditya, twice or thrice with Pûṣan and Savitṛ, and once with Agni and Viṣṇu. She clearly corresponds to the Avestan Parendi, who is normally ranked as goddess of plenty and abundance: the view of Hillebrandt sees in her and in the Vedic Puramdhi a goddess of activity: the scanty evidence leaves us with no conclusive means of testing either version, especially as the two ideas can be made by a little ingenuity almost synonymous. A goddess Dhiṣaṇā who is mentioned about a dozen times in the Rigveda 5 may also be a goddess of abundance or of impulsion. Anumati, favour of the gods&amp;rsquo;, is twice. personified in the Rigveda,&amp;quot; and is besought to be propitious and to grant long life. In the Yajurveda and in the Atharvaveda she appears as a goddess who presides over propagation and favours love, and in the Sutras she is clearly understood as connected with the moon, denoting the day before full moon.&amp;quot; It is difficult to suppose that this view of the deity is anything but a later conception, for there is nothing to support it in the early mention of the deity. Sūnṛtā, &amp;lsquo;bounty&amp;rsquo;, is here and there personified in the Rigveda, while on the contrary the spirit of niggardliness, Arāti, avarice&amp;rsquo;, is represented as a demon in the Atharvaveda. Asunīti,10&amp;rsquo;spirit leading &amp;lsquo;, is besought in the Rigveda in one hymn to grant long life.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>6 Aditi and Diti</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/12_ABSTRACT_DEITIES_AND_SONDERGTTER/6_Aditi_and_Diti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/12_ABSTRACT_DEITIES_AND_SONDERGTTER/6_Aditi_and_Diti/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The place of Aditi in the Vedic pantheon is very remarkable, if, as is on the whole most probable, she is to be regarded as an abstract deity. She has, indeed, no entire hymn in the Rigveda, but she is mentioned not less than eighty times, and in the great majority of these with her sons, the Adityas. Of her personality little is said beyond the fact that she is intact, extended, bright, and luminous, a supporter of creatures, an epithet enjoyed by Mitra and Varuna, and belonging to all men. She is invoked at morning, noon, and evening. While the Adityas are normally her sons, she is once said to be their sister, and to be the daughter of the Vasus. She appears in the Yajurveda &amp;quot; once as the wife of Viṣṇu: in the post-Vedic mythology she is especially the daughter of Dakṣa and the mother of Vivasvant, and of Viṣṇu, but also of all the gods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>7 The Wives of the Gods</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/12_ABSTRACT_DEITIES_AND_SONDERGTTER/7_The_Wives_of_the_Gods/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/12_ABSTRACT_DEITIES_AND_SONDERGTTER/7_The_Wives_of_the_Gods/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In some cases the wives of the gods are obviously based on natural phenomena, the relation of two such phenomena presenting for some reason or other traits which suggest their close connexion: the primeval pair is that of heaven and earth, and on this doubtless the other accounts of the marriages of the gods are in part based. Other examples are also obviously suggested by natural events: thus the wedding of Soma the king as the moon to the twentyseven or twenty-eight Nakṣatras is a mythical account of the obvious relation of the moon to the constellations in question. Again, the wedding of Soma as the moon with the sun-maiden may conceivably be due to some primitive astronomical views. The making of the Dawn the wife of the Aśvins is also explicable on mythological grounds. The wedding of the same goddess to Puṣan, the sun-god, is also not unnatural.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
