<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;12 ABSTRACT DEITIES AND SONDERGÖTTER on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/12_ABSTRACT_DEITIES_AND_SONDERGTTER/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;12 ABSTRACT DEITIES AND SONDERGÖTTER on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/12_ABSTRACT_DEITIES_AND_SONDERGTTER/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 The Nature of Abstract Deities</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/12_ABSTRACT_DEITIES_AND_SONDERGTTER/1_The_Nature_of_Abstract_Deities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/12_ABSTRACT_DEITIES_AND_SONDERGTTER/1_The_Nature_of_Abstract_Deities/</guid>
      <description>It is unfortunate that no term has yet been found which can be used to describe the gods, who do not rest on the basis of some natural phenomenon or some activity which is taking place in external nature, without conveying the false impression which is created by the adoption of the current term abstract. The idea of the deification of n abstraction inevitably suggest that the god was the production of priestly speculation; that he, therefore, could never be a really popular god; and that it could not be felt that the god was active and powerful to help in the same way as a god based on some phenomenon of nature.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2 Tvastṛ and other Agent Gods</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/12_ABSTRACT_DEITIES_AND_SONDERGTTER/2_tvastR_and_other_Agent_Gods/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/12_ABSTRACT_DEITIES_AND_SONDERGTTER/2_tvastR_and_other_Agent_Gods/</guid>
      <description>By far the most important of the agent gods is Tvastṛ, who is mentioned some sixty-five times in the Rigveda, most often in the late first and tenth books, but also in the family books, though rarely in the seventh of the Vasistha family, and in the eighth. Like the other gods of the Rigveda he goes to the heaven, and bestows blessings, but his characteristic feature is the
This phase of belief is that currently</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5 Deified States or Conditions</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/12_ABSTRACT_DEITIES_AND_SONDERGTTER/5_Deified_States_or_Conditions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/12_ABSTRACT_DEITIES_AND_SONDERGTTER/5_Deified_States_or_Conditions/</guid>
      <description>2
8
211
Of these divine figures special interest attaches to Aramati, ‘devotion&amp;rsquo;, who is also described as the great one: in the Avesta Aramaiti is a genius of the earth and also of wisdom, and there seems no real reason for objection to the view that the personification goes back to the Indo-Iranian period,1 though it is doubtful whether we can see in the Rigvedic epithet &amp;lsquo;great&amp;rsquo; a suggestion that the earth which often bears this epithet was placed under the care of this spirit, and still more whether we can believe Sāyaṇa&amp;rsquo;s assertion that Aramati is the earth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>6 Aditi and Diti</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/12_ABSTRACT_DEITIES_AND_SONDERGTTER/6_Aditi_and_Diti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/12_ABSTRACT_DEITIES_AND_SONDERGTTER/6_Aditi_and_Diti/</guid>
      <description>The place of Aditi in the Vedic pantheon is very remarkable, if, as is on the whole most probable, she is to be regarded as an abstract deity. She has, indeed, no entire hymn in the Rigveda, but she is mentioned not less than eighty times, and in the great majority of these with her sons, the Adityas. Of her personality little is said beyond the fact that she is intact, extended, bright, and luminous, a supporter of creatures, an epithet enjoyed by Mitra and Varuna, and belonging to all men.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>7 The Wives of the Gods</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/12_ABSTRACT_DEITIES_AND_SONDERGTTER/7_The_Wives_of_the_Gods/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/12_ABSTRACT_DEITIES_AND_SONDERGTTER/7_The_Wives_of_the_Gods/</guid>
      <description>In some cases the wives of the gods are obviously based on natural phenomena, the relation of two such phenomena presenting for some reason or other traits which suggest their close connexion: the primeval pair is that of heaven and earth, and on this doubtless the other accounts of the marriages of the gods are in part based. Other examples are also obviously suggested by natural events: thus the wedding of Soma the king as the moon to the twentyseven or twenty-eight Nakṣatras is a mythical account of the obvious relation of the moon to the constellations in question.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
