<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;08 THE GREAT GODS-CELESTIAL on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;08 THE GREAT GODS-CELESTIAL on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 Dyaus the Father</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/1_Dyaus_the_Father/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/1_Dyaus_the_Father/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;DYAUS has the honour of being the only Indo-European god who is certainly to be recognized as having existed in the earliest period, and he has been claimed for that time as a real sovereign of the gods, much as Zeus among the Greeks. For this view there is clearly no cogent evidence available, though equally there is no cogent evidence to the contrary, for the fact that Dyaus is not a great god in India may be di e to decline in greatness, not to the absence of such greatness originally. In the Rigveda he has not a single hymn of his own, and his appearance is nearly always in one or other of two capacities: either he is the parent, who has as children Uṣas, the Aśvins, Agni, Parjanya. Surya, the Adityas, the Maruts, and the Añgirases, or he is coupled with the earth, Pṛthivĩ, or at least mentioned with other deities of whom Pṛthivi is normally one2; the legend of the union and separation of the two is often referred to, but without detail. Where he stands alone, he is mentioned as father of Indra, of Agni, as a father, as rich in seed, as a red bull which bellows downward, or, by another theriomorphic idea, as a black steed decked with pearls, an obvious allusion to the midnight sky. He smiles through the clouds, a trait which can only refer to the lightening sky, and an incipient anthropomorphism appears in the statement that he holds the bolt. With Pṛthivi he shares six hymns, but they have little force or significance; of more interest is the fact that sky and earth are called the two mothers, and that not rarely the word dyaus is feminine, a fact which shows that much weight cannot be laid on the contrast between male and female, stress upon which as a principle of Vedic religion has been laid by Bergaigne. With the higher life of the community Dyaus has little to do; he bears the usual title of the great gods, Asura, and with earth he is asked to avert sin committed against the gods or a friend or the head of the clan, but this is merely an application to the god of a commonplace prayer. The Vedic evidence&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2 Varuna, Mitra, and the Adityas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/2_Varuna_Mitra_and_the_Adityas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/2_Varuna_Mitra_and_the_Adityas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The slight prominence of Dyaus in the Indian period is doubtless in part at least due to the prominence of Mitra and Varuṇa, of which pair the greatest by far is Varuna. Mitra, indeed, by his close association with Varuna has lost any real independence of character. Though Varuna is anthropomorphic and has arms, hands, feet, walks, drives, sits, eats, and drinks, the cosmic character of his eye is brought very clearly: the eye of Mitra and Varuna is repeatedly declared to be the sun, and it figures conspicuously in all the hymns regarding Varuṇa. Varuṇa is also far-sighted and thousand-eyed: he wears a golden mantle and a shining robe. He and Mitra drive with the rays of the sun as with arms, and like Savitṛ and Tvastṛ they are beautiful handed. In striking contrast with this picture of a fair god is that suggested by a passage in the Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa, where Varuṇa is described as a bald yellow-eyed old man; but this passage must be read in its context, from which it appears clearly that we have to deal not with a primitive, but with a mystical, view of the nature of Varuṇa.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 Sūrya, Savitṛ, and Pūṣan</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/3_sUrya_savitR_and_pUShan/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/3_sUrya_savitR_and_pUShan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In Surya we have the sun-god in his simplest and most direct form, and ten hymns of the Rigveda are devoted to him. His natural character is very obvious in all that is told of him: he is the eye of the sky or of Varuṇa and Mitra he is far-seeing, the spy of the whole world who looks on the deeds of men and rouses them to action. He is an Aditya, but is also distinguished from the Adityas. Like other gods he is a son of Dyaus. In the Purusasūkta he is made to be born from the eye of Puruṣa, and by an inversion of this idea the eye of the dead man is said to go to the sun. A late and absurd legend of the Atharvaveda makes the sun as Divākara born from the demon Vṛtra.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4 Viṣnu</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/4_viShnu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/4_viShnu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;But in that case&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the Rigveda Viṣṇu can claim but five whole hymns, and his name occurs not more than a hundred times in all. He is said to be young, but vast in body, not a child, and his one action is the taking of three strides : hence he is called the wide strider. Of these strides two are visible, the third is beyond the ken even of the birds, or, as it is also put, his third name is in the bright region of the heaven. But again it is said that the liberal see the highest place of Viṣṇu like an eye in the sky. The highest place is Visṇu&amp;rsquo;s favourite dwelling, there also are the gods and pious men, there is Indra and the many-horned swiftly moving cows, doubtless the clouds. There can be little doubt as to what the three steps are: the later Saṁhitās, the Brāhmaṇas, and Śakapūṇi, a predecessor of Yāska, agree in equating them with the three divisions of the universe, and the alternative view of Aurṇavābha that they correspond with the rising sun, the zenith, and the setting is in flat contradiction with the references of the Vedas to the nature of the highest place. The motive for the strides is variously given as for men in distress, to bestow the earth upon man as a dwelling, to obtain wide-stepping existence or the existence of men. Again Viṣṇu is essentially the swift of motion and&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 Vivasvant</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/5_Vivasvant/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/5_Vivasvant/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Vivasvant is not the subject of any complete hymn in the Rigveda, where, however, he is mentioned about thirty times. The most important thing about him is his relation to Manu, the ancestor of the human race, who thence bears the name Vaivasvata or Vivasvant, taking simply his father&amp;rsquo;s name as a sign of paternity. Men are also in the Brāhmaṇas styled directly his offspring, and the Rigveda ascribes to him as to other gods the fathership of the gods. His wife is Saraṇyū, the daughter of Tvaṣṭr, and he is the father of the Aśvins. To him and to Matariśvan Agni was first manifested, and he has Mātariśvan or Agni as his messenger. Soma again dwells with Vivasvant and is cleansed by his daughters, doubtless, in the ordinary mythical style of the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>6 The Aśvins</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/6_The_ashvins/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/6_The_ashvins/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Aśvins are, next to Indra, Agni, and Soma, the gods most frequently mentioned in the Rigveda, where they claim more than fifty hymns and are mentioned over 400 times. The most constant feature is their duplicate nature: they are compared to eyes, hands, feet, wings, and animals which&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1 RV. viii. 67. 20.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;xviii, 3. 62.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3 x. 5. 2. 4; RV. x. 39. 2.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;• MS. i. 6. 12.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>7 The Goddess Dawn</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/7_The_Goddess_Dawn/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/7_The_Goddess_Dawn/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Usas the goddess is no small figure in the Rigveda: she is the subject of twenty hymns and is mentioned not less than 300 times in all, and the hymns addressed to her are among the most brilliant in the whole of the Samhitā. The personification of the dawn is of the slightest description, and takes the form of picturing her as a maiden decked by her mother in gay attire, who reveals her bosom to mortal eyes. She is young, being born again and again,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>8 The Moon</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/8_The_Moon/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/8_The_Moon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Apart from his connexion with Soma,2 the moon is not prominent in the Vedic literature, unless with Hillebrandt we recognize him under such guises as that of Bṛhaspati, Apāṁ Napāt, Varuṇa, Yama, Narāśañsa, or Tvaṣtṛ, or Viśvarūpa. He appears rarely in conjunction with Surya in the compounds Sūryāmāsā and Sūryācandramasā, but little is said of the pair beyond noting their alternate appearance, which is once attributed to Bṛhaspati, their creation by the creator, and the fact that they are the two bright eyes of Varuna. The birth of the moon from the sun is recognized, as well as its regular death. The connexion of the moon with the mind is early recorded,&amp;quot; and may stand in relation to its connexion with the Fathers. In addition to the influence of the moon on vegetation, its connexion with the tides is recognized.&amp;quot; The moon phases also receive some degree of worship, and the darkness in the face of the moon is accounted for in various ways.9 The Jaiminiya Brāhmaṇa 10 already records the existence in the moon of a hare, identified with Yama, whence the later name of Śaśin, a view corresponding to the occidental belief in the man in the moon. Among other identifications Prajapati appears once equated with Candramas, but the more normal view is found in the idea of the Kauṣītaki Brāhmaṇa that from the asceticism of Prajapati there sprang up five beings, Agni, Vāyu, Aditya, Candramas, and Usas. Another passage tells that the first four of these deities made good the members of Prajapati when the work of creation exhausted him and he fell to pieces.11&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
