<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;08 THE GREAT GODS-CELESTIAL on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;08 THE GREAT GODS-CELESTIAL on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 Dyaus the Father</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/1_Dyaus_the_Father/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/1_Dyaus_the_Father/</guid>
      <description>DYAUS has the honour of being the only Indo-European god who is certainly to be recognized as having existed in the earliest period, and he has been claimed for that time as a real sovereign of the gods, much as Zeus among the Greeks. For this view there is clearly no cogent evidence available, though equally there is no cogent evidence to the contrary, for the fact that Dyaus is not a great god in India may be di e to decline in greatness, not to the absence of such greatness originally.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2 Varuna, Mitra, and the Adityas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/2_Varuna_Mitra_and_the_Adityas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/2_Varuna_Mitra_and_the_Adityas/</guid>
      <description>The slight prominence of Dyaus in the Indian period is doubtless in part at least due to the prominence of Mitra and Varuṇa, of which pair the greatest by far is Varuna. Mitra, indeed, by his close association with Varuna has lost any real independence of character. Though Varuna is anthropomorphic and has arms, hands, feet, walks, drives, sits, eats, and drinks, the cosmic character of his eye is brought very clearly: the eye of Mitra and Varuna is repeatedly declared to be the sun, and it figures conspicuously in all the hymns regarding Varuṇa.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 Sūrya, Savitṛ, and Pūṣan</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/3_sUrya_savitR_and_pUShan/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/3_sUrya_savitR_and_pUShan/</guid>
      <description>In Surya we have the sun-god in his simplest and most direct form, and ten hymns of the Rigveda are devoted to him. His natural character is very obvious in all that is told of him: he is the eye of the sky or of Varuṇa and Mitra he is far-seeing, the spy of the whole world who looks on the deeds of men and rouses them to action. He is an Aditya, but is also distinguished from the Adityas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4 Viṣnu</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/4_viShnu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/4_viShnu/</guid>
      <description>But in that case
In the Rigveda Viṣṇu can claim but five whole hymns, and his name occurs not more than a hundred times in all. He is said to be young, but vast in body, not a child, and his one action is the taking of three strides : hence he is called the wide strider. Of these strides two are visible, the third is beyond the ken even of the birds, or, as it is also put, his third name is in the bright region of the heaven.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5 Vivasvant</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/5_Vivasvant/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/5_Vivasvant/</guid>
      <description>Vivasvant is not the subject of any complete hymn in the Rigveda, where, however, he is mentioned about thirty times. The most important thing about him is his relation to Manu, the ancestor of the human race, who thence bears the name Vaivasvata or Vivasvant, taking simply his father&amp;rsquo;s name as a sign of paternity. Men are also in the Brāhmaṇas styled directly his offspring, and the Rigveda ascribes to him as to other gods the fathership of the gods.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>6 The Aśvins</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/6_The_ashvins/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/6_The_ashvins/</guid>
      <description>8
The Aśvins are, next to Indra, Agni, and Soma, the gods most frequently mentioned in the Rigveda, where they claim more than fifty hymns and are mentioned over 400 times. The most constant feature is their duplicate nature: they are compared to eyes, hands, feet, wings, and animals which
1 RV. viii. 67. 20.
xviii, 3. 62. 3 x. 5. 2. 4; RV. x. 39. 2.
• MS. i. 6.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>7 The Goddess Dawn</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/7_The_Goddess_Dawn/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/7_The_Goddess_Dawn/</guid>
      <description>Usas the goddess is no small figure in the Rigveda: she is the subject of twenty hymns and is mentioned not less than 300 times in all, and the hymns addressed to her are among the most brilliant in the whole of the Samhitā. The personification of the dawn is of the slightest description, and takes the form of picturing her as a maiden decked by her mother in gay attire, who reveals her bosom to mortal eyes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>8 The Moon</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/8_The_Moon/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/08_THE_GREAT_GODS-CELESTIAL/8_The_Moon/</guid>
      <description>Apart from his connexion with Soma,2 the moon is not prominent in the Vedic literature, unless with Hillebrandt we recognize him under such guises as that of Bṛhaspati, Apāṁ Napāt, Varuṇa, Yama, Narāśañsa, or Tvaṣtṛ, or Viśvarūpa. He appears rarely in conjunction with Surya in the compounds Sūryāmāsā and Sūryācandramasā, but little is said of the pair beyond noting their alternate appearance, which is once attributed to Bṛhaspati, their creation by the creator, and the fact that they are the two bright eyes of Varuna.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
