<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Calasso - Ardor on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Calasso - Ardor on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 REMOTE BEINGS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/01_REMOTE_BEINGS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/01_REMOTE_BEINGS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/00017.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;They were remote beings. Remote not only from modern man but from their ancient contemporaries. Distant not just as another culture, but as another celestial body. So distant that the point from which they are viewed becomes almost irrelevant. Nothing much changes whether that point is today or a hundred years ago. For those born in India, certain words, certain forms, certain objects may seem familiar, like an invincible atavism. But they are scattered fragments of a dream whose story has been blotted out.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 YĀJÑAVALKYA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/02_yAjnavalkya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/02_yAjnavalkya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/00020.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sometime before the days of the Buddha—no one can be quite sure when—there appeared the figure of Yājñavalkya. Sacrifice (&lt;em&gt;yajña&lt;/em&gt;) is in his name, but the meaning of -&lt;em&gt;valkya&lt;/em&gt; is not so clear. He had received his learning from the Sun, Āditya. To &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt;, one must &lt;em&gt;burn.&lt;/em&gt; Otherwise all knowledge is ineffective. One must therefore practice &lt;em&gt;tapas. Tapas&lt;/em&gt; means “ardor”—it means the heat within the mind but also cosmic heat. And the Sun is the being that produces heat more than any other. To gain learning, it is natural to turn to him. In the oldest texts, wherever Yājñavalkya appears, he speaks little and speaks last. His speech is cutting, decisive. To clash with him is a fearful prospect. Even the “shrewd” Śākalya, whom Staal described as “the first great linguist in human history,” since he established the Padapatha version of the &lt;em&gt;Ṛgveda&lt;/em&gt;—the one we still read today, with its text divided into separate words—had to suffer its consequences. He was unable to answer a question posed by Yājñavalkya and his head burst into pieces. His bones were gathered by scavengers who did not know to whom they had belonged.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 ANIMALS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/03_ANIMALS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/03_ANIMALS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/00023.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Consumed by the arrogance of knowledge, the young Bhṛgu, son of the supreme god Varuṇa, was sent off by his father into the world (into this world, according to the &lt;em&gt;Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt;, into the other world according to the version in the &lt;em&gt;Jaiminīya Brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt;) to &lt;em&gt;see&lt;/em&gt; what knowledge alone could not reveal, to find out how the world itself is made. Without this, all knowledge is pointless.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the east, Bhṛgu came across men who were slaughtering other men. Bhṛgu asked: “Why?” They answered: “Because these men did the same to us in the other world.” He saw the same strange scene in the south. In the west there were men eating other men and sitting about, calmly. In the north as well, amid piercing cries, there were men eating other men.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 THE PROGENITOR</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/04_THE_PROGENITOR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/04_THE_PROGENITOR/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/00026.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The god at the origin of everything didn’t have a name but a title: Prajāpati, Lord of the Creatures. He discovered this when one of his sons, Indra, told him: “I want to be what you are.” Prajāpati asked him: “But who (&lt;em&gt;ka&lt;/em&gt;) am I?” And Indra answered: “‘Exactly what you just said.’ So Prajāpati became Ka.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Indra wanted his father’s “greatness” or, according to others, his “splendor.” And Prajāpati had no difficulty in divesting himself of it. So Indra became king of the gods, even though Prajāpati had been “the sole lord of creation.” But it was neither “greatness” nor “splendor” that made Prajāpati the “god alone above the gods,” a formula that smacks of incompatibility only for latter-day readers in the West. What Prajāpati could not renounce was something else: the unknown, the irreducible unknown. At the moment in which he knew he was Ka, Prajāpati became guarantor of the uncertainty involved in questioning. He guaranteed that it would always remain. If Ka didn’t exist, the world would be a sequence of questions and answers, at the end of which everything would be fixed once and for all—and the unknown could be erased from life. But since Prajāpati “is everything”—and Prajāpati is Ka—there is a question in every part of everything that finds an answer in the name of everything. And this in turn takes us back to the question, which opens onto the unknown. But this is not an unknown that is due to the inadequacy of the human intellect. It is unknown even for the god who includes it in his name. Divine omniscience does not extend to itself.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 THEY WHO SAW THE HYMNS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/05_THEY_WHO_SAW_THE_HYMNS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/05_THEY_WHO_SAW_THE_HYMNS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/00003.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The hymns of the &lt;em&gt;Ṛgveda&lt;/em&gt; were said to have been &lt;em&gt;seen&lt;/em&gt; by the &lt;em&gt;ṛṣis.&lt;/em&gt; The &lt;em&gt;ṛṣis&lt;/em&gt; may therefore be described as “seers.” They saw the hymns in the same way as we see a tree or a river. They were the most disconcerting, least easily explainable beings in the Vedic cosmos. Chief among them were the Saptarṣis, the Seven who lived in the stars of the Great Bear, who have some affinity with the Seven Greek Sages, with the Islamic &lt;em&gt;abdāls&lt;/em&gt;, and with the Seven Akkadian Apkallus of the Apsu. But something in the very nature of the &lt;em&gt;ṛṣis&lt;/em&gt; was an epistemological scandal: they alone were allowed to belong to the unmanifest and at the same time take part in the events of everyday life, which they secretly ruled.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 THE ADVENTURES OF MIND AND SPEECH</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/06_THE_ADVENTURES_OF_MIND_AND_SPEECH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/06_THE_ADVENTURES_OF_MIND_AND_SPEECH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/00005.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Manas&lt;/em&gt;, “mind” (later &lt;em&gt;mens&lt;/em&gt; in Latin), “thought.” But above all the pure fact of being conscious, awake. For the Vedic people, everything came from consciousness, in the sense of pure awareness devoid of any other attribute. They invoked it delicately, as “the divine one that comes forward from afar when we awake and falls back when we slumber.” Likewise “she through whom the seers, able creators, operate in the sacrifice and in the rites.” They said it was an “unprecedented wonder, dwelling in living beings.” They recognized in it “what envelops all that was, is and shall be.” They called it “stable in the heart and yet moveable, infinitely fast.” The unattainable speed of the mind: here it was named, evoked, adored perhaps for the first time. Finally the much-repeated wish: “May that which it [the mind] conceives be propitious for me.” The mind is an external power, equal to the gods and superior to the gods, which conceives in solitude and can, through its grace, reverberate in the mind of every living being. And the first, the highest wish, is that this might take place “propitiously.” &lt;em&gt;Manas&lt;/em&gt; would then act like “a good charioteer,” it would become the one “who powerfully guides his men like steeds, by the reins.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 *ĀTMAN*</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/07_Atman/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/07_Atman/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Brahman&lt;/em&gt; or the knowledge of it are no different among very powerful beings such as Vāmadeva or in the much less powerful men of today. But one may suspect that in men of today the fruit of the knowledge of &lt;em&gt;brahman&lt;/em&gt; is uncertain.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;—Śaṅkara, &lt;em&gt;Bṛhadāraṇyakopaniṣadbhāṣya&lt;/em&gt;, 1.4.10&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/00008.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;From the &lt;em&gt;Ṛgveda&lt;/em&gt; to the &lt;em&gt;Bhagavad Gītā&lt;/em&gt; a way of reasoning is developed that never acknowledges a single subject, but rather presupposes a dual subject. This is because the constitution of the mind is dual: consisting of a gaze that perceives (eats) the world and of a gaze that contemplates the gaze directed at the world. The first expression of this idea appears with the two birds in hymn 1.164 of the &lt;em&gt;Ṛgveda&lt;/em&gt;: “Two birds, a couple of friends, are perched on the same tree. One of them eats the sweet berry of the &lt;em&gt;pippal&lt;/em&gt;; the other, without eating, watches.” There is no more basic revelation than this. And the &lt;em&gt;Ṛgveda&lt;/em&gt; presents it with the clarity of its enigmatic language. The dual constitution of the mind implies that two birds dwell perpetually within each of us: the Self, &lt;em&gt;ātman&lt;/em&gt;, and the I, &lt;em&gt;aham.&lt;/em&gt; Friends, alike, sitting on the tree at the same level, one might seem the double of the other. And so it is in the life of many, who never manage to distinguish between them. But, once their difference has been recognized, everything changes. Every moment becomes the superimposition of two perceptions that can add together, cancel each other out, multiply each other. When they multiply each other, according to the mysterious formula 1 × 1, thought springs forth. Even if, seen from outside, all remains the same. The answer seems still to be 1.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 PERFECT WAKEFULNESS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/08_PERFECT_WAKEFULNESS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/08_PERFECT_WAKEFULNESS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/00014.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The wakefulness the Upaniṣads speak of (and the &lt;em&gt;Ṛgveda&lt;/em&gt; before them) is a state opposed, not to sleep, but to another kind of wakefulness—inattentive, inert, automatic. Awakening means rousing oneself from that kind of wakefulness, as from a vapid dream. Philosophers have not regarded this swerve within the mind as worthy of consideration, but it became the focus of thought in one place and in one period: in India, in the time between the Veda and the Buddha—and then reverberated unremittingly through all the centuries thereafter.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 THE BRĀHMAṆAS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/09_THE_brAhmaNas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/09_THE_brAhmaNas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;He who knew the taut thread on which all creatures are woven, he who knew the thread of the thread, would know the great Exegesis.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;—&lt;em&gt;Atharvaveda&lt;/em&gt; 10.8.37 (trans. L. Renou, 1938)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;He who knows the taut thread on which these creatures are woven, he who knows the thread of the thread, knows the great essence of &lt;em&gt;brahman.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;—&lt;em&gt;Atharvaveda&lt;/em&gt; 10.8.37 (trans. L. Renou, 1956)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/00006.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Brāhmaṇas are the part of the Veda most neglected by scholars and most ignored by readers. In the second volume of Dandekar’s &lt;em&gt;Vedic Bibliography&lt;/em&gt;, the list of writings on the Brāhmaṇas fills eight pages, while thirty are taken up by the Upaniṣads and twenty-eight by the &lt;em&gt;Ṛgveda.&lt;/em&gt; We can guess that not so many scholars, and even fewer readers, have taken any interest in them. And we might wonder why.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 THE LINE OF THE FIRES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/10_THE_LINE_OF_THE_FIRES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/10_THE_LINE_OF_THE_FIRES/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/00009.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Man’s initial state is formless, opaque, composite, and also “impure.” Man is a being who “speaks untruth.” He could carry on living like this, though leaving no significant trace. Otherwise he must compose a series of connected gestures that make an “action,” &lt;em&gt;karman.&lt;/em&gt; The quintessential action, the one that presupposes and assures that gestures have a meaning, is the sacrificial work.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But what is the origin of this work whose first peculiarity is that of being the model for all other work? Desire. Not a general, roving, multifarious, shifting desire—for “mortal man has many desires” and this plurality of desires dwells unremittingly within him from the first to the last moment of his life—but a &lt;em&gt;single&lt;/em&gt; desire that seeks to detach itself from every other, to break its ties with the mesh of other desires and find the path to fulfillment. How? By becoming a “vow,” &lt;em&gt;vrata.&lt;/em&gt; Entering a vow is like entering another space, that of detached desire, which binds itself, barricades itself from the outside world, and builds a sequence of gestures within the new space that reaffirm it each time. What then is the first of these gestures? To touch water. But not anywhere. To touch it on a point of the invisible line that joins the &lt;em&gt;āhavanīya&lt;/em&gt; fire and the &lt;em&gt;gārhapatya&lt;/em&gt; fire. This is the &lt;em&gt;line of the fires.&lt;/em&gt; The &lt;em&gt;gārhapatya&lt;/em&gt;, “domestic,” hearth is circular, sited to the west. There the fire is lit. There burn the embers with which the other fires will be lit. Not far away, to the east, on any type of ground, freshly swept with &lt;em&gt;palāśa&lt;/em&gt; branches (&lt;em&gt;Butea frondosa&lt;/em&gt;, Flame of the Forest, but it should also be thought of as &lt;em&gt;brahman&lt;/em&gt;), a square hearth is built, called &lt;em&gt;āhavanīya.&lt;/em&gt; On this fire the oblations will be offered—and it can be lit only with an ember taken from the &lt;em&gt;gārhapatya&lt;/em&gt; fire. The &lt;em&gt;āhavanīya&lt;/em&gt; fire is the sky, the &lt;em&gt;gārhapatya&lt;/em&gt; fire is the earth (and it is circular since the earth is a circle at the center of other circles.) Between the two fires is the atmosphere, where we breathe, where we act. In the middle there is also “the trunk of the body,” where the heart, life, beats. There are other fires, but these two must be set up first: &lt;em&gt;āhavanīya&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;gārhapatya.&lt;/em&gt; They provide the tension on which everything rests. Everything is supposed to happen on the invisible line that connects them. The miracle behind everything else can happen only here—only here can things acquire meaning. If man wishes to escape from the untruth in which he is born, and in which he is destined to remain, he must tread that line, touch the water there and formulate a desire. In this way he will &lt;em&gt;enter the vow&lt;/em&gt;, enter the hazardous state in which truth can be spoken, in which desire can be fulfilled, in which the gesture assumes a meaning. If every sacrifice is a “ship that sails toward the sky,” the two fires, &lt;em&gt;āhavanīya&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;gārhapatya&lt;/em&gt;, will be the sides of that ship, the limits within which the pilot (each and every sacrificer) must move, from the moment in which he begins to carry out certain movements: those movements, if they take place &lt;em&gt;between the two fires&lt;/em&gt;, acquire a meaning that separates them from the ebb and flow of human actions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 VEDIC EROTICA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/11_VEDIC_EROTICA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/11_VEDIC_EROTICA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/00012.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The altar is a woman with perfect proportions: “With broad hips, shoulders a little less broad, and narrow at the waist.” Like a woman, it must not be naked. It is sprinkled with fine gravel or sand, so as to cover its body with a light gleaming film (“gravel is certainly an adornment, since gravel is fairly luminous”). Then with twigs and grass. The woman—the altar—makes herself beautiful, is helped to look beautiful, ready for the arrival of the gods. And so she passes a night.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 GODS WHO OFFER LIBATIONS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/12_GODS_WHO_OFFER_LIBATIONS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/12_GODS_WHO_OFFER_LIBATIONS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/00015.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There is one gesture that inextricably unites the whole Indo-European world. It is the gesture of the libation. The pouring of a liquid into a fire that flares up, destroying a valuable or an ordinary substance in the flame. Libation is found back in the Minoan period, on the Hagia Triada sarcophagus. Homer’s characters often carry it out as a necessary preliminary to their exploits. Sacrifices performed with no libation are extremely rare. And even Olympian gods are depicted on many vases in the act of offering a libation. Erika Simon has studied them—and has asked the inevitable question: to whom are they offering the libation? And why do gods feel they have to do it, just as much as humans?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 RESIDUE AND SURPLUS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/13_RESIDUE_AND_SURPLUS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/13_RESIDUE_AND_SURPLUS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In that place therefore the blessed god, all-present, sleeping on the ocean, cloaked his night with thick darkness. But a surplus of luminous quality awakened him and he saw the empty world.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;—Mahābhārata&lt;/em&gt;, 3.272.40–41ab&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/00019.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The whole of Indian tradition, in its various branches, is influenced by a &lt;em&gt;doctrine of residue&lt;/em&gt;, which can be embodied in three words, corresponding to three successive stages: &lt;em&gt;vāstu&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;ucchiṣṭa&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;śeṣa.&lt;/em&gt; It has a key role as a doctrine, similar to that of &lt;em&gt;ousía&lt;/em&gt; in classical Greece, in that it suggests the inadequacy of sacrifice (but instead of sacrifice we can also say: &lt;em&gt;of any system&lt;/em&gt;) in supporting the whole of existence. Something always remains outside—indeed, &lt;em&gt;has to&lt;/em&gt; remain outside, because, if it were included in the system, it would disrupt it from within. On the other hand, the sacrifice or any system makes sense only if it extends to everything. A compromise therefore had to be established with what was left &lt;em&gt;outside&lt;/em&gt;, what was left &lt;em&gt;behind.&lt;/em&gt; So Rudra became Vāstavya, the ruler of the place and of the residue. This was the place the gods had left behind to get to the sky. But this place was the whole earth. So the whole earth was the residue.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14 HERMITS IN THE FOREST</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/14_HERMITS_IN_THE_FOREST/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/14_HERMITS_IN_THE_FOREST/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/00021.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;saṃnyāsin&lt;/em&gt;, the “renouncer,” in whose traits Louis Dumont had the farsightedness to recognize the archetypal &lt;em&gt;individual&lt;/em&gt; in the Western sense, is a figure who does not appear in the earliest stratum of the Vedic texts. The system, at that time, is compact and leaves no such space. Having once entered the process of cosmic interaction on birth, there is no way out. But on reaching the Upaniṣads, which take ritualist reasoning to an extreme, the &lt;em&gt;saṃnyāsin&lt;/em&gt; makes his appearance—the first defector, not because he rejects the complex system of interaction on which ritual is based, but because he seeks to absorb it within himself, in the inaccessible space of the mind. So the &lt;em&gt;agnihotra&lt;/em&gt; becomes the &lt;em&gt;prāṇāgnihotra&lt;/em&gt;, the first case of the complete internalization of an event, an invisible ceremony that takes place in an individual’s “breath,” &lt;em&gt;prāṇa.&lt;/em&gt; There is no longer any fire, there is no longer any milk to pour on it, the words of the texts are no longer to be heard. But all this still exists: in silence, in the activity of the mind. And so the &lt;em&gt;inner man&lt;/em&gt; makes his first appearance in history. He is the “individual-outside-the-world,” who has severed his links with society—and who will eventually prove to be enormously effective in his action &lt;em&gt;upon&lt;/em&gt; society. Dumont recognizes in him the earliest figure of the &lt;em&gt;intellectual&lt;/em&gt;, right up to his most recent awkward or lethal manifestations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 RITOLOGY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/15_RITOLOGY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/15_RITOLOGY/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Nothing actually left it and nothing entered from anywhere—there was indeed nothing else—and it [this all, &lt;em&gt;tónde tòn ólon&lt;/em&gt;] nurtured itself procuring its own destruction, whereas all that it suffered and did in itself and by itself happened by art [&lt;em&gt;ek téchnēs&lt;/em&gt;]. He who had created it felt indeed that it would have been better if it had been self-sufficient and not needy of anything else.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;—Plato, &lt;em&gt;Timaeus&lt;/em&gt;, 33 c–d&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 THE SACRIFICIAL VISION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/16_THE_SACRIFICIAL_VISION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/16_THE_SACRIFICIAL_VISION/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As for Numa himself, they say that he confided so much in the divine that one day, while he was celebrating a sacrifice, when told that enemies were approaching, he smiled and said: “And I am sacrificing.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;—Plutarch, &lt;em&gt;Numa&lt;/em&gt;, XV, 12&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/00024.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The sacrifice is a journey—linked to a destruction. A journey from a visible place to an invisible place, and back. The point of departure can be anywhere. And also the point of arrival, so long as it is inhabited by the divine. What is destroyed is the energy—an animate or inanimate being—that moves the journey. But it is always considered a living being—an animal or plant or even a liquid that is poured or an edible substance or an object (a ring or a precious stone or something that is perhaps precious only to the sacrificer).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17 AFTER THE FLOOD</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/17_AFTER_THE_FLOOD/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/17_AFTER_THE_FLOOD/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/00000.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Noah left the Ark, obeying Elohim’s command. And with him all other creatures, one by one, countless pairs of animals of every species. Long processions, especially of insects. As many left the Ark as had entered, since none of them had had intercourse during the voyage. Intercourse was forbidden in times of calamity. And during the long months of the voyage, even death was held in abeyance, even for those whose lives were fleeting. Noah didn’t know what Elohim intended to do now. His last manifestation had been a disaster that had wiped away the land. And now his voice was inviting him to set foot once again on land that was barely dry. But what if Noah had got it wrong, from the very start? What if he himself had incurred the wrath of Elohim, as had happened to the rest of his generation? So Noah decided to do something that had never been done before. He built an altar. No more than a block of stone. But no one had thought of doing such a thing until that moment. Then Noah made a choice “among every clean beast and of every clean fowl” and killed them, beside the altar. Then he laid out the various pieces of flesh on the altar so that they burned completely. This is what we must assume, since the chronicler says that he “made holocausts rise on the altar.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>18 TIKI</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/18_TIKI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/18_TIKI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/00002.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The idea that the web of correspondences constitutes a foundational element in a society was recognized and accepted in the most rigorous academic circles at the beginning of the twentieth century, with the essay by Émile Durkheim and Marcel Mauss, &lt;em&gt;“De quelques formes primitives de classification”&lt;/em&gt; (1903). But a confusion immediately began that reflected the two-headed nature of that paper, the result of a collaboration between a born analogist (Mauss) and a born determinist (Durkheim), related through family ties (Mauss was Durkheim’s nephew). That was the beginning of the tendency to affirm that &lt;em&gt;first&lt;/em&gt; came society and &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; correspondences. Which were therefore &lt;em&gt;determined&lt;/em&gt; by the social structure. The realm of analogy was certainly recognized, but was considered as a consequence of the main cause, which was society itself. And so it came about that the most formidable investigator and identifier of correspondences—Marcel Granet, who followed in the tracks of Mauss—could declare on several occasions, almost as if to close the matter, that there was no doubt that every form of thought was dependent on and subject to the structure of society.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>19 THE ACT OF KILLING</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/19_THE_ACT_OF_KILLING/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/19_THE_ACT_OF_KILLING/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If, in digging out the ground for the altar, there was already a fear of hurting the land and its creatures, the killing of animals must have seemed horrific.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;—Julius Schwab, &lt;em&gt;Das altindische Thieropfer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/00007.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The question to be answered: Why does the imbalance between divine and human have to be corrected with a killing?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;***&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Killing is present everywhere in the food chain that runs throughout the animal kingdom. In each link particular species have to kill others in order to survive. With man, the chain is not broken, indeed it expands. But man is the only being who reflects upon killing, who builds up the act into a sequence of prescribed gestures. As the Vedic ritualists say, man is the only one of the sacrificial victims who also celebrates sacrifices. This happens not because man occupies a final, culminating position in the food chain. Above him are alpha predators who have terrorized and hunted him for millennia—and can still get the better of him. The capacity to reflect upon killing is therefore an anomaly in the food chain, an unexpected divergence that occurs only in that link of the chain. Above it and below it, everything continues and proceeds as always, unchanged. The repertory of gestures is fixed in advance and takes no account of history, which is really a history of that anomaly: the transformation of a being who is basically vegetarian into an omnivore. It is a history of the various ways in which that anomaly appears in actions and gestures. If the food chain were observed from far away in space, human history would appear like a deformed link that assumes a multiplicity and variety of forms compared with the geometrically rigorous fixity of all the other links.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>20 THE FLIGHT OF THE BLACK ANTELOPE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/20_THE_FLIGHT_OF_THE_BLACK_ANTELOPE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/20_THE_FLIGHT_OF_THE_BLACK_ANTELOPE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The blackbuck is considered by many to be the most beautiful of all antelopes because of the male’s striking black and white pelage and his long spiral horns. The species once roamed in huge herds throughout the open woodlands and cultivated tracts of India, making it one of the most conspicuous and most hunted members of the country’s fauna. These large herds are now gone, and the animal clings to the last vestige of its former range in small scattered groups.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>21 KING SOMA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/21_KING_SOMA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/21_KING_SOMA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/00013.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Thousands of pages in the Brāhmaṇas, and all the hymns in the ninth cycle of the &lt;em&gt;Ṛgveda&lt;/em&gt;, are dedicated to &lt;em&gt;soma.&lt;/em&gt; Of the few &lt;em&gt;realia&lt;/em&gt; mentioned in the texts, &lt;em&gt;soma&lt;/em&gt; is the most present. We cannot be sure what it was, except for saying: it was a “juice,” &lt;em&gt;soma&lt;/em&gt;, which produced intoxication. Attempts at identifying it, from the mid-nineteenth century up to today, have all been rather awkward and unreliable. Nor do they explain why &lt;em&gt;soma&lt;/em&gt; was already spoken of in the Vedic era as something from the past, for which a substitute had to be found in the rites. But how can its intoxicating effect be substituted? This is one of the many sharp ironies that anyone venturing into the Vedic world encounters. Not surprisingly, it is ignored, intentionally or otherwise, by many scholars who continue to treat &lt;em&gt;soma&lt;/em&gt; like an algebraic symbol. It is more important—they argue—to make a precise reconstruction of the rites that celebrated &lt;em&gt;soma&lt;/em&gt;, and less important to know what exactly they celebrated. The moderns, as a rule, are proud when they make statements of this kind, since they are indifferent about substance in general and concerned only with getting the procedures clear. In this way they think they have risen high up the evolutionary ladder.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>22 ANTECEDENTS AND CONSEQUENTS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/22_ANTECEDENTS_AND_CONSEQUENTS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/22_ANTECEDENTS_AND_CONSEQUENTS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When you gods were in the waves, holding each other tightly, thick foams then rose up from you, as from dancers.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;—Ṛgveda&lt;/em&gt; 10.72.6&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/00016.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This book was started quite a number of years ago out of the rash idea of writing a commentary on the &lt;em&gt;Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt;, the &lt;em&gt;Brāhmaṇa of One Hundred Paths.&lt;/em&gt; The &lt;em&gt;Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; is a treatise on Vedic rituals that dates back to the eighth century B.C.E. and is made up of fourteen &lt;em&gt;kāṇḍas&lt;/em&gt;, “sections,” which add up to 2,366 pages in Julius Eggeling’s five-volume translation in the Sacred Books of the East series, published in Oxford between 1882 and 1900. This is at present the only complete translation (that of C. R. Swaminathan has so far reached only the eighth &lt;em&gt;kāṇḍa&lt;/em&gt;). The Brāhmaṇas—and the &lt;em&gt;Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; stands out among them—contain thoughts that cannot be ignored yet rarely find a place in the philosophy books. Thus, very often, they were treated with impatience, as being a sort of intrusion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
