<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Calasso - Ardor on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Calasso - Ardor on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 REMOTE BEINGS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/01_REMOTE_BEINGS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/01_REMOTE_BEINGS/</guid>
      <description>They were remote beings. Remote not only from modern man but from their ancient contemporaries. Distant not just as another culture, but as another celestial body. So distant that the point from which they are viewed becomes almost irrelevant. Nothing much changes whether that point is today or a hundred years ago. For those born in India, certain words, certain forms, certain objects may seem familiar, like an invincible atavism.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 YĀJÑAVALKYA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/02_yAjnavalkya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/02_yAjnavalkya/</guid>
      <description>Sometime before the days of the Buddha—no one can be quite sure when—there appeared the figure of Yājñavalkya. Sacrifice (yajña) is in his name, but the meaning of -valkya is not so clear. He had received his learning from the Sun, Āditya. To know, one must burn. Otherwise all knowledge is ineffective. One must therefore practice tapas. Tapas means “ardor”—it means the heat within the mind but also cosmic heat.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 ANIMALS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/03_ANIMALS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/03_ANIMALS/</guid>
      <description>Consumed by the arrogance of knowledge, the young Bhṛgu, son of the supreme god Varuṇa, was sent off by his father into the world (into this world, according to the Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa, into the other world according to the version in the Jaiminīya Brāhmaṇa) to see what knowledge alone could not reveal, to find out how the world itself is made. Without this, all knowledge is pointless.
In the east, Bhṛgu came across men who were slaughtering other men.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 THE PROGENITOR</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/04_THE_PROGENITOR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/04_THE_PROGENITOR/</guid>
      <description>The god at the origin of everything didn’t have a name but a title: Prajāpati, Lord of the Creatures. He discovered this when one of his sons, Indra, told him: “I want to be what you are.” Prajāpati asked him: “But who (ka) am I?” And Indra answered: “‘Exactly what you just said.’ So Prajāpati became Ka.”
Indra wanted his father’s “greatness” or, according to others, his “splendor.” And Prajāpati had no difficulty in divesting himself of it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 THEY WHO SAW THE HYMNS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/05_THEY_WHO_SAW_THE_HYMNS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/05_THEY_WHO_SAW_THE_HYMNS/</guid>
      <description>The hymns of the Ṛgveda were said to have been seen by the ṛṣis. The ṛṣis may therefore be described as “seers.” They saw the hymns in the same way as we see a tree or a river. They were the most disconcerting, least easily explainable beings in the Vedic cosmos. Chief among them were the Saptarṣis, the Seven who lived in the stars of the Great Bear, who have some affinity with the Seven Greek Sages, with the Islamic abdāls, and with the Seven Akkadian Apkallus of the Apsu.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 THE ADVENTURES OF MIND AND SPEECH</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/06_THE_ADVENTURES_OF_MIND_AND_SPEECH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/06_THE_ADVENTURES_OF_MIND_AND_SPEECH/</guid>
      <description>Manas, “mind” (later mens in Latin), “thought.” But above all the pure fact of being conscious, awake. For the Vedic people, everything came from consciousness, in the sense of pure awareness devoid of any other attribute. They invoked it delicately, as “the divine one that comes forward from afar when we awake and falls back when we slumber.” Likewise “she through whom the seers, able creators, operate in the sacrifice and in the rites.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>07 *ĀTMAN*</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/07_Atman/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/07_Atman/</guid>
      <description>Brahman or the knowledge of it are no different among very powerful beings such as Vāmadeva or in the much less powerful men of today. But one may suspect that in men of today the fruit of the knowledge of brahman is uncertain.
—Śaṅkara, Bṛhadāraṇyakopaniṣadbhāṣya, 1.4.10
From the Ṛgveda to the Bhagavad Gītā a way of reasoning is developed that never acknowledges a single subject, but rather presupposes a dual subject.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>08 PERFECT WAKEFULNESS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/08_PERFECT_WAKEFULNESS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/08_PERFECT_WAKEFULNESS/</guid>
      <description>The wakefulness the Upaniṣads speak of (and the Ṛgveda before them) is a state opposed, not to sleep, but to another kind of wakefulness—inattentive, inert, automatic. Awakening means rousing oneself from that kind of wakefulness, as from a vapid dream. Philosophers have not regarded this swerve within the mind as worthy of consideration, but it became the focus of thought in one place and in one period: in India, in the time between the Veda and the Buddha—and then reverberated unremittingly through all the centuries thereafter.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>09 THE BRĀHMAṆAS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/09_THE_brAhmaNas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/09_THE_brAhmaNas/</guid>
      <description>He who knew the taut thread on which all creatures are woven, he who knew the thread of the thread, would know the great Exegesis.
—Atharvaveda 10.8.37 (trans. L. Renou, 1938)
He who knows the taut thread on which these creatures are woven, he who knows the thread of the thread, knows the great essence of brahman.
—Atharvaveda 10.8.37 (trans. L. Renou, 1956)
The Brāhmaṇas are the part of the Veda most neglected by scholars and most ignored by readers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 THE LINE OF THE FIRES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/10_THE_LINE_OF_THE_FIRES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/10_THE_LINE_OF_THE_FIRES/</guid>
      <description>Man’s initial state is formless, opaque, composite, and also “impure.” Man is a being who “speaks untruth.” He could carry on living like this, though leaving no significant trace. Otherwise he must compose a series of connected gestures that make an “action,” karman. The quintessential action, the one that presupposes and assures that gestures have a meaning, is the sacrificial work.
But what is the origin of this work whose first peculiarity is that of being the model for all other work?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>11 VEDIC EROTICA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/11_VEDIC_EROTICA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/11_VEDIC_EROTICA/</guid>
      <description>The altar is a woman with perfect proportions: “With broad hips, shoulders a little less broad, and narrow at the waist.” Like a woman, it must not be naked. It is sprinkled with fine gravel or sand, so as to cover its body with a light gleaming film (“gravel is certainly an adornment, since gravel is fairly luminous”). Then with twigs and grass. The woman—the altar—makes herself beautiful, is helped to look beautiful, ready for the arrival of the gods.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>12 GODS WHO OFFER LIBATIONS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/12_GODS_WHO_OFFER_LIBATIONS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/12_GODS_WHO_OFFER_LIBATIONS/</guid>
      <description>There is one gesture that inextricably unites the whole Indo-European world. It is the gesture of the libation. The pouring of a liquid into a fire that flares up, destroying a valuable or an ordinary substance in the flame. Libation is found back in the Minoan period, on the Hagia Triada sarcophagus. Homer’s characters often carry it out as a necessary preliminary to their exploits. Sacrifices performed with no libation are extremely rare.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>13 RESIDUE AND SURPLUS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/13_RESIDUE_AND_SURPLUS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/13_RESIDUE_AND_SURPLUS/</guid>
      <description>In that place therefore the blessed god, all-present, sleeping on the ocean, cloaked his night with thick darkness. But a surplus of luminous quality awakened him and he saw the empty world.
—Mahābhārata, 3.272.40–41ab
The whole of Indian tradition, in its various branches, is influenced by a doctrine of residue, which can be embodied in three words, corresponding to three successive stages: vāstu, ucchiṣṭa, and śeṣa. It has a key role as a doctrine, similar to that of ousía in classical Greece, in that it suggests the inadequacy of sacrifice (but instead of sacrifice we can also say: of any system) in supporting the whole of existence.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>14 HERMITS IN THE FOREST</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/14_HERMITS_IN_THE_FOREST/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/14_HERMITS_IN_THE_FOREST/</guid>
      <description>The saṃnyāsin, the “renouncer,” in whose traits Louis Dumont had the farsightedness to recognize the archetypal individual in the Western sense, is a figure who does not appear in the earliest stratum of the Vedic texts. The system, at that time, is compact and leaves no such space. Having once entered the process of cosmic interaction on birth, there is no way out. But on reaching the Upaniṣads, which take ritualist reasoning to an extreme, the saṃnyāsin makes his appearance—the first defector, not because he rejects the complex system of interaction on which ritual is based, but because he seeks to absorb it within himself, in the inaccessible space of the mind.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>15 RITOLOGY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/15_RITOLOGY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/15_RITOLOGY/</guid>
      <description>Nothing actually left it and nothing entered from anywhere—there was indeed nothing else—and it [this all, tónde tòn ólon] nurtured itself procuring its own destruction, whereas all that it suffered and did in itself and by itself happened by art [ek téchnēs]. He who had created it felt indeed that it would have been better if it had been self-sufficient and not needy of anything else.
—Plato, Timaeus, 33 c–d</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>16 THE SACRIFICIAL VISION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/16_THE_SACRIFICIAL_VISION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/16_THE_SACRIFICIAL_VISION/</guid>
      <description>As for Numa himself, they say that he confided so much in the divine that one day, while he was celebrating a sacrifice, when told that enemies were approaching, he smiled and said: “And I am sacrificing.”
—Plutarch, Numa, XV, 12
The sacrifice is a journey—linked to a destruction. A journey from a visible place to an invisible place, and back. The point of departure can be anywhere. And also the point of arrival, so long as it is inhabited by the divine.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>17 AFTER THE FLOOD</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/17_AFTER_THE_FLOOD/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/17_AFTER_THE_FLOOD/</guid>
      <description>Noah left the Ark, obeying Elohim’s command. And with him all other creatures, one by one, countless pairs of animals of every species. Long processions, especially of insects. As many left the Ark as had entered, since none of them had had intercourse during the voyage. Intercourse was forbidden in times of calamity. And during the long months of the voyage, even death was held in abeyance, even for those whose lives were fleeting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>18 TIKI</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/18_TIKI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/18_TIKI/</guid>
      <description>The idea that the web of correspondences constitutes a foundational element in a society was recognized and accepted in the most rigorous academic circles at the beginning of the twentieth century, with the essay by Émile Durkheim and Marcel Mauss, “De quelques formes primitives de classification” (1903). But a confusion immediately began that reflected the two-headed nature of that paper, the result of a collaboration between a born analogist (Mauss) and a born determinist (Durkheim), related through family ties (Mauss was Durkheim’s nephew).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>19 THE ACT OF KILLING</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/19_THE_ACT_OF_KILLING/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/19_THE_ACT_OF_KILLING/</guid>
      <description>If, in digging out the ground for the altar, there was already a fear of hurting the land and its creatures, the killing of animals must have seemed horrific.
—Julius Schwab, Das altindische Thieropfer
The question to be answered: Why does the imbalance between divine and human have to be corrected with a killing?
***
Killing is present everywhere in the food chain that runs throughout the animal kingdom. In each link particular species have to kill others in order to survive.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>20 THE FLIGHT OF THE BLACK ANTELOPE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/20_THE_FLIGHT_OF_THE_BLACK_ANTELOPE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/20_THE_FLIGHT_OF_THE_BLACK_ANTELOPE/</guid>
      <description>The blackbuck is considered by many to be the most beautiful of all antelopes because of the male’s striking black and white pelage and his long spiral horns. The species once roamed in huge herds throughout the open woodlands and cultivated tracts of India, making it one of the most conspicuous and most hunted members of the country’s fauna. These large herds are now gone, and the animal clings to the last vestige of its former range in small scattered groups.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>21 KING SOMA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/21_KING_SOMA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/21_KING_SOMA/</guid>
      <description>Thousands of pages in the Brāhmaṇas, and all the hymns in the ninth cycle of the Ṛgveda, are dedicated to soma. Of the few realia mentioned in the texts, soma is the most present. We cannot be sure what it was, except for saying: it was a “juice,” soma, which produced intoxication. Attempts at identifying it, from the mid-nineteenth century up to today, have all been rather awkward and unreliable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>22 ANTECEDENTS AND CONSEQUENTS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/22_ANTECEDENTS_AND_CONSEQUENTS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/calasso_ardor/22_ANTECEDENTS_AND_CONSEQUENTS/</guid>
      <description>When you gods were in the waves, holding each other tightly, thick foams then rose up from you, as from dancers.
—Ṛgveda 10.72.6
This book was started quite a number of years ago out of the rash idea of writing a commentary on the Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa, the Brāhmaṇa of One Hundred Paths. The Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa is a treatise on Vedic rituals that dates back to the eighth century B.C.E. and is made up of fourteen kāṇḍas, “sections,” which add up to 2,366 pages in Julius Eggeling’s five-volume translation in the Sacred Books of the East series, published in Oxford between 1882 and 1900.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
