<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;01 Geography of the Vedas and Their Language on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/1_ORIGINS_AND_BACKGROUNDS/01_Geography_of_the_Vedas_and_Their_Language/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;01 Geography of the Vedas and Their Language on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/1_ORIGINS_AND_BACKGROUNDS/01_Geography_of_the_Vedas_and_Their_Language/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 RIGVEDA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/1_ORIGINS_AND_BACKGROUNDS/01_Geography_of_the_Vedas_and_Their_Language/01_RIGVEDA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/1_ORIGINS_AND_BACKGROUNDS/01_Geography_of_the_Vedas_and_Their_Language/01_RIGVEDA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Rigveda is the earliest because its language is the most archaic and because the other three Vedas presuppose, depend on, quote or refer to it. It consists of verse (&lt;em&gt;rig-&lt;/em&gt;). Many of its invocations ask gods for long life, riches, sons, cattle and victory in battle. Other compositions tell stories or refer to myths, familiar to their audience but not known to us. They discuss sex with the same attention to detail as rites. They contain speculations about the universe and much else.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 SĀMAVEDA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/1_ORIGINS_AND_BACKGROUNDS/01_Geography_of_the_Vedas_and_Their_Language/02_sAmaveda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/1_ORIGINS_AND_BACKGROUNDS/01_Geography_of_the_Vedas_and_Their_Language/02_sAmaveda/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Sāmaveda is the Rigveda set to music. Almost all its verses are taken from the Rigveda but its melodies (&lt;em&gt;sāman&lt;/em&gt;) are older. Two of them are mentioned in the Rigveda, one called Rathantara ‘Excellent Chariot’. Others have unfamiliar names.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Sāmaveda is larger than the Rigveda because it lists all the modifications the Rigvedic verses undergo when they are chanted or used in ritual.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 YAJURVEDA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/1_ORIGINS_AND_BACKGROUNDS/01_Geography_of_the_Vedas_and_Their_Language/03_YAJURVEDA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/1_ORIGINS_AND_BACKGROUNDS/01_Geography_of_the_Vedas_and_Their_Language/03_YAJURVEDA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Yajurveda is the Veda of ritual. Its composers are priests. The term &lt;em&gt;yajus&lt;/em&gt; refers to a ritual formula. The bulk of the Yajurveda comes again from the Rigveda. These verses are referred to as &lt;em&gt;mantra&lt;/em&gt;. They are accompanied by prose sections which interpret the mantras in terms of ritual, often in a muddled fashion. These sections are called &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt;, a term which also refers to their composers, the hermeneuticians of the day. Baudhāyana, already mentioned, sorted them out by concentrating on &lt;em&gt;ritual form&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 ATHARVAVEDA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/1_ORIGINS_AND_BACKGROUNDS/01_Geography_of_the_Vedas_and_Their_Language/04_ATHARVAVEDA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/1_ORIGINS_AND_BACKGROUNDS/01_Geography_of_the_Vedas_and_Their_Language/04_ATHARVAVEDA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Atharvaveda is in some respects similar to the Rigveda. About one-seventh of its verses are the same or more or less the same. The collection reflects a different social background. Instead of poets, singers or priests, we meet with physicians and magicians who use drugs and spells to cure diseases, mental as well as physical. The Atharvaveda exists in two recensions, each containing almost 6,000 verses.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is clear from the earliest compositions that they were the prized possessions of small tribal groups, families or clans, hunter-gatherers and pastoralists who avoided the forests and followed the course of rivers before they settled down. The geography of the Vedas may be largely reconstructed from the names of these rivers. They are shown on the map in Figure 1 (see end of book) which is reproduced from Michael Witzel’s 1989 study on Vedic dialects. The reader will recognize most rivers: &lt;em&gt;Sindhu&lt;/em&gt; is, of course, the Indus after which India has been named. &lt;em&gt;Kubhā&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Suvāstu&lt;/em&gt; are the Kabul and Swat Rivers, &lt;em&gt;Vitastā&lt;/em&gt; the Jhelum, &lt;em&gt;Asikn&lt;/em&gt;ī the Chenab, &lt;em&gt;Paru&lt;/em&gt;ṣṇī the Ravi, Ś&lt;em&gt;utudr&lt;/em&gt;ī the Sutlej and others should speak for themselves as does &lt;em&gt;Himavant&lt;/em&gt;, the Himalayan range.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
