<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;22 MAGIC IN THE RITUAL on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;22 MAGIC IN THE RITUAL on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 The Relations of Magic to Religion</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/1_The_Relations_of_Magic_to_Religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/1_The_Relations_of_Magic_to_Religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THE theory that all religion is later than magic has already been discussed, and its fundamental weakness pointed out,1 and it is therefore possible to consider the question of the relation of these two factors apart from any preconceived doctrine of the priority of magic. The position in the literature of Vedic India is a simple one with very few exceptions the Rigveda is a book in which magic is not dealt with a few late hymns are indeed found there, but these stand out as exceptions in a religious milieu. (The Atharvaveda is a book of magic, mingled with some theosophy: that it is priestly magic, and not popular magic uninfluenced by the priests is clear: the priests have constantly altered, and changed much of what they dealt with, but the book itself is conclusive proof that the priests of that time were keenly concerned with magic rites. The position is further made clear by the Brahmaṇas, which show beyond possibility of doubt that the whole of the sacrifice was penetrated by conceptions of magic. Scarcely any rite but can be so adapted as to produce magic ends the rites are often varied in detail for this very purpose, the mode in which the post is covered with the cord will determine the amount of rain which will fall, the priest can bring to nothing the kingdom if he varies by manipulations the offering; he is constantly told how to alter the words, when he dislikes the sacrificer, or when he seeks to obtain for him such special blessings as a male child. }&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2 The Nature of Vedic Magic</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/2_The_Nature_of_Vedic_Magic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/2_The_Nature_of_Vedic_Magic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the sphere of Vedic magic we have to do both with personal and with impersonal substances. The conception of all sorts of demons as threatening man is one which is supplemented by the more impersonal view of substances or potencies, which dwell in things, and which are often, therefore, of value in magic rites. It is possible that the earlier view is that which conceives these potencies either animatistically as actually alive, or animistically as spirits, but in the Vedic literature the two views, personal and impersonal, are both clearly found, and, like everything in the Veda, they are never clearly kept apart. Such powers are the power of error in the sacrifice which clings to the sacrificial post, and therefore may pass to the sacrificers, if care is not taken to render it harmless, the nature in woman, which causes her to slay her husband or to bear no children to him, and to bring death and disease among his cattle.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 The Removal of Hostile Influences</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/3_The_Removal_of_Hostile_Influences/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/3_The_Removal_of_Hostile_Influences/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a modified degree the principle is adopted in Vedic ritual that hostile powers should be propitiated. Thus the Rakṣases are given the portions that fall away from the grain, when it is pounded for the offerings: the blood, the entrails, the excrement of the animal victim, are made over to them or the snakes. Diseases treated as demons are propitiated and shown reverence in the hope, which is expressed, that they will depart, being satisfied with what is done for them. The disease Takman is entreated to depart, and addressed as a god, just as among the Esths down to modern times the same procedure of paying homage was adopted to make a disease depart. What is more interesting is that both methods might be tried in close conjunction: the jackal might be addressed with formulae of reverence at the one time, and at the same time a fire brand be thrown at it.3 The ants receive an offering, but, if that fails, a poisonous mixture is made for them, and the aid of the gods in their utter extirpation is invoked. Snakes are simultaneously treated with reverence, and their extinction invoked: in the snake offering itself, while the snakes are fed, the sacrificer draws round the house a line of water to keep them away from it. But as a rule the attitude of the Vedic Indian to&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4 The Attraction of Beneficial Substances and Powers</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/4_The_Attraction_of_Beneficial_Substances_and_Powe/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/4_The_Attraction_of_Beneficial_Substances_and_Powe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The sacrificer must avail himself of the same means to attack his enemies as they use to attack him: if the enemy assail, the skilled priest can send against them the demon Apvā which seems to be the diarrhoea caused by terror, and to symbolize in emphatic fashion the fear produced by panic in battle: this performance is already recorded in the Rigveda.&amp;rsquo; So also it is perfectly in keeping with the ideas of magic that terror and fear would be conveyed to the enemy by the process of sending a white-footed one, presumably a sheep, against the opposing host. In such a case Apvā is indeed a dreadful thing, but it is in the control of the priest and therefore useful to him. In other cases he has more direct control: he can use one substance for washing himself, another he can drink or cat, another use as an amulet; with yet another he can rub or anoint himself. The avoidance of the touch of anything dangerous is one side of a practice, of which the other is the touching of things which are bencficial. The touching of the victim has two sides : it may convey the death to which the victim is being led, but it may also convey and this is the view which Brahman logic 1o finally adopts-the power and strength of the divine essence. Hence we have an enormous number of rites, the standing on a tiger-skin to obtain royal power, the use of an antelope-skin, the placing of the wife on a bull&amp;rsquo;s hide, the placing of her and of the student upon a stone to attain firmness, the depositing at the fire-piling and other offerings on the place of the fire altar of a piece of earth&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 Mimetic Magic</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/5_Mimetic_Magic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/5_Mimetic_Magic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In one special class of cases the effect which it is desired by magic means to produce in nature is brought about by the simple plan of representing in sensible form, within the means available to man, the operations which it is desired should take place. Thus when an enemy is to be defeated it is useful to break in two a piece of grass which is thrown towards the opposing host the breaking of the grass symbolizes the breaking in two of the armed foemen. Or the rite can be made more effective in quite a simple way: as a daughter-in-law by an old taboo is expected to shrink away from her father-in-law, so by taking the hostile enemy as the daughter-in-law, and by&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>6 Divination and Ordeal</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/6_Divination_and_Ordeal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/6_Divination_and_Ordeal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The principle of divination is in large measure directly due to the doctrine of mimetic magic: if the use of a representation of things can produce them, it is also legitimate, if less easy, to deduce the future of events from the behaviour of things, which are supposed to be an imitation of the events. This, however, is no doubt not the whole ground of the belief in the power to read the future, and, moreover, the fact that the future was uncertain must have induced many people to resort to the gods for aid in unravelling it. In these cases the performances are indeed much the same as in an ordinary species of divination, but the belief is different: it is the view that the future is revealed by the god, through the means employed: magic here is supplemented as often by religious conceptions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>7 The Magic Spell</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/7_The_Magic_Spell/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/7_The_Magic_Spell/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The power of the word is very marked in all systems of magic and naturally not least in India. The magic spell is sometimes in prose, in the style of the formulae used by the Adhvaryus at the sacrifice, more often in verse, sometimes newly made for the purpose, sometimes, and indeed very often, chosen without any appropriateness from the vast body of existing sacred literature. Of this latter tendency two examples may be given the number available is legion. The finest hymn to Varuna in the Vedic literature is found in the Atharvaveda where it has been preserved in a charm.5 The great hymn of the Rigveda, which celebrates the god Prajapati in the form of questions, has the second verse used in a spell for preventing the miscarriage of a cow, doubtless for no better reason than that the idiotic system on which names of authors were assigned to every hymn of the collection resulted in postulating an author Hiranyagarbha, he of the golden womb&amp;rsquo;, really an epithet of the supreme god, and the fact that the deity was Prajapati.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>8 The Magic Sacrifice</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/8_The_Magic_Sacrifice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/8_The_Magic_Sacrifice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In many cases the sacrifice itself is degraded to merc magic: this is a precise parallel to the degradation of the formulae to spells which we have already seen, and of which the mystic Hotṛ formulae, originally of a superior type of thought, but later degraded to common magic purposes, are the best example. The actual sacrifice itself may be adapted to magical ends: thus to secure the opposite of the natural results the sorcerer performs it with the arrangement reversed as far as may be the movements are not from south to north and from left to right, but from north to south, the region of the dead, and from right to left. Or again the offering verse in a sacrifice for Indra may be addressed to the Maruts, and vice versa in an offering to the Maruts. The KauŚika Sūtra has full descriptions of black magic, an idea which has never been without votaries and which in the Middle Ages attained great fame.2 More directly the sacrifice becomes not merely in the theosophy of the Brahmans the great power of the universe: more prosaically it becomes the means by which the sorcerers who practise magic against one can be made to show themselves, by which rival wives can be overcome, by which the monarch in exile can regain his throne. The sacrifice can be adapted to these ends by any manipulations of its component parts or by the precise mode in which the ritual acts are performed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>9 Yoga Practices</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/9_Yoga_Practices/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/9_Yoga_Practices/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;7&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The ritual, as has been seen, both in the case of magic and of the sacrifice, is full of elements which appear systematized in the later Yoga philosophy and practice. But it would be a mistake to exaggerate the degree of correspondence, and in point of fact much that is later characteristic and essential is lacking in the earlier Vedic literature. In special hardly any trace can be found of the importance later attaching to elaborate regulation of the breath, despite the fact that the division of the breaths or vital airs as five is early. The suggestion that the term Śuṣma is a word with ecstatic implications is wholly implausible. The inducing of perspiration as a part of the Dikṣā and as a means of exciting ecstasy is clear, but it does not appear as a distinct or important rite as with the Scythians of Herodotos or the aborigines of North America or Australia. Nor do we find any clear reference to the various sitting postures familiar to the later Yoga, for it is absurd to believe that the sense altar&amp;rsquo;, if it ever really belongs to the obscure term Dhiṣaṇā, owes its origin to the fact that by his posture at the place of sacrifice the priest beholds the might (dhiṣaṇa) of the gods. The mysterious Uttanapad of the Rigveda as a cosmic power cannot with any plausibility be deemed to yield a proof of the practice of assuming the position of an embryo in the womb as a means of attaining mystic rebirth. That silence and solitude were conducive to ecstasy is, curiously enough, little referred to, and the dirt of both person and garments of the later Yogin is recognized only in a few hints. There is more evidence of fasting, and the hymn of Lopamudra and Agastya in the Rigveda 10 1 AV. xi. 1; xii. 8.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
