<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;22 MAGIC IN THE RITUAL on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;22 MAGIC IN THE RITUAL on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 The Relations of Magic to Religion</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/1_The_Relations_of_Magic_to_Religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/1_The_Relations_of_Magic_to_Religion/</guid>
      <description>THE theory that all religion is later than magic has already been discussed, and its fundamental weakness pointed out,1 and it is therefore possible to consider the question of the relation of these two factors apart from any preconceived doctrine of the priority of magic. The position in the literature of Vedic India is a simple one with very few exceptions the Rigveda is a book in which magic is not dealt with a few late hymns are indeed found there, but these stand out as exceptions in a religious milieu.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2 The Nature of Vedic Magic</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/2_The_Nature_of_Vedic_Magic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/2_The_Nature_of_Vedic_Magic/</guid>
      <description>In the sphere of Vedic magic we have to do both with personal and with impersonal substances. The conception of all sorts of demons as threatening man is one which is supplemented by the more impersonal view of substances or potencies, which dwell in things, and which are often, therefore, of value in magic rites. It is possible that the earlier view is that which conceives these potencies either animatistically as actually alive, or animistically as spirits, but in the Vedic literature the two views, personal and impersonal, are both clearly found, and, like everything in the Veda, they are never clearly kept apart.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 The Removal of Hostile Influences</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/3_The_Removal_of_Hostile_Influences/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/3_The_Removal_of_Hostile_Influences/</guid>
      <description>In a modified degree the principle is adopted in Vedic ritual that hostile powers should be propitiated. Thus the Rakṣases are given the portions that fall away from the grain, when it is pounded for the offerings: the blood, the entrails, the excrement of the animal victim, are made over to them or the snakes. Diseases treated as demons are propitiated and shown reverence in the hope, which is expressed, that they will depart, being satisfied with what is done for them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4 The Attraction of Beneficial Substances and Powers</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/4_The_Attraction_of_Beneficial_Substances_and_Powe/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/4_The_Attraction_of_Beneficial_Substances_and_Powe/</guid>
      <description>The sacrificer must avail himself of the same means to attack his enemies as they use to attack him: if the enemy assail, the skilled priest can send against them the demon Apvā which seems to be the diarrhoea caused by terror, and to symbolize in emphatic fashion the fear produced by panic in battle: this performance is already recorded in the Rigveda.&amp;rsquo; So also it is perfectly in keeping with the ideas of magic that terror and fear would be conveyed to the enemy by the process of sending a white-footed one, presumably a sheep, against the opposing host.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5 Mimetic Magic</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/5_Mimetic_Magic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/5_Mimetic_Magic/</guid>
      <description>In one special class of cases the effect which it is desired by magic means to produce in nature is brought about by the simple plan of representing in sensible form, within the means available to man, the operations which it is desired should take place. Thus when an enemy is to be defeated it is useful to break in two a piece of grass which is thrown towards the opposing host the breaking of the grass symbolizes the breaking in two of the armed foemen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>6 Divination and Ordeal</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/6_Divination_and_Ordeal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/6_Divination_and_Ordeal/</guid>
      <description>The principle of divination is in large measure directly due to the doctrine of mimetic magic: if the use of a representation of things can produce them, it is also legitimate, if less easy, to deduce the future of events from the behaviour of things, which are supposed to be an imitation of the events. This, however, is no doubt not the whole ground of the belief in the power to read the future, and, moreover, the fact that the future was uncertain must have induced many people to resort to the gods for aid in unravelling it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>7 The Magic Spell</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/7_The_Magic_Spell/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/7_The_Magic_Spell/</guid>
      <description>The power of the word is very marked in all systems of magic and naturally not least in India. The magic spell is sometimes in prose, in the style of the formulae used by the Adhvaryus at the sacrifice, more often in verse, sometimes newly made for the purpose, sometimes, and indeed very often, chosen without any appropriateness from the vast body of existing sacred literature. Of this latter tendency two examples may be given the number available is legion.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>8 The Magic Sacrifice</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/8_The_Magic_Sacrifice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/8_The_Magic_Sacrifice/</guid>
      <description>In many cases the sacrifice itself is degraded to merc magic: this is a precise parallel to the degradation of the formulae to spells which we have already seen, and of which the mystic Hotṛ formulae, originally of a superior type of thought, but later degraded to common magic purposes, are the best example. The actual sacrifice itself may be adapted to magical ends: thus to secure the opposite of the natural results the sorcerer performs it with the arrangement reversed as far as may be the movements are not from south to north and from left to right, but from north to south, the region of the dead, and from right to left.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>9 Yoga Practices</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/9_Yoga_Practices/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/3_VEDIC_RITUAL/22_MAGIC_IN_THE_RITUAL/9_Yoga_Practices/</guid>
      <description>7
The ritual, as has been seen, both in the case of magic and of the sacrifice, is full of elements which appear systematized in the later Yoga philosophy and practice. But it would be a mistake to exaggerate the degree of correspondence, and in point of fact much that is later characteristic and essential is lacking in the earlier Vedic literature. In special hardly any trace can be found of the importance later attaching to elaborate regulation of the breath, despite the fact that the division of the breaths or vital airs as five is early.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
