<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;2 THE GODS AND DEMONS OF THE VEDA on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;2 THE GODS AND DEMONS OF THE VEDA on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>07 THE INTERRELATION OF THE GODS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/07_THE_INTERRELATION_OF_THE_GODS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/07_THE_INTERRELATION_OF_THE_GODS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THE Rigveda recognizes the number of the gods as 38, a figure given also in the Iranian tradition, and these it further divides into three groups of 11, connected with the heaven, the earth, and the waters of the air: more often the connexion of the gods with these three regions is mentioned without any precise statement of number. Of this 38 no explanation in detail can be gathered from the Rigveda: it is certain that it is not exhaustive, for other gods are mentioned in addition to the 38. The absence of any established tradition is shown by the Brahmaṇas which recognize the 33 gods, and agree in making them out to include 8 Vasus, 11 Rudras, and 12 Adityas, but differ as to the remaining two: the Śatapatha1 gives either Dyaus and Pṛthivi, with a thirty-fourth in Prajapati, or Indra and Prajapati, while the Aitareya 2 adds Prajāpati and the Vaṣat call, a technical introduction from the sacrifice which is manifestly not primitive. It is not unnatural, therefore, that Hopkins should have sought to find the origin of the number in an older 10, but there is, as we have seen, no tolerable evidence in tradition of an older set of ten gods either in India or in any other Indo-European religion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 THE GODS AND THEIR WORSHIPPERS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/16_THE_GODS_AND_THEIR_WORSHIPPERS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/2_THE_GODS_AND_DEMONS_OF_THE_VEDA/16_THE_GODS_AND_THEIR_WORSHIPPERS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As men fashion their concepts of their gods in accordance with their own attitude towards life, it is natural to find in the Rigveda the expression of the real religious spirit of the day. It must, however, be borne in mind in any estimate of that spirit that the sources are all priestly, and that, therefore, they express the views not so much of the ordinary man even of the higher ranks, and social distinctions certainly existed then, but of the priest himself, and of a priesthood which had already advated a long way in the direction of the elaboration and definition of religion. This fact, however, while it explains much that is to be found in the thought of the Rigveda, and warns us against imputing that thought to a simple people living in immediate contact with nature and the birth of the gods, does not alter the impression which is unquestionably made by the Rigveda as a whole, and which is of a definite and intelligible character.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
