<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;vedic-mythology - macdonnell on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;vedic-mythology - macdonnell on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 INTRODUCTION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/1_INTRODUCTION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/1_INTRODUCTION/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;i. Religion and mythology. Religion in its widest sense includes on the one hand the conception which men entertain of the divine or supernatural powers and, on the other, that sense of the dependence of human welfare on those powers which finds its expression in various forms of wor ship. Mythology is connected with the former side of religion as furnishing the whole body of myths or stories which are told about gods and heroes and which describe their character and origin, their actions and surroundings. Such myths have their source in the attempt of the human mind, in a primitive and unscientific age, to explain the various forces and phenomena of nature with which man is confronted. They represent in fact the conjectural science of a primitive mental condition. For statements which to the highly civilised mind would be merely metaphorical, amount in that early stage to explanations of the phenomena observed. The intellectual difficulties raised by the course of the heavenly bodies, by the incidents of the thunderstorm, by reflexions on the origin and constitution of the outer world, here receive their answers in the form of stories. The basis of these myths is the primitive attitude of mind which regards all nature as an aggregate of animated entities. A myth actually arises when the imagination interprets a natural event as the action of a personified being resembling the human agent. Thus the observation that the moon follows the sun without overtaking it, would have been transformed into a myth by describing the former as a maiden following a man by whom she is rejected. Such an original myth enters on the further stage of poetical embellishment, as soon as it becomes the property of people endowed with creative imagination. Various traits are now added according to the individual fancy of the narrator, as the story passes from mouth to mouth. The natural phenomenon begins to fade out of the picture as its place is taken by a detailed representation of human passions. When the natural basis of the tale is forgotten, new touches totally unconnected with its original significance may be added or even transferred from other myths. When met with at a late stage of its development, a myth may be so far overgrown with secondary accretions unconnected with its original form, that its analysis may be extremely difficult or even impossible. Thus it would be hard indeed to discover the primary naturalistic elements in the characters or actions of the Hellenic gods, if we knew only the highly anthropomorphic deities in the plays of Euripides.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2: VEDIC CONCEPTIONS OF THE WORLD AND ITS ORIGIN</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/2_VEDIC_CONCEPTIONS_OF_THE_WORLD_AND_ITS_ORIGIN/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/2_VEDIC_CONCEPTIONS_OF_THE_WORLD_AND_ITS_ORIGIN/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;7&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Cosmology. - - The Universe, the stage on which the actions ofthe gods are enacted, is___regarded by the Vedic poets as divided into thethree domains 1 of earth, air or atmosphere, and heaven 2. The sky whenregarded as the whole space above the earth, forms with the latter the entireuniverse consisting of the upper and the nether world. The vault (ndkd) ofthe sky is regarded as the limit dividing the visible upper world from the&amp;amp;gt;. COMPARATIVE MYTHOLOGY. 7. COSMOLOGY.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;third or invisible world of heaven, which is the abode of light and the dwelling place of the gods. Heaven, air, and earth form the favourite triad of the RV., constantly spoken of explicitly or implicitly (8, io 6. go6 &amp;amp;c.). The s&amp;amp;ter S^ phenomena which appear, to take place on the vault of the sky, are referred to heaven, while those of lightning, rain, and wind belong to the atmosphere. But when heaven designates the whole space above the earth both classes of phenomena are spoken of as taking place there. In a passage of the AV.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 THE VEDIC GODS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/3_THE_VEDIC_GODS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/3_THE_VEDIC_GODS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;10&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;General character and classification. Indefiniteness of out line and lack of individuality characterize the Vedic conception of the gods. This is mainly due to the fact that they are nearer to the physical pheno mena which they represent, than the gods of any other Indo-European people. Thus the ancient Vedic interpreter Yaska 1 (Nir. 7, 4) speaking of the nature of the gods, remarks that what is seen of them is not anthropomorphic at all, as in the case of the Sun, the Earth, and others. The natural bases of the Vedic gods have, to begin with, but few specific characteristics, while they share some of the attributes of other phenomena belonging to the same domain. Thus Dawn, Sun, Fire have the common features of being luminous, dispelling darkness, appearing in the morning. The absence of distinctiveness must be still greater when several deities have sprung from different aspects of one and the same phenomenon. Hence the character of each Vedic god is made up of only a few essential traits combined with a number of other features common to all the gods, such as brilliance, power, beneficence, and wisdom. Certain great cosmical functions are predicated of nearly every leading deity individually. The action of supporting or establishing heaven and earth is so generally attributed to them, that in the AV. (19, 32) it is even ascribed to a magical bunch of darbha grass. Nearly a dozen gods are described as having created the two worlds, and rather more are said to have produced the sun, to have placed it in the sky, or to have prepared a path for it. Four or five are also spoken of as having spread out the earth, the sky, or the two worlds. Several (Surya, Savitr, Pusan, Indra, Pra janva, and the Adityas) are lords of all that moves and is stationary.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;LJSuch common features tend to obscure what is essential, because in hymns of prayer and praise they naturally assume special prominence. Againr gods belonging to different departments, but having prominent functions in common, are apt to be approximated. [JThus Agni, primarily the god of terrestrial fire, dispels the demons of darkness with his lightwhile Indra, the aerial god of the thunderstorm, slays them with his lightning] Into the con ception of the fire-god further enters his aspect as lightning in the atmosphere. The assimilation is increased by such gods often being invoked in pairs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4 MYTHICAL PRIESTS AND HEROES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/4_MYTHICAL_PRIESTS_AND_HEROES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/4_MYTHICAL_PRIESTS_AND_HEROES/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;50&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Manu. As the appellation Manu or Manus is often used in the sense of man , there is sometimes an uncertainty as to when it has thevalue of a proper name in the RV. It appears to have the latter signification49- TUTELARY DEITIES. IV. MYTHICAL PRIESTS AND HEROES. 50. MANU. 139&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;nearly twenty times in the form of Manu and almost as often in that of Manus. Manu is five times styled a father, and in two of these passages more definitely as our father (2, 33^ &amp;amp;c.; cp. 9). Sacrificers are spoken of as the people (visafy) of Manus (4, 37x &amp;amp;c.) and Agni is said to abide among the offspring of Manu (i, 68 4). Manu was the institutor of sacrifice.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 ANIMALS AND INANIMATE OBJECTS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/5_ANIMALS_AND_INANIMATE_OBJECTS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/5_ANIMALS_AND_INANIMATE_OBJECTS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;59&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;General Traits. &amp;ndash; Animals enter to a considerable extent into the mythological creations of the Veda. There are still numerous traces surviving from a more primitive age, when the line dividing men from animals 10*&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;148 III. RELIGION, WELTL. WISSENSCH. u. KUNST. i A. VEDIC MYTHOLOGY.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;was not definitely drawn ( 65) and gods might be conceived as havinganimal forms also. The higher Vedic gods themselves being anthropomorphicin character, the supernatural beings of the Veda which have an animal formbelong to a lower order, being semi-divine only or demoniac according as the animal is useful to man, as the cow, or injurious, as the serpent. Moreover, just as man has attached to him various animals which are serviceable to him, so the great anthropomorphic gods are naturally surrounded by acelestial animal world of a similar character. Lastly, actual animals are in the ritual connected with mythological conceptions of the gods. They aresymbolical representatives intended only as an instrument for the time beingto influence the gods they in some respect resemble. This fetishistic pointof view is probably the faded remnant of a more primitive identification ofgods with visible objects. The part which such animal fetishes play in Vedictimes is, however, no longer great,, since the representation of deities byanimals conflicted with the higher conception prevailing of the gods as mightymen dwelling in heaven and coming invisibly to the sacrifice.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>6 DEMONS AND FIENDS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/6_DEMONS_AND_FIENDS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/6_DEMONS_AND_FIENDS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;67&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A. Asuras. Opposed to the beneficent gods is a body of malevolent beings called by various designations. Asura is throughout the Vedicliterature the name of the celestial demons who are regarded as the regularadversaries of the gods in their mythical conflicts and who only rarely appearas present foes of men (e. g. AV. 8, 65; KS. 8;16; 88 1 ). The term, however,occurs only a few times in the RV. with the later sense of demon. It is&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;there found only four times in the plural with this meaning. Indra is invokedto scatter the godless Asuras (8, 85 9). Otherwise they are only mentioned in the tenth book, always as opposed to the gods in general. The gods, it is said, smote the Asuras (10, i57 4;. Agni promises to devise a hymn by whichthe gods may vanquish the Asuras (10, 53 4). The gods are even said to have placed faith in the formidable Asuras (10, i5i 3 ). The word also occursthree times as the designation of an individual demon. Brhaspati is besoughtto pierce with a burning stone the heroes of the wolfish Asura (2, 3 o4). Indrashattered the forts of the crafty Asura Pipru (10, i383 ) and Indra-Visnu smotethe i oo ooo heroes of the Asura Varcin (7, 995). The sense of demon is also found in the epithet asurahan, Asura-slayer , \vhich occurs three timesand is applied to Indra (6, 22 4 ), to Agni (7, 13*), and to the Sun (10, i7o2). The older Rigvedic notion of the conflict of a single god with a single demon,mainly exemplified by Indra and Vrtra, gradually developed into that of thegods and the Asuras in general being arrayed against each other in twohostile camps. This is the regular view of the Brahmanas. A new andfrequent feature of the conflicts constantly described in these works is thatthe gods are worsted at the outset and only win by artifice. The mostnotable illustration of this notion is the myth of Visnu taking his three strides in the form of a dwarf on behalf of the gods1.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>7 ESCHATOLOGY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/7_ESCHATOLOGY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/7_ESCHATOLOGY/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;S 71. Disposal of the Dead. &amp;ndash;In the Vedic hymns there is little reference to death. When the seers mention it, they generally express a desire that it should overtake their enemies, while for themselves they wish long life on earth. It is chiefly at funerals that the future life engages their thoughts. Burial and cremation were concurrent. One hymn of the RV. (10, 1 6) describes a funeral by burning, and part of another (10, iS 10&amp;quot; 13)1, one by burial. The house of clay is also once spoken of (7, 891). Fathers burnt with fire and those not burnt with fire (i. e. buried) are referred to (10, i5 M ; AV. 18,, 2 34). But cremation was the usual way for the dead to reach the next world. The later ritual (cp. AGS. 4, i) practically knew only this method; for besides the bones and ashes of adults, only young children and ascetics were buried 2.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
