<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;vedic-mythology - macdonnell on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;vedic-mythology - macdonnell on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 INTRODUCTION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/1_INTRODUCTION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/1_INTRODUCTION/</guid>
      <description>i. Religion and mythology. Religion in its widest sense includes on the one hand the conception which men entertain of the divine or supernatural powers and, on the other, that sense of the dependence of human welfare on those powers which finds its expression in various forms of wor ship. Mythology is connected with the former side of religion as furnishing the whole body of myths or stories which are told about gods and heroes and which describe their character and origin, their actions and surroundings.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2: VEDIC CONCEPTIONS OF THE WORLD AND ITS ORIGIN</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/2_VEDIC_CONCEPTIONS_OF_THE_WORLD_AND_ITS_ORIGIN/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/2_VEDIC_CONCEPTIONS_OF_THE_WORLD_AND_ITS_ORIGIN/</guid>
      <description>Cosmology. - - The Universe, the stage on which the actions ofthe gods are enacted, is___regarded by the Vedic poets as divided into thethree domains 1 of earth, air or atmosphere, and heaven 2. The sky whenregarded as the whole space above the earth, forms with the latter the entireuniverse consisting of the upper and the nether world. The vault (ndkd) ofthe sky is regarded as the limit dividing the visible upper world from the&amp;amp;gt;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 THE VEDIC GODS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/3_THE_VEDIC_GODS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/3_THE_VEDIC_GODS/</guid>
      <description>General character and classification. Indefiniteness of out line and lack of individuality characterize the Vedic conception of the gods. This is mainly due to the fact that they are nearer to the physical pheno mena which they represent, than the gods of any other Indo-European people. Thus the ancient Vedic interpreter Yaska 1 (Nir. 7, 4) speaking of the nature of the gods, remarks that what is seen of them is not anthropomorphic at all, as in the case of the Sun, the Earth, and others.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4 MYTHICAL PRIESTS AND HEROES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/4_MYTHICAL_PRIESTS_AND_HEROES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/4_MYTHICAL_PRIESTS_AND_HEROES/</guid>
      <description>Manu. As the appellation Manu or Manus is often used in the sense of man , there is sometimes an uncertainty as to when it has thevalue of a proper name in the RV. It appears to have the latter signification49- TUTELARY DEITIES. IV. MYTHICAL PRIESTS AND HEROES. 50. MANU. 139 nearly twenty times in the form of Manu and almost as often in that of Manus. Manu is five times styled a father, and in two of these passages more definitely as our father (2, 33^ &amp;amp;c.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5 ANIMALS AND INANIMATE OBJECTS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/5_ANIMALS_AND_INANIMATE_OBJECTS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/5_ANIMALS_AND_INANIMATE_OBJECTS/</guid>
      <description>General Traits. &amp;ndash; Animals enter to a considerable extent into the mythological creations of the Veda. There are still numerous traces surviving from a more primitive age, when the line dividing men from animals 10* 148 III. RELIGION, WELTL. WISSENSCH. u. KUNST. i A. VEDIC MYTHOLOGY.
was not definitely drawn ( 65) and gods might be conceived as havinganimal forms also. The higher Vedic gods themselves being anthropomorphicin character, the supernatural beings of the Veda which have an animal formbelong to a lower order, being semi-divine only or demoniac according as the animal is useful to man, as the cow, or injurious, as the serpent.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>6 DEMONS AND FIENDS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/6_DEMONS_AND_FIENDS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/6_DEMONS_AND_FIENDS/</guid>
      <description>A. Asuras. Opposed to the beneficent gods is a body of malevolent beings called by various designations. Asura is throughout the Vedicliterature the name of the celestial demons who are regarded as the regularadversaries of the gods in their mythical conflicts and who only rarely appearas present foes of men (e. g. AV. 8, 65; KS. 8;16; 88 1 ). The term, however,occurs only a few times in the RV.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>7 ESCHATOLOGY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/7_ESCHATOLOGY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/vedic-mythology_macdonnell/7_ESCHATOLOGY/</guid>
      <description>S 71. Disposal of the Dead. &amp;ndash;In the Vedic hymns there is little reference to death. When the seers mention it, they generally express a desire that it should overtake their enemies, while for themselves they wish long life on earth. It is chiefly at funerals that the future life engages their thoughts. Burial and cremation were concurrent. One hymn of the RV. (10, 1 6) describes a funeral by burning, and part of another (10, iS 10&amp;quot; 13)1, one by burial.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
