<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The rise of yajña and</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2023-04-25_the-rise-of-yajna-and-kausika-exceptionalism/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2023-04-25_the-rise-of-yajna-and-kausika-exceptionalism/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The rise of yajña and Kauśika exceptionalism
Ritual classes The extant Vedic ritual is bifurcated into two domains the gṛhya (the household rites and rites of passage) and the śrauta (large-scale/grand rituals).
First, in operational terms, they are distinguished by the use of a single fire (the aupāsana) in the former and the three fires with the central vedi in the latter; the grander śrauta rites involve the construction of a more complex system of altars.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>shrauta ritualists 1900-2008- an approximate lower bound estimate</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2008-02-27_shrauta-ritualists-1900-2008-an-approximate-lower-/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Feb 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2008-02-27_shrauta-ritualists-1900-2008-an-approximate-lower-/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
I have seen a bunch of estimates by Kashikar et al, Kannan and via various personal contacts. Drawing from all of them I come up with some numbers. These numbers can only be considered the rough lower bound
Tamil Nad (smArta-s and srI-vaiShNavas): 145 (found also secondarily displaced to Kashi e.g. Purushottama Dravid, a great soma ritualist)
Kerala (nambUthiris): 125
Karnataka (mainly havayaka and some tulavas): 50
Andhra (mainly vaidIki smArta-s): 160</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the vedic sacrificial ritual and its Babylonian parallels</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2007-01-27_on-the-vedic-sacrificial-ritual-and-its-babylonian/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jan 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2007-01-27_on-the-vedic-sacrificial-ritual-and-its-babylonian/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The mlechCha orientalists Dumont and Albright pointed to certain similarities between the Vedic sacrificial ritual and that found in Babylon. We revisit this to investigate if flow of memes between Eurasian civilizations can throw any light on the date and time of cultural interactions.
ashvamedha The great ashvamedha, the high point of vedic ritual, definitely goes back to the early Indo-European past.+++(5)+++ In some form or the other it seen amongst different branches of Indo-Europeans, like the Celts, Romans, Germans Greeks, Iranians and Indo-Aryans.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The gotra-specific elements of the installation of the gArhapatya fire</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-09-25_the-gotra-specific-elements-of-the-installation-of-the-garhapatya-fire/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Sep 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-09-25_the-gotra-specific-elements-of-the-installation-of-the-garhapatya-fire/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
-The udgAtA starts singing the rathanthara and ya~jna-yaj~nIya sAman-s [The jaiminIyas recite their samans in a low inaudible voice on the occassion of this rite].
-The adhvaryu starts installing the gArhapatya from the fire he has just kindled with the araNi-s on the saMbhAra-s that he has laid down at the site of the gArhapatya altar. The saMbhAra-s comprise of the following dravya-s- the pArthiva set: 1) sand, 2) soil that is rich in salt, 3) soil from a rodent-excavated tunnel, 4) soil from a termite mound 5) soil dug by boars 6) sediment from the bed of a perennial lake 7) smooth pebbles 8) gold.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The sarpasattra: vedic and aitihasic.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-07-16_the-sarpasattra-vedic-and-aitihasic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-07-16_the-sarpasattra-vedic-and-aitihasic/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The sarpasattra as per the itihAsa was the gory sacrifice of janamejaya pArIkshita done to avenge the death of his father parIkShit by the sarpas. The itihAsa states that the interaction between the pANDus, yadus and the sarpa-s was a long-standing and complicated one. arjuna first fathers a son irAvAn, through the sarpa princes ulUpI, the daughter of kauravya, the son of dhR^itarAshTra airAvata. kR^iShNa devakIputra defeats a sarpa king kali~nga according to the harivaMsha on the yamuna.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>atharvaNic saMdhyopAsana vidhi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-06-06_atharvanic-samdhyopasana-vidhi/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-06-06_atharvanic-samdhyopasana-vidhi/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The practioners of the fourth veda are dying creed. As we may be amongst the very last of the practioners and some who are learning it in a recent revival do not known of how the atharvaNa saMdhya needs to be done we provide some details. As this is a common question asked by the atharvan revivalists, with time I hope to provide a detailed protocol of atharvan saMdhya, atharvan upAkarma and some other important para-vedic rites of the atharvan-s like the skanda yAga or the dhUrta homa.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>agnichayana Altars</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-01-23_agnichayana-altars/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-01-23_agnichayana-altars/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
A number of archaic altars shapes existed for the agnichayana of which the practical geometric knowledge is largely lost in the surviving shrauta tradition.
The most famous which are still performed are: 1) the broad winged ShaDpatrika shyenachiti or the gliding eagle altar with 6 feathered wings. There is a variant of this with wings entirely made of 6 rows of parallelogram bricks.
2) the drawn wing pa~Nchapatrika shyenachiti or the diving eagle altar with 5 feathered wings.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The vrAtya stoma</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-09-27_the-vratya-stoma/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-09-27_the-vratya-stoma/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The vratya stoma is described in the first 4 sections of the 17th chapter of the pa~nchaviMsha brAhmaNa. The stoma has been described as a means of admitting non-Aryans to the Aryan fold but this is not clear from the vedic text describing the rite. A summary of the brAhmaNa discourse is given below:
The vrAtya stoma’s frame tale goes thus. The devas went to svargo lokaH. The gaNas of the dreaded The god were left behind leading the life of vrAtyas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The rite of the solsticial day</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-12-17_the-rite-of-the-solsticial-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Dec 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-12-17_the-rite-of-the-solsticial-day/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The old solsticial rite of the Indo-Aryans is performed on the second last-last day of the year (mahAvrata). The description of the oldest version of the rite is seen in the pa~nchavimsha, aitareya and shA~NkhAyana brAhmaNa. The clearest explanations of the ritual actions are found in the shA~NkhAyana shruti. It appears to preserve some of the archaisms of the Proto-Indoeuropean form of the rite. It was literally round the clock and one requires considerable energy to perform it successfully.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The donkey sacrifice</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-12-12_the-donkey-sacrifice/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-12-12_the-donkey-sacrifice/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The shrauta sUtra of kAtyAyana and the pAraskara gR^ihya sUtra mention a peculiar rite namely the gardhabhejya or the donkey sacrifice. The context suggests that it is performed by a brahmachAri who has fallen to passion and had sex against the norms of a vedic student. The offerings were made into the unconsecrated fire with the puroDAsha cakes being cooked on the bare ground. The heart and the tongue and other parts of the donkey were offered into water.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recombination of meters</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-12-11_recombination-of-meters/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-12-11_recombination-of-meters/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
Circular permutation A technique of Chandas transformation is the circular permutation, which is used in the ShoDashin soma pouring. Here offerings of soma are made to indra with 5 specialized anuShTubh mantras called indra juShasva. They are derived from R^iks originally in the atharva veda in the rare and peculiar svarAj meter (shaunaka AV 2.5.1-3). The svarAj has a total of 34 syllables in a mantra.
5 svarATs The total of 5 svarAj mantras are derived by repeating the first R^ik 3 time, as is typical of a shastra recitation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rules for ritual eligibility</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-12-11_rules-for-ritual-eligibility/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-12-11_rules-for-ritual-eligibility/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
There is considerable debate about who is eligible for vedic rites. The shrauta sUtras, which are the authorities on the topic are quite clear about the matter, barring a few debatable points. kAtyAyana expounds these matters most clearly:
1.1.1 athAto.adhikAraH
Now we shall explain the eligibility for performing vedic rites.
1.1.2 falyuktAni karmANi
The rites are connected with specific results.
1.1.3 sarveShAMvisheShAt
Prima facie everyone is entitled vedic rites as no specification has been made in this regard.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The obscene formulae in the ashvamedha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-11-21_the-obscene-formulae-in-the-ashvamedha/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-11-21_the-obscene-formulae-in-the-ashvamedha/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The male participants (the priests and the bard) say:
ambe ambAlyambike na mA yabhati kashchana | sa sastyashvakaH | haye cha haye asau ||
Ladies (ambA, ambAli and ambikA) no one seems to have sex with me. The bad horse is sleeping.That is the horse and you are the mare princess.
The princess says the following anuShTubh (one of the dialogs ):
iyaM yakA shakuntikA .ahalamiti sarpati | AhataM gabhe pasu ni jalgulIti dhANikA ||</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The sacrifice of the Horse in the ashvamedha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-11-21_the-sacrifice-of-the-horse-in-the-ashvamedha/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-11-21_the-sacrifice-of-the-horse-in-the-ashvamedha/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
1) The adhvaryu takes the last drink of water to the horse and offers it with the formulae apAM peruH and agniH pashuH.
2) Then the yajur priests take fire around the 13 animal starting from the kapi~njala that are tied along with the stallion and then release them.
3) The horse is lead to a large piece of cloth spread on the ground on which a piece of gold is placed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Aryan mortuary rite</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-08-05_an-aryan-mortuary-rite/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Aug 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-08-05_an-aryan-mortuary-rite/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The pitR^imedha is a relatively obscure Aryan mortuary rite done an year or later after the death of an ancestor. It used to be performed in the height of summer, a new moon day or in the month of magha, usually choosing a nakShatra with a single star. The bones of the ancestor were brought in an urn and placed on a couch. The urn was wrapped in an unwashed cloth and the living descendents and their women folk go around the urn 3 times as the vINA and other musical instruments are played.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vedic human sacrifice</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2003-08-11_vedic-human-sacrifice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2003 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2003-08-11_vedic-human-sacrifice/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
The Indo-Aryan kshatriyas performed a peculiar rite called the puruSha-medha that has been spoken of by Indians in hushed tones. Much like the cow sacrifice and horse sacrifice, which people have tried to explain away as not implying a real slaying, the human sacrifice has also been denied. However, there is really no point being coy about our past, based on modern notions and standards.
The puruSha-medha was a rare rite, as it finds very infrequent mention in Indic literature.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adhvaryava-dominance</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/Adhvaryava-dominance/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/Adhvaryava-dominance/</guid>
      <description>The rise of yaj~na in the Indo-Iranian world and Adhvaryava dominance
Text # syllables yajña yajña/1000 syl Taittiriya-samhitä 252950 1052 4.16 Rgveda 384165 601 1.56 Atharvaveda (vulgate) 204649 307 1.50 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comments_on_puruShamedha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/comments_on_puruShamedha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/comments_on_puruShamedha/</guid>
      <description>[TW17]
Srauta sutras and even brahmanas mention that men are not killed in purushamedha. But maybe in pre samhita yajnas and para-vaidika traditions may have continued it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>pravargya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/pravargya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/pravargya/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
The parvargya rite is an exalted vedic sacrifice performed by an Arya to the ashvins and offers a glimpse of the fusion of the two ancient ritual streams of the pre-R^igvedic past. One component of it is the ancient gharma rite to the Ashvins instituted by the bhR^igus under the great atharvan chyavAna.
ChyavAna was revived from decrepitude and disease by the ashvins and went on to win sukanya the daughter of shAryAti and accordingly in their honor offered the great sacrifice of congealed milk (tereti pAl in Dravidian).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>tAntrika acceptance</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/tAntrika-acceptance/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/tAntrika-acceptance/</guid>
      <description>There were all kinds of accommodations &amp;amp; hybrid positions all the way from bhaTTa jayanta&amp;rsquo;s time to today. The saiddhAntika-s like aghorashiva deshika insist that their votaries should observe vaidika rituals. Closer to our time a kaula like bhAskararAya also held the title of makhIndra. The choLa kings with saiddhAntika dIkSha performed shrautayAga-s.
In the end many of the great tAntrika system&amp;rsquo;s collapsed during the Mohammedan assault but the shrauta ritualists retained quite a degree of their vitality.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>vRkta-barhiSh</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/vRkta-barhiSh/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/vRkta-barhiSh/</guid>
      <description>(Source: https://threader.app/thread/1463382047389622274)
counts of vR^iktabarhiSh
maNDala 1 &amp;hellip; 5 maNDala 3 &amp;hellip; 3 maNDala 5 &amp;hellip; 3 maNDala 6 &amp;hellip; 1 maNDala 8 &amp;hellip; 11 maNDala 9 &amp;hellip; 1 maNDala 10 &amp;hellip; 2 clearly the kANva-s have a much greater propensity to us this phrase than others.
Then vaishvAmitra-s &amp;amp; atri-s. Even in maNDala 1 of the 5, 1 is by the vaishvAmitra madhuChandas &amp;amp; 4 are by kANva-s include the founder of the clan kaNva himself.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
