<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The rise of yajña and</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2023-04-25_the-rise-of-yajna-and-kausika-exceptionalism/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2023-04-25_the-rise-of-yajna-and-kausika-exceptionalism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2023/04/25/the-rise-of-yajna-and-kausika-exceptionalism/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The rise of yajña and Kauśika exceptionalism&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;ritual-classes&#34;&gt;Ritual classes&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The extant Vedic ritual is bifurcated into two domains the gṛhya (the household rites and rites of passage) and the śrauta (large-scale/grand rituals).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;First, in operational terms, they are distinguished by the use of a single fire (the aupāsana) in the former and the three fires with the central vedi in the latter; the grander śrauta rites involve the construction of a more complex system of altars.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>shrauta ritualists 1900-2008- an approximate lower bound estimate</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2008-02-27_shrauta-ritualists-1900-2008-an-approximate-lower-/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Feb 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2008-02-27_shrauta-ritualists-1900-2008-an-approximate-lower-/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2008/02/27/shrauta-ritualists-1900-2008-an-approximate-lower-bound-estimate/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I have seen a bunch of estimates by Kashikar et al, Kannan and via various personal contacts. Drawing from all of them I come up with some numbers. These numbers can only be considered the rough lower bound&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Tamil Nad (smArta-s and srI-vaiShNavas): 145 (found also secondarily displaced to Kashi e.g. Purushottama Dravid, a great soma ritualist)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Kerala (nambUthiris): 125&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Karnataka (mainly havayaka and some tulavas): 50&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Andhra (mainly vaidIki smArta-s): 160&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the vedic sacrificial ritual and its Babylonian parallels</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2007-01-27_on-the-vedic-sacrificial-ritual-and-its-babylonian/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jan 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2007-01-27_on-the-vedic-sacrificial-ritual-and-its-babylonian/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2007/01/27/on-the-vedic-sacrificial-ritual-and-its-babylonian-parallels/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The mlechCha orientalists Dumont and Albright pointed to certain similarities between the Vedic sacrificial ritual and that found in Babylon. We revisit this to investigate if flow of memes between Eurasian civilizations can throw any light on the date and time of cultural interactions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;ashvamedha&#34;&gt;ashvamedha&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The great ashvamedha, the high point of vedic ritual, definitely goes back to the early Indo-European past.+++(5)+++ In some form or the other it seen amongst different branches of Indo-Europeans, like the Celts, Romans, Germans Greeks, Iranians and Indo-Aryans. But as every other Indo-European tradition its pristine version with all the meaning-laden archaisms is found only in the vedic world and it continued to remain the symbol of the victorious Hindu kings (like pushyamitra shunga performing it after destroying the yavana-s in a great battle on the sindhu or vIra hammira performing it after destroying “1000s of turuShkas”).+++(5)+++&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The gotra-specific elements of the installation of the gArhapatya fire</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-09-25_the-gotra-specific-elements-of-the-installation-of-the-garhapatya-fire/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Sep 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-09-25_the-gotra-specific-elements-of-the-installation-of-the-garhapatya-fire/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/09/25/the-gotra-specific-elements-of-the-installation-of-the-garhapatya-fire/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;-The udgAtA starts singing the rathanthara and ya~jna-yaj~nIya sAman-s&#xA;[The jaiminIyas recite their samans in a low inaudible voice on the&#xA;occassion of this rite].&lt;br&gt;&#xA;-The adhvaryu starts installing the gArhapatya from the fire he has just&#xA;kindled with the araNi-s on the saMbhAra-s that he has laid down at the&#xA;site of the gArhapatya altar. The saMbhAra-s comprise of the following&#xA;dravya-s- the pArthiva set: 1) sand, 2) soil that is rich in salt, 3)&#xA;soil from a rodent-excavated tunnel, 4) soil from a termite mound 5)&#xA;soil dug by boars 6) sediment from the bed of a perennial lake 7) smooth&#xA;pebbles 8) gold. The dru set: wooden pieces of 1) ashvattha 2) udumbara&#xA;3) palAsha 4) shami 5) vika~NkaTa 6) fulgurites or a tree struck by&#xA;lighting and 7) lotus leaves. He may at least get 5 of each of these.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The sarpasattra: vedic and aitihasic.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-07-16_the-sarpasattra-vedic-and-aitihasic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-07-16_the-sarpasattra-vedic-and-aitihasic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/07/16/the-sarpasattra-vedic-and-aitihasic/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The sarpasattra as per the itihAsa was the gory sacrifice of janamejaya&#xA;pArIkshita done to avenge the death of his father parIkShit by the&#xA;sarpas. The itihAsa states that the interaction between the pANDus,&#xA;yadus and the sarpa-s was a long-standing and complicated one. arjuna&#xA;first fathers a son irAvAn, through the sarpa princes ulUpI, the&#xA;daughter of kauravya, the son of dhR^itarAshTra airAvata. kR^iShNa&#xA;devakIputra defeats a sarpa king kali~nga according to the harivaMsha&#xA;on the yamuna. Then arjuna the pANDu and kR^ishna the yadu attack&#xA;khANDavaprastha the kingdom of the takShaka the king of the nAga-s and&#xA;defeat him to seize his land, with the vedic deities from indra to rudra&#xA;fighting on the side of the sarpas. The pANDus build their new capital&#xA;there. In the great war the half-sarpa son of arjuna comes to fight on&#xA;his side and is killed, whereas takShaka tries to aid karNa in killing&#xA;arjuna. After the war the sarpa-s avenge themselves on parIkShit, called&#xA;the grandson of arjuna, and kill him. Finally, this is avenged by&#xA;janamejaya in his sarpa-sattra where he massacres the sarpas. The&#xA;sarpa-s are saved from complete extinction by deva indra who sends the&#xA;brAhmin AstIka to end the rite of janamejaya. In addition this battle,&#xA;the bhArgava utanka fights takShaka in the quest for the earrings of the&#xA;queen.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>atharvaNic saMdhyopAsana vidhi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-06-06_atharvanic-samdhyopasana-vidhi/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-06-06_atharvanic-samdhyopasana-vidhi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/06/06/atharvanic-samdhyopasana-vidhi/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The practioners of the fourth veda are dying creed. As we may be amongst&#xA;the very last of the practioners and some who are learning it in a&#xA;recent revival do not known of how the atharvaNa saMdhya needs to be&#xA;done we provide some details. As this is a common question asked by the&#xA;atharvan revivalists, with time I hope to provide a detailed protocol of&#xA;atharvan saMdhya, atharvan upAkarma and some other important para-vedic&#xA;rites of the atharvan-s like the skanda yAga or the dhUrta homa. Here is&#xA;an outline for the saMdhya&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>agnichayana Altars</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-01-23_agnichayana-altars/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-01-23_agnichayana-altars/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/01/23/agnichayana-altars/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A number of archaic altars shapes existed for the agnichayana of which&#xA;the practical geometric knowledge is largely lost in the surviving&#xA;shrauta tradition.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The most famous which are still performed are: 1) the broad winged&#xA;ShaDpatrika shyenachiti or the gliding eagle altar with 6 feathered&#xA;wings. There is a variant of this with wings entirely made of 6 rows of&#xA;parallelogram bricks.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;2) the drawn wing pa~Nchapatrika shyenachiti or the diving eagle altar&#xA;with 5 feathered wings.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;3) The pIthachiti- In the form a square with 3 rectangular paths leading&#xA;out on 3 of the sides (this is nearly extinct, only a single Andhra&#xA;ritualist, whose patnI is also a qualified soma ritualist, knows this.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;4) The puruShachiti- in the form of a standing man with arms extended to&#xA;the sides.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5) The kUrmachiti- in the form of a turtle&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The vrAtya stoma</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-09-27_the-vratya-stoma/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-09-27_the-vratya-stoma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/09/27/the-vratya-stoma/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The vratya stoma is described in the first 4 sections of the 17th&#xA;chapter of the pa~nchaviMsha brAhmaNa. The stoma has been described as&#xA;a means of admitting non-Aryans to the Aryan fold but this is not clear&#xA;from the vedic text describing the rite. A summary of the brAhmaNa&#xA;discourse is given below:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The vrAtya stoma’s frame tale goes thus. The devas went to svargo lokaH.&#xA;The gaNas of the dreaded The god were left behind leading the life of&#xA;vrAtyas. They reached the spot where the devas had ascended to svarga&#xA;but they neither found the stoma nor the Chandas by means of which they&#xA;may join them. Then the devas told the maruts deliver the attendents of&#xA;rudra the needful so that they may reach us. To them the maruts&#xA;delivered that stoma with the 16 mantra chant which is the cryptic&#xA;anuShTubh.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The rite of the solsticial day</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-12-17_the-rite-of-the-solsticial-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Dec 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-12-17_the-rite-of-the-solsticial-day/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2004/12/17/the-rite-of-the-solsticial-day/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The old solsticial rite of the Indo-Aryans is performed on the second&#xA;last-last day of the year (mahAvrata). The description of the oldest&#xA;version of the rite is seen in the pa~nchavimsha, aitareya and&#xA;shA~NkhAyana brAhmaNa. The clearest explanations of the ritual actions&#xA;are found in the shA~NkhAyana shruti. It appears to preserve some of&#xA;the archaisms of the Proto-Indoeuropean form of the rite. It was&#xA;literally round the clock and one requires considerable energy to&#xA;perform it successfully.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The donkey sacrifice</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-12-12_the-donkey-sacrifice/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-12-12_the-donkey-sacrifice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2004/12/12/the-donkey-sacrifice/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The shrauta sUtra of kAtyAyana and the pAraskara gR^ihya sUtra mention a&#xA;peculiar rite namely the gardhabhejya or the donkey sacrifice. The&#xA;context suggests that it is performed by a brahmachAri who has fallen to&#xA;passion and had sex against the norms of a vedic student. The offerings&#xA;were made into the unconsecrated fire with the puroDAsha cakes being&#xA;cooked on the bare ground. The heart and the tongue and other parts of&#xA;the donkey were offered into water. The prashitra offering made to iDA&#xA;by the brahmA priest was the phallus of the donkey. This primitive rite&#xA;does not seem to have any echoes elsewhere in the Indo-Aryan world, but&#xA;by its characteristics may be a late surviving archaism from the time&#xA;when the early Indo-Aryans roved the central Asiatic steppes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recombination of meters</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-12-11_recombination-of-meters/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-12-11_recombination-of-meters/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2004/12/11/recombination-of-meters/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;circular-permutation&#34;&gt;Circular permutation&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A technique of Chandas transformation is the circular permutation, which is used in the ShoDashin soma pouring. Here offerings of soma are made to indra with 5 specialized anuShTubh mantras called indra juShasva. They are derived from R^iks originally in the atharva veda in the rare and peculiar svarAj meter (shaunaka AV 2.5.1-3). The svarAj has a total of 34 syllables in a mantra.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;5-svarats&#34;&gt;5 svarATs&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The total of 5 svarAj mantras are derived by repeating the first R^ik 3 time, as is typical of a shastra recitation. Thus we get 34*5=170 syllables.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rules for ritual eligibility</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-12-11_rules-for-ritual-eligibility/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-12-11_rules-for-ritual-eligibility/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2004/12/11/rules-for-ritual-eligibility/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There is considerable debate about who is eligible for vedic rites. The&#xA;shrauta sUtras, which are the authorities on the topic are quite clear&#xA;about the matter, barring a few debatable points. kAtyAyana expounds&#xA;these matters most clearly:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1.1.1 athAto.adhikAraH&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now we shall explain the eligibility for performing vedic rites.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1.1.2 falyuktAni karmANi&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The rites are connected with specific results.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1.1.3 sarveShAMvisheShAt&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Prima facie everyone is entitled vedic rites as no specification has&#xA;been made in this regard.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The obscene formulae in the ashvamedha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-11-21_the-obscene-formulae-in-the-ashvamedha/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-11-21_the-obscene-formulae-in-the-ashvamedha/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2004/11/21/the-obscene-formulae-in-the-ashvamedha/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The male participants (the priests and the bard) say:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ambe ambAlyambike na mA yabhati kashchana | sa sastyashvakaH | haye&#xA;cha haye asau ||&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ladies (ambA, ambAli and ambikA) no one seems to have sex with me. The&#xA;bad horse is sleeping.That is the horse and you are the mare princess.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The princess says the following anuShTubh (one of the dialogs ):&lt;br&gt;&#xA;iyaM yakA shakuntikA .ahalamiti sarpati | AhataM gabhe pasu ni&#xA;jalgulIti dhANikA ||&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The sacrifice of the Horse in the ashvamedha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-11-21_the-sacrifice-of-the-horse-in-the-ashvamedha/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-11-21_the-sacrifice-of-the-horse-in-the-ashvamedha/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2004/11/21/the-sacrifice-of-the-horse-in-the-ashvamedha/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1) The adhvaryu takes the last drink of water to the horse and offers&#xA;it with the formulae apAM peruH and agniH pashuH.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;2) Then the yajur priests take fire around the 13 animal starting from&#xA;the kapi~njala that are tied along with the stallion and then release&#xA;them.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;3) The horse is lead to a large piece of cloth spread on the ground on&#xA;which a piece of gold is placed. The the horse is strangulated by&#xA;another large piece of cloth bound around its muzzle by the shamitar.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;4) The adhvaryu offers the paripashavayA oblations as the horse is being&#xA;killed and as it dies 3 oblations of ghee are made with prAnAya ;&#xA;apAnAya; vyAnAya + svAhA.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5) At the direction of the neShTA priest the royal ladies chant the&#xA;mantras beginning with namaste amba.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6) Then royal ladies move towards the horse and go around it 3 times&#xA;from left to right and recite the mantra gaNAnAntva gaNapatiM. Then the&#xA;go 3 times from right to left and chant priyAnAm tva. Then they go 3&#xA;times from left to right reciting nidhInAM tvA.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;7) Then the emperor, the chief queen the mahiShi and the adhvaryu utter&#xA;the purificatory incantation for the dead horse. Then the mahiShi&#xA;recites Aham ajAni and lies besides the dead horse.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;8) The adhvaryu then covers the two with the large sheet of cloth with&#xA;the formula svarge loke.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;9) Then then phallus of the horse is excised and the mahiShi takes it on&#xA;her lap reciting the formula vR^iShA vAjI.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;10) The emperor looks at the horse and recites the formula utsakthyA.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;11) Then the adhvaryu, the brahmA, the udgAtA, the hotA and the sUtA&#xA;bard of the emperor, each, recite one of the five sexually explicit&#xA;formulae beginning with “yakA asakau..” directed at the royal ladies and&#xA;their brAhmaNa female companions. At the end of each hymn and they&#xA;recite the formula “haye cha haye asau —–” and utter the name of the&#xA;ladies. The kshatriya women and their companions reply by reciting the&#xA;sexually explict hymns paired with with the “yakA asakau..” series.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;12) Then the mahiShI stands up and the priests in unison recite the&#xA;surabhimati hymns to purify their mouths.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Aryan mortuary rite</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-08-05_an-aryan-mortuary-rite/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Aug 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-08-05_an-aryan-mortuary-rite/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2004/08/05/an-aryan-mortuary-rite/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The pitR^imedha is a relatively obscure Aryan mortuary rite done an year&#xA;or later after the death of an ancestor. It used to be performed in the&#xA;height of summer, a new moon day or in the month of magha, usually&#xA;choosing a nakShatra with a single star. The bones of the ancestor were&#xA;brought in an urn and placed on a couch. The urn was wrapped in an&#xA;unwashed cloth and the living descendents and their women folk go around&#xA;the urn 3 times as the vINA and other musical instruments are played.&#xA;They fan the urn with their upper garments as they go around. These&#xA;circumambulations are performed in the initial, middle and last part of&#xA;the night. The day the ritual is done also includes a &lt;strong&gt;feast&lt;/strong&gt; and&#xA;distribution of food along with a &lt;strong&gt;provision for dancing, singing and&#xA;and playing on musical instruments.&lt;/strong&gt; Some food is also dedicated to the&#xA;urn of the dead ancestor.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vedic human sacrifice</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2003-08-11_vedic-human-sacrifice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2003 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/2003-08-11_vedic-human-sacrifice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2003/08/11/vedic-human-sacrifice/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Indo-Aryan kshatriyas performed a peculiar rite called the&#xA;puruSha-medha that has been spoken of by Indians in hushed tones. Much&#xA;like the cow sacrifice and horse sacrifice, which people have tried to&#xA;explain away as not implying a real slaying, the human sacrifice has&#xA;also been denied. However, there is really no point being coy about our&#xA;past, based on modern notions and standards.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The puruSha-medha was a rare rite, as it finds very infrequent mention&#xA;in Indic literature. Typically, it was a exaggeration of the ashvamedha&#xA;that was occasionally conducted by victorious kings. In the&#xA;puruSha-medha rite the rival king was captured and brought as a prisoner&#xA;by the sacrificing king. The rite lasted a whole year. At the end of it&#xA;he was smothered and sacrificed with the deployment of the puruSha&#xA;sUkta. Along with him, his animals may also be sacrificed and immolated&#xA;as offerings. The pUru king, ayutanAyi is said to have performed the&#xA;puruSha-medha rite with his enemies. In many ways this gory rite was&#xA;reminiscent of the rite of Julius Caesar when he slew some detractors of&#xA;his along with the sacrificial horse. The puruSha-medha may have been&#xA;seen as a more formal mode of eliminating ones foes in the context of a&#xA;pious ritual, as compared to a bland execution.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adhvaryava-dominance</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/Adhvaryava-dominance/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/Adhvaryava-dominance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The rise of yaj~na in the Indo-Iranian world and Adhvaryava dominance&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;table&gt;&#xA;  &lt;thead&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th&gt;Text&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th&gt;# syllables&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th&gt;yajña&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th&gt;yajña/1000 syl&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/thead&gt;&#xA;  &lt;tbody&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Taittiriya-samhitä&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;252950&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;1052&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;4.16&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Rgveda&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;384165&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;601&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;1.56&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Atharvaveda (vulgate)&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;204649&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;307&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;1.50&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BarhiSh</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/barhiSh/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/barhiSh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/blog_supplement/status/1869282894654685604&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;vedic-use&#34;&gt;Vedic use&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Some variations in the Indo-Iranian world of the use of barhiSh:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Indo-Aryans use darbha grass as barhiSh.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;they strewed (dhAtupATha: stR^I) long blades of this grass as the seat of the gods.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Among them, the atri-s seems to have used wool alongside the grass in certain rituals.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Certain clans seem to have used it more than others.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;barhiSh is mentioned 100 times in the RV, but the collection of vAmadeva gautama mentions it only once, which is atypically rare for a collection of that size. The context suggests that these gautama-s used it only in the animal sacrifice.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comments_on_puruShamedha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/comments_on_puruShamedha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/comments_on_puruShamedha/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/blog_supplement/status/849800893201612800&#34;&gt;TW17&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Srauta sutras and even brahmanas mention that men are not killed in purushamedha. But maybe in pre samhita yajnas and para-vaidika traditions may have continued it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>pravargya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/pravargya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/pravargya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.oocities.org/somasushma/pravargya.html&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The parvargya rite is an exalted vedic sacrifice performed by an Arya to the ashvins and offers a glimpse of the fusion of the two ancient ritual streams of the pre-R^igvedic past. One component of it is the ancient gharma rite to the Ashvins instituted by the bhR^igus under the great atharvan chyavAna.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ChyavAna was revived from decrepitude and disease by the ashvins and went on to win sukanya the daughter of shAryAti and accordingly in their honor offered the great sacrifice of congealed milk (tereti pAl in Dravidian). Then the bhArgava dadhichi, gained secreted vidyas from the ashvins who had fixed on him the head of the horse, hence he worshipped them as the gods of medicine.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>tAntrika acceptance</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/tAntrika-acceptance/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/tAntrika-acceptance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There were all kinds of accommodations &amp;amp; hybrid positions all the way from bhaTTa jayanta&amp;rsquo;s time to today. The saiddhAntika-s like aghorashiva deshika insist that their votaries should observe vaidika rituals. Closer to our time a kaula like bhAskararAya also held the title of makhIndra. The choLa kings with saiddhAntika dIkSha performed shrautayAga-s.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the end many of the great tAntrika system&amp;rsquo;s collapsed during the Mohammedan assault but the shrauta ritualists retained quite a degree of their vitality. It is remarkable that trika is almost gone in South India but still shrautayAga-s are done.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>vRkta-barhiSh</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/vRkta-barhiSh/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/kalpaH/shrautam/articles/MT_lekhAH/vRkta-barhiSh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://threader.app/thread/1463382047389622274&#34;&gt;https://threader.app/thread/1463382047389622274&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;counts of vR^iktabarhiSh&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;maNDala 1 &amp;hellip; 5&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;maNDala 3 &amp;hellip; 3&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;maNDala 5 &amp;hellip; 3&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;maNDala 6 &amp;hellip; 1&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;maNDala 8 &amp;hellip; 11&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;maNDala 9 &amp;hellip; 1&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;maNDala 10 &amp;hellip; 2&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;clearly the kANva-s have a much greater propensity to us this phrase than others.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Then vaishvAmitra-s &amp;amp; atri-s. Even in maNDala 1 of the 5, 1 is by the vaishvAmitra madhuChandas &amp;amp; 4 are by kANva-s include the founder of the clan kaNva himself. Thus totally the kANva-s have 15; vaishvAmitra-s 4 thereafter. Thus, the twisted grass though universal among v1s todaymight have had its origins in a specific sub-locale among the Arya-s probably close to the kANva heartland.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
