<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;2 A Historical Overview of the Delta on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/1_The_Godavari_Delta/2_A_Historical_Overview_of_the_Delta/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;2 A Historical Overview of the Delta on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/1_The_Godavari_Delta/2_A_Historical_Overview_of_the_Delta/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 Early Centuries</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/1_The_Godavari_Delta/2_A_Historical_Overview_of_the_Delta/1_Early_Centuries/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/1_The_Godavari_Delta/2_A_Historical_Overview_of_the_Delta/1_Early_Centuries/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Due to the constant self-landscaping of the two rivers archeologists obtain  few results from combing within the Godavari or Krishna deltas. Inland  well west of the deltas, great ash mounds of burnt cow dung reveal tempo rary settlements of Neolithic cattle herders. Also dotted through the interior  are numerous megalithic tombs. It is estimated that Telugu developed as a  discrete Dravidian spoken language in Andhra early in the first millennium  bce. No historical records have been found, however, earlier than Sanskrit and  Prakrit inscriptions of the second century bce, and inscriptions in Telugu do  not occur for another half millennium or more.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2 Contending Dynasties of Regional Kings</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/1_The_Godavari_Delta/2_A_Historical_Overview_of_the_Delta/2_Contending_Dynasties_of_Regional_Kings/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/1_The_Godavari_Delta/2_A_Historical_Overview_of_the_Delta/2_Contending_Dynasties_of_Regional_Kings/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The boasts of “southern” supremacy by Satakarni I  and Kharavela would  no doubt have been ridiculed by kings and chieftains farther south. The  Ceras (Keralas) on the west coast, the Colas who gave their name to the  east coast (Coromandal, the mandala of Colas), and the Pandyas in between,  competed for power over the territory during the early centuries ce, a pot&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;pourri of kingdoms controlling villages and extracting revenue not only in  Tamil Nadu, “land of the Tamils,” but also parts of the northern Deccan and  up the Kalinga coast. Romila Thapar has aptly dubbed such contention a  “see-sawing of dynasties” with relatively equal military strength repeatedly  replacing one another in the same region. Hermann Kulke and Dietmar  Rothermund extend the image to “triangular contests” since conflicts were  often more than one on one.4&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 The Emergence of Telugu Literature</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/1_The_Godavari_Delta/2_A_Historical_Overview_of_the_Delta/3_The_Emergence_of_Telugu_Literature/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/1_The_Godavari_Delta/2_A_Historical_Overview_of_the_Delta/3_The_Emergence_of_Telugu_Literature/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the last few centuries bce Tamil speakers began to compose poetry and  prose that foreshadowed Sangam era classics of the first three centuries ce.  Gradually Tamil had taken on vocabulary and themes from Sanskrit. By the  close of the first millennium ce two more Dravidian languages, Telugu and  Kannada, followed suit with literary forms and sizable input from Sanskrit.  In the eleventh century Telugu classical poetry received its template from  the reworking of the first two and a half books of the Sanskrit Mahabharata  by Nannaya, a task continued on palm leaves in the thirteenth century by  Tikkana, another formidable and creative poet.11 Although both Nannaya  and Tikkana were Brahmans, Veda pandits or Brahmans as a class did not  monopolize the proliferation of Telugu literary works. Also in the thirteenth  century, Palkuri Somanatha produced the Basava Purana collection of leg ends of Virasaiva (Lingayata) saints who rejected Vedic textual authority, class  and caste hierarchy, funerary rites, and the whole enterprise of sacrifice. One  saint declared that his dog could chant the Vedas better than Brahman pan&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4 The Kakatiya Dynasty at Warangal</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/1_The_Godavari_Delta/2_A_Historical_Overview_of_the_Delta/4_The_Kakatiya_Dynasty_at_Warangal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/1_The_Godavari_Delta/2_A_Historical_Overview_of_the_Delta/4_The_Kakatiya_Dynasty_at_Warangal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;until 1322&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Warangal, midway between middle stretches of the Godavari and Krishna riv ers, had become the hub of the Kakatiya dynasty from the eleventh to the  beginning of the fourteenth centuries as the center of political control moved  inland from the coast. The most ambitious of its kings was Ganapati who  ruled more than sixty years c.1198–1262, corralling the two deltas (the enlarged  meaning of “Vengi”) within his kingdom. Subjugation of the coast occurred  on Ganapati’s way south to reduce Kanci in Tamil Nadu, one of his many victo rious battles having been fought at Pithapuram in the Godavari Delta.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 A New Religion, Culture, and Polity: Islam Enters the Deccan</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/1_The_Godavari_Delta/2_A_Historical_Overview_of_the_Delta/5_A_New_Religion_Culture_and_Polity_Islam_Enters_the_Deccan/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/1_The_Godavari_Delta/2_A_Historical_Overview_of_the_Delta/5_A_New_Religion_Culture_and_Polity_Islam_Enters_the_Deccan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The grandson of Ganapati was Pratapa Rudra who ruled successfully, by most  accounts, from 1289 until the Delhi Sultan Ala-ud-din dispatched armies to  subdue the Kakatiya region. Sieges were laid, bargains were struck, but finally  the well-fortified city of Warangal and abundant Kakatiya armies were no  match for the battle-hardened cavalry tactics and leadership of Ulugh Khan.  Warangal fell in 1322 to the fifth successive Sultanate invasion and a captive  king Pratapa Rudra was under transport toward Delhi when he died near the  Namada River, perhaps by his own hand.15 It is noteworthy that Marco Polo&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>6 Vijayanagara c 1346–1564</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/1_The_Godavari_Delta/2_A_Historical_Overview_of_the_Delta/6_Vijayanagara_c_13461564/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/1_The_Godavari_Delta/2_A_Historical_Overview_of_the_Delta/6_Vijayanagara_c_13461564/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A powerful rival to both the Hindu Kakatiyas of Warangal and the Muslim  Bahmani kingdoms arose in Karnataka as Vijayanagara, one of the largest for tifications in Asia with an eventual ten square miles within massive walls.  Lasting for almost three centuries, the “city of victory” dominated the center  of the southern peninsula from Hampi on the Tungabhadra River, a southern  tributary of the Krishna. In 1327, Muhammad Tughluq conquered the Kampili  dynasty that had succeeded the Hoysalas in Karnataka and thereby completed&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>7 Arrival of the Europeans</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/1_The_Godavari_Delta/2_A_Historical_Overview_of_the_Delta/7_Arrival_of_the_Europeans/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/1_The_Godavari_Delta/2_A_Historical_Overview_of_the_Delta/7_Arrival_of_the_Europeans/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Greek and Roman merchant ships in the last centuries bce and early centuries  CE most certainly viewed and perhaps explored the Krishna and Godavari del tas along the Coromandal coast. European colonization of the subcontinent,  however, did not begin until well after Vasco da Gama landed four ships at  Calicut on the Kerala coast in 1498. The early arriving Portuguese concen trated on India’s Arabian Sea coast. A century later the east coast on the Bay of  Bengal was the target of Dutch, Danish, and French traders as well as the even tually all-encompassing English.22 Dutch merchant ships dominated trade in  the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries but the English slowly caught up  and then surpassed them. In the seventeenth century the English East India  Company established from modest origins three seaports, Madras, Bombay,  and Calcutta, each to become one of the famous megalopolises of modern  India, Chennai, Mumbai, and Kolkata, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>8 Domesticating the Delta</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/1_The_Godavari_Delta/2_A_Historical_Overview_of_the_Delta/8_Domesticating_the_Delta/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/1_The_Godavari_Delta/2_A_Historical_Overview_of_the_Delta/8_Domesticating_the_Delta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Everywhere on domestic, business, and civic walls, and especially on trees at  crossroads and river banks, there are posters and statues of divine beings— Hanuman, Ganesa, all possible avatara of Devi, Siva, or Visnu, and the occasional  god-man or god-woman stepping back from history into myth—Shirdi Sai Baba  or Sarada Devi, for example. Images of two male figures with historical focus  are ubiquitous in the delta, as indeed they are in most of India. One is Gandhi,  seated cross-legged or in mid-stride, staff in resolute hand, spectacles prominent  on a wizened face. The other is the Dalit and neo-Buddhist hero B. R. Ambedkar  posed stiffly in white shirt, red tie, and improbable blue suit, his arm pointing  out the hope of progress somewhere on the horizon. But in the water-rich deltas  of the Godavari and Krishna, as nowhere else in the subcontinent, a third male  figure may be seen in landscape statuary, either in standing pose alone in the flat  space of a paddy field or in the saddle of a spirited brown stallion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>9 Creating a Modern Telugu Language State</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/1_The_Godavari_Delta/2_A_Historical_Overview_of_the_Delta/9_Creating_a_Modern_Telugu_Language_State/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/knipe_vedic-voices/1_The_Godavari_Delta/2_A_Historical_Overview_of_the_Delta/9_Creating_a_Modern_Telugu_Language_State/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The historian of Andhra, P. Raghunanda Rao, credits English education for  intellectual and social reforms leading to the “awakening of Andhra” from  medieval stupor.31 The University of Madras originated in 1857 and by 1873 a  government college for the Godavari Delta was established in Rajahmundry.  Labeled by the Veda pandits huna-vidya, the practice of the Huns (a  heavy-handed reference to British colonials), the Brahmans were wary of an  educational system that interfered with traditional Vedic culture.32 The English  curriculum and its enlightenment ideology did in fact produce rapid change.  A battery of educated and energetic reformers arose and coastal Andhra con tributed a fair share. The combination of traditional learning and superior  social status of Brahmans was an advantage. According to Kenneth Jones,  “between 1876–86 Brahmans accounted for 73% of all successful candidates  in Madras University.”33&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
