<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;06 Sāmaveda on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/06_sAmaveda/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;06 Sāmaveda on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/06_sAmaveda/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Singing in Villages and Forests</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/06_sAmaveda/01_Singing_in_Villages_and_Forests/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/06_sAmaveda/01_Singing_in_Villages_and_Forests/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Sāmaveda exhibits two types of chant: &lt;em&gt;grāma-geya-gāna&lt;/em&gt;, ‘to be sung in the village’ and &lt;em&gt;araṇya-geya-gāna&lt;/em&gt;, ‘to be sung in the forest’. The former are accessible and relatively popular. The latter are complex and regarded as extremely powerful. &lt;em&gt;Araṇya&lt;/em&gt; is sometimes translated as ‘wilderness’ for that reason. The Sāmavedic perspective of the forest as something dangerous, alien and replete with powerful chants, supports the idea that they belonged to an indigenous lineage that had long been settled. Did they picture the Rigvedins, who had given them the words for their songs, as alien beings that had emerged from the forest where they were roaming about with their powerful mantras? Or was it the other way round, since even a Rigvedic composer evoked the image of a traveller, isolated and frightened because he was lost in a forest (&lt;em&gt;Two: Archaeology and the Oral Tradition&lt;/em&gt;)? That Rigvedic poem, however, belongs to a late circle (the tenth) and merely shows that by that time the Rigvedins were just as settled as the Sāmavedins. All we can say is that those were golden times (subsequently called the &lt;em&gt;Satyayuga&lt;/em&gt; or ‘Age of Truth’) at least in one respect: our planet was still replete with forests.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
