<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;10 Upaniṣads on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/10_upaniShads/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;10 Upaniṣads on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/10_upaniShads/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Generalities</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/10_upaniShads/01_Generalities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/10_upaniShads/01_Generalities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Vedic or Classical Upaniṣads are sometimes called Vedānta or ‘End (&lt;em&gt;anta&lt;/em&gt;) of the Veda’. The term occurs first after the end of the Vedic period, in the Muṇḍaka Upaniṣad (fourth to third centuries BCE?), when the Upaniṣads were looked upon as a separate group and it was felt that the ritualistic Veda had reached its ‘end’, the English word that is not only etymologically related to Sanskrit &lt;em&gt;anta&lt;/em&gt; but has its same double connotation: the final portion of a thing, and also its goal, ultimate aim or destination. Not only aficionados of the Upaniṣads stress the latter meanings, they are the only ones that are acceptable because the composers of the Upaniṣads did not adopt a historical perspective. But the term Vedānta has an entirely different meaning also. It refers to a group of Indic philosophies that look at the Upaniṣads as their source of inspiration, not necessarily the only one. One of the earliest of these is the philosophy of Bhāskara who lived around 800 CE. Many of his works have been lost and he left no school. More or less contemporary with him is Śaṇkara, also a follower of the Upaniṣads, to whose theories Bhāskara made vitriolic references. But Śaṇkara eclipsed him and became the most famous philosopher of India. His Vedānta is called A-dvaita Vedānta because its position is ‘non-dual’. Another Vedānta is the Viśiṣṭādvaita Vedānta of Rāmānujā (twelfth century CE) who defends a ‘qualified non-dualism’, yet another is the Dvaita Vedānta of Madhvācārya (thirteenth century CE) who accepts dualism. And there are others.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Karma, Rebirth and Life after Death</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/10_upaniShads/02_Karma_Rebirth_and_Life_after_Death/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/10_upaniShads/02_Karma_Rebirth_and_Life_after_Death/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The most celebrated Upaniṣadic speaker and philosopher was Yājñavalkya. The debate, recorded or imagined by the composer of the BĀU, took an unexpected turn when he was asked by Ārthabhāga what happens when a man dies. He took a number of steps and his first question was: Where does the breath of a dead person go? Yājñavalkya gave the kind of down-to-earth answer that is typical of him: ‘His breaths do not depart of him. They accumulate within his body, causing it to swell and become bloated.’ Many further questions follow, but they are not rebuffed as we shall see. Ārthabhāga asks where go speech, mind, hearing, body, self, hair, blood and semen when a man dies. Yājñavalkya provides answers to all those questions, but Ārthabhāga persists and asks: what happens to the person himself? Yājñavalkya replies: ‘My friend, we cannot talk about this in public. Take my hand, Ārthabhāga; let’s discuss this in private.’ So they leave, and talk about it. What did Yājñavalkya and Ārthabhāga talk about? They talked about:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Karma, Jñāna and Bhakti</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/10_upaniShads/03_Karma_jnAna_and_Bhakti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/10_upaniShads/03_Karma_jnAna_and_Bhakti/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Upaniṣads are not all like the famous dialogue between Yājñavalkya and Ārthabhāga. They continue from the Brāhmaṇas and Āraṇyakas and contain, therefore, the usual mixture of pearls and dung. A striking specimen of the latter is crisply formulated by the CU (1.3.3):&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The interval between exhalation and inhalation is suspended breath. Suspended breath is language.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I am not familiar with any theory of language that is more succinct than this. Armand Minard, the greatest expert of the Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa since Eggeling, paid it a kind of compliment which I translate from the French:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 ‘In That Way You Are’</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/10_upaniShads/04_In_That_Way_You_Are/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/10_upaniShads/04_In_That_Way_You_Are/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We have encountered several meanings of brahman. It means sublime ‘language’ in the early Rigveda and the brahman priest is an officiant attached to the Atharvaveda. In the Upaniṣads, brahman is something entirely different. It cannot be easily defined and its frequent translation as ‘absolute’ does not contradict the fact that it must sometimes be translated as ‘language’. The word &lt;em&gt;ātman&lt;/em&gt; is even more intractable. Etymologically related to an Indo-European word for ‘breath’ (German &lt;em&gt;Athem&lt;/em&gt;, Dutch &lt;em&gt;adem&lt;/em&gt;), it is used in Vedic and Sanskrit as a reflexive pronoun for all three genders and persons, as in English: ‘he did it himself’, ‘they went out by themselves’, ‘the book itself says so’. In English, one cannot say ‘the self’ just as one cannot say ‘the we.’ ‘The I’ is only used by philosophers (psychologists prefer ‘the ego’). ‘The self’ and ‘the Self’ occur only in English writings on Indian philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Dhyāna, Meditation and the End of the Veda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/10_upaniShads/05_dhyAna_Meditation_and_the_End_of_the_Veda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/10_upaniShads/05_dhyAna_Meditation_and_the_End_of_the_Veda/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Whether or not we are brahman and whether or not the ethical dimensions of the &lt;em&gt;karma&lt;/em&gt; doctrine are Upaniṣadic, the karma doctrine is related to something else that is Indic and goes beyond it: techniques of concentration or meditation (&lt;em&gt;dhyāna&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;abhidhyāna&lt;/em&gt;). They are Vedic because they occur in the early Upaniṣads, but they are found elsewhere, for example in Jainism and Buddhism, where they are referred to by different terms and are often specific meditations on the cycle of rebirth. They spread through Buddhism over large parts of Asia first and of the world now. There is no general agreement about what meditation is and what it is not, but in some senses it is monotheistic and probably universal. It is not something to be discussed in the present context. What is the Vedic context?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 The Two Main Contributions of the Upaniṣads</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/10_upaniShads/06_The_Two_Main_Contributions_of_the_upaniShads/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/2_THE_VEDAS/10_upaniShads/06_The_Two_Main_Contributions_of_the_upaniShads/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If I were asked to point at the greatest contributions of the Upaniṣads and the Vedānta, I would mention two. The first is public discussions and rational dialogues without restraints (e.g., ‘political correctness’). Rational discussions never existed between the two Jaina sects, who did not talk to each other, but survived in Indian philosophy, in the Buddhist Councils, in the Council of Lhasa that allegedly took place between Indian and Chinese Buddhists, and among Tibetans, though no longer in Tibet itself. In India, they continued to exist in religious contexts, at least until half a century ago in Kanchipuram, when I looked up at the leaders of the two main Viśiṣṭādvaita schools or sects, arguing with each other, high above me on elephant back and surrounded by throngs of followers. The name of one was Prativādam Bhayaṃkaram, ‘Terrible Refutation’. Logic and religion combined in one fantastic spectacle. What a lesson for the twenty-first century!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
