<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;13 Secrets of the Sadas on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/13_Secrets_of_the_Sadas/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;13 Secrets of the Sadas on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/13_Secrets_of_the_Sadas/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Soma Sequences</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/13_Secrets_of_the_Sadas/01_Soma_Sequences/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/13_Secrets_of_the_Sadas/01_Soma_Sequences/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;All the larger Soma rituals are characterized by sequences of rites which I have called ‘Soma Sequences’. Each consist of a Sāmaveda chant (&lt;em&gt;stuti&lt;/em&gt;), a Rigveda recitation (&lt;em&gt;śastra&lt;/em&gt;), Soma offerings and Soma drinking by the ritual patron and some of his priests. The Soma offerings are made out in the open, on the offering altar at the eastern end of the ritual arena. The other three rites take place behind the walls of the Sadas. Its position is shown in Figure 16. But it is only now that we will get an inkling of the significance of the Adhvaryu’s statement, which is issued at the beginning of each sequence: ‘You are the bed for coupling Rik and Sāman for the sake of procreation!’ Procreation of what?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Moving South and East</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/13_Secrets_of_the_Sadas/02_Moving_South_and_East/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/13_Secrets_of_the_Sadas/02_Moving_South_and_East/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Part I emphasized links of Vedic civilization with Central Asia and the Near East. Part II showed how that civilization moved south-east, adapted itself on the subcontinent to a new environment, interacted with other cultures and began to settle down. Ritual, history and geography illustrate how those settlements moved further east. Figure 16 shows how the Ritual Arena for the Soma ceremonies corresponds to the historical map of Central Asia including Vedic India. The officiating priests are not aware of those correspondences and they remain unexpressed by the large majority of our sources.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Never Seeing Eye To Eye</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/13_Secrets_of_the_Sadas/03_Never_Seeing_Eye_To_Eye/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/13_Secrets_of_the_Sadas/03_Never_Seeing_Eye_To_Eye/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One might simplify Vedic ritual by describing it as a cooperative effort of priests from three Vedas: the Rigvedins recite, the Sāmavedins chant and the Yajurvedins perform rites. Some Rigvedins may be descendants through the male line of composers of the Rigveda. The Sāmavedins took their verse and set them to music, following melodies their ancestors had sung on the words of another language. There were rivalries between the two groups and our ritual sources show that the Sāmavedins were often discriminated against.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Facing All Directions</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/13_Secrets_of_the_Sadas/04_Facing_All_Directions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/13_Secrets_of_the_Sadas/04_Facing_All_Directions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Baudhāyana described the ancient paradigm: ‘Facing east (&lt;em&gt;prāṇmukham&lt;/em&gt;), turning to the right (&lt;em&gt;pradakṣiṇam&lt;/em&gt;), invested with the sacred thread, he performs the divine rites.’ In the course of the development of the Śrauta ritual, between say 1100 and 900 BCE, a paradigm change took place. ‘Facing east’ was replaced by ‘facing all directions’ (&lt;em&gt;sarvatomukham&lt;/em&gt;). It is explicitly specified for the &lt;em&gt;Agnicayana&lt;/em&gt; altar where, on each layer, the bricks are arranged and consecrated in specific directions. What applies to the directions of bricks applies to the directions of the officiants themselves. Baudhāyana repeats it five times in his Śrauta Sūtra formulations, at the beginning of each of the five layers and with the help of two statements which I shall put between single quotes. They quote metarules (&lt;em&gt;Fourteen: Sūtra: Vedic Sciences&lt;/em&gt;) (between double quotes) as is their wont. First he says: ‘Metarules like “he deposits them toward the east, he deposits them toward the west” denote the series of bricks when there are groups.’ Then he continues: ‘Metarules like “he deposits it toward the east, he deposits it toward the west” indicate that the agent who does the depositing faces in that direction.’ He mentions east and west explicitly but it is obvious throughout that it applies to all the four directions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Epilogue</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/13_Secrets_of_the_Sadas/05_Epilogue/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/staal/discovering_vedas/3_ANALYSING_THE_VEDAS/13_Secrets_of_the_Sadas/05_Epilogue/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of the Vedic period, rivals appeared on the horizon: Buddhism was one to which we return in Part V; literacy another. In the long run, Buddhism did not stay in India. Books bound in India continue to fall apart but the Vedic Oral Tradition is still there.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As for the Sadas, it would have been easy for Rig- and Sāmavedins to face each other. One solution would be to face all directions. Another, for each party to continue facing its preferential directions but face each other by sitting in a circle. It is a common practice in the round-table conferences of contemporary politics and looks like the most transparent solution, but it has another drawback: it is a display of insularity because the participants hide behind their backs something even more important—the wide open universe. Thus they resemble two-dimensional beings crawling within a circle.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
