<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;APPENDIX on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/APPENDIX/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;APPENDIX on वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/APPENDIX/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A THE AGE OF THE AVESTA AND THE RIGVEDA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/APPENDIX/A_THE_AGE_OF_THE_AVESTA_AND_THE_RIGVEDA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/APPENDIX/A_THE_AGE_OF_THE_AVESTA_AND_THE_RIGVEDA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;AN effort definitely to establish the date of the reform of Iranian religion by Zoroaster has been made by J. Hertel,1 who seeks to trace the activity of the prophet from 559-522 B.C., a result of much importance in view of the probability that no very great interval of time can intervene between the Rigveda and the Gathas of the Avesta.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Stress is naturally laid by Hertel on the fact that the religion of the Persians as described by Herodotos contains nothing specifically Zoroastrian, while it accepts much that Zoroaster rejected, especially the direct veneration of nature gods, and the animal sacrifice; moreover Herodotos records the drunkenness of the Persians, which may be connected with the Haoma offering, the fear of defiling fire or water, and the practice of the Magoi of permitting the bodies of the dead to be torn by birds or beasts, matters which are not recognized in the Gathās. Hence it may be concluded that Zoroaster&amp;rsquo;s activity fell at no great date before the reign of Xerxes I. Nor can we form any reasoned judgement to the contrary on the strength of the view of Xanthos of Lydia, a contemporary of Artaxerxes I (465-424 B.C.), who places Zoroaster 6,000 years 2 before the expedition of Xerxes, or the slightly variant account of Aristotle which makes him 6,000 years before the death of Plato.3&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>B THE SACRIFICE OF PURUŞA AND THE ORIGIN OF THE WORLD</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/APPENDIX/B_THE_SACRIFICE_OF_PURUA_AND_THE_ORIGIN_OF_THE_WOR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/APPENDIX/B_THE_SACRIFICE_OF_PURUA_AND_THE_ORIGIN_OF_THE_WOR/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;H. Gūntert1 has traced the common possession over an area extending from Germany, through the Thraco-Phrygian area, to the Indo-Iranians of a number of mythological elements, which are preserved for us in complex and contaminated forms in the religious records of these peoples. The first of these ideas is that of the origin of mankind and the world from the sacrifice of a primeval being, an idea suggested by the great potency which primitive religious thought ascribes to the bloody sacrifice. This is preserved for us in the legend of the sacrifice of Purusa and of Ymir, whose original character he strongly defends against suggestion of Christian influence; it is reflected also in the strange, though late, legend of Odin who records how for nine nights he hung on a trec, wounded by the spear, dedicated to Odin, himself to himself. The action of the god in permitting himself to be sacrificed is one of free will, motived by the desire to create the world and establish the race of men. Yama, he holds, is such a god; the difficult passage of the Rigveda, x. 13. 4, he explains as a reference to a deliberate decision by Yama to sacrifice himself for the sake of mankind; it is as a sacrificer of himself that Yama performs the feat of finding the hidden Agni,3 who is the mediator in the sacrifice between the offerer and the gods. Later we find in Iran the conception of some sin in the primitive being, as in Yima, and, when the human sacrifice became antiquated, the creator as in the legend of Mithra slays a bull, not a human being.4&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>C THE ARYAN CONCEPTION OF THE HEAVEN</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/APPENDIX/C_THE_ARYAN_CONCEPTION_OF_THE_HEAVEN/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/APPENDIX/C_THE_ARYAN_CONCEPTION_OF_THE_HEAVEN/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;J. Hertel claims that in India and Iran alike we find the conception of the heaven as a great stone building, filled with light, through whose doors, the sun and the stars, the light of heaven shines upon men. For this view is adduced the reference in the Rigveda to the palace of Varuna with a thousand doors, which is asserted to be none other than the heaven with its stars. For Iran there is the narrative in Vendidad ii, which has long passed as the Iranian version of the legend of the flood, but in which we should rather see the account of Yama&amp;rsquo;s reign in the golden age and of the way in which he conveyed the first to die through the opening of the heaven, i.e. the sun, into the heaven of light. It is, however, true that this original legend of the Magian faith has been altered in the form in which we have it, since it could not, as it stood, be made consistent with the Zoroastrian doctrine of the fate of the dead. The Vara mentioned in the Vendidad is to be compared with the Vedic Vala,8 which is none other than the closed firmament which the lord of the heaven of light, Brhaspati, or sometimes Indra, cleaves in order to set free the ruddy kine, i.e. the stars. Yet a further confirmation of the new interpretation of the Vendidad is seen in an obscure verse of the Rigveda, which is made to yield the sense that Manu adorned with flames the door of the heaven of Indra. By yet another conjecture we are to see in Rigveda x. 14. 2 (Yama as the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>D THE DRINK OF IMMORTALITY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/APPENDIX/D_THE_DRINK_OF_IMMORTALITY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/APPENDIX/D_THE_DRINK_OF_IMMORTALITY/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;G. Dumézil in his Le Festin d&amp;rsquo;Immortalité seeks to establish, despite the silence of the Veda, the existence of an Indo-European myth of the winning of the drink of immortality. From the epic legend of the churning of the ocean he derives a myth which tells how, in fear of death, the gods took counsel as to procuring a drink to preserve them from it. Visṇu advises them to churn the occan for it, and, after coming to terms with the demons, and obtaining the assent of the god of the ocean, they accomplish their end, producing the Amṛta, and other good things, including Lakṣmi; a poison engendered in the churning is drunk by Śiva, whose neck thus becomes blue. The Asuras, however, steal the Amṛta, and demand Lakṣmi; Viṣṇu-Nārāyaṇa, in female guise, accompanied by Nara, in similar costume, goes to them, and wins them over to give him the Amṛta, which then he bears back to the gods. They proceed to drink the nectar; the demon, Rahu, found among them is decapitated by Visnu, and the fall of his body produces much commotion of the earth. A fight follows, in which the Asuras, defeated by the gods, are banished to the earth and the waters, and the gods remain in definitive possession of the drink.4&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>E THE INDO-EUROPEAN FIRE CULT</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/APPENDIX/E_THE_INDO-EUROPEAN_FIRE_CULT/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/APPENDIX/E_THE_INDO-EUROPEAN_FIRE_CULT/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;625&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;That fire should be regarded in its own right as a divine power, worthy of worship, appears so natural that it is only reasonable to recognize such worship as Indo-European. The sanctity of Agni in the Rigveda is, of course, especially that of the fire regarded as the recipient of sacrifice and the bearer of oblations, but it seems wholly unjustifiable to suggest that his sanctity arose from his nature as the sacrificial fire; rather he was the recipient of offerings as sacred in his own right.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>F CREMATION AND BURIAL</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/APPENDIX/F_CREMATION_AND_BURIAL/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/APPENDIX/F_CREMATION_AND_BURIAL/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The view that cremation was a distinctively Indo-European form of disposal of the dead cannot be supported by any evidence of value. There is abundant proof that burial is at least as ancient a method, and, indeed, it is possible to hold that it was Indo-European, while burning was introduced after that period among the different peoples either independently or by borrowing. The Vedic evidence, as has been shown, proves that burial was early; Herodotos&amp;quot; ascribes the usage to the Persians, while the Magoi, possibly by religious conservatism, preserved the method of exposure; burial he also&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>G THE DRAVIDIAN ELEMENT IN INDIAN THOUGHT</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/APPENDIX/G_THE_DRAVIDIAN_ELEMENT_IN_INDIAN_THOUGHT/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/APPENDIX/G_THE_DRAVIDIAN_ELEMENT_IN_INDIAN_THOUGHT/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The desire to prove that Dravidian or pre-Dravidian peoples affected deeply Vedic thought and life is natural, and is supported by the generally accepted view that the population of India is predominantly Dravidian or at least of non-Indo-European origin. It is true, however, that in the absence of any real certainty of the physical characteristics of the Indo-Europeans this belief cannot be made the subject of strict proof. Assuming, however, the validity of the doctrine, there remains the question whether the invaders were essentially responsible for the Vedic religion and philosophy, imposing a superior culture on inferior races, or whether the process as regards culture was reversed; instances of analogical cases can be easily adduced. Here again, however, we must remember that we have no satisfactory evidence of the relative numbers of the invaders and the earlier settlers; we are left in this matter wholly to conjecture.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>H PYTHAGORAS AND PARMENIDES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/APPENDIX/H_PYTHAGORAS_AND_PARMENIDES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH/meta/articles/keith/APPENDIX/H_PYTHAGORAS_AND_PARMENIDES/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;U. von Wilamowitz-Moellendorff holds that in the doctrine of Philolaos the five bodies in the sphaira are the four elements, which compose it, with as fifth râs opaipas Akós in the sense of that which gives the sphaira its form, the nature of that something being only vaguely felt; in the Timaios Plato makes the world-soul perform an analogous function. He insists that it is to Aristotle we must look for the conception of the ether as a fifth element, for he evidently deliberately claims this as his own invention. The assertion of Xenokrates which ascribes the doctrine to Plato he explains either as referring to a casual adoption of the idea by Plato, which he did not carry farther, or to his accepting an innovation of Aristotle&amp;rsquo;s. Doubtless ascription to Plato or Aristotle of the precise form of the doctrine is legitimate, but there is force in the view of Rostagni that already in the carly Pythagorean view, if we accept the traditional accounts, the basis of the doctrine existed. The fifth element is the reptéxov which is described also as the other as well as the aπepov Tvevua, while on the immaterial side we have the world spirit as the power which binds together the mass. In any event there is no close&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
